Today we will talk about wholesome and unwholesome thoughts.
Our mind is like an artist that can paint the entire world.
From this the five skandhas arise as well as all phenomena.
Our mind is a great artist that creates the universe.
We can either paint a beautiful life for ourselves or we can paint a miserable life, it's all
up to us.
In this class, we will learn 11 wholesome thoughts and 10 unwholesome thoughts in order
to transform our lives with our thoughts.
Let's first look at the 11 wholesome thoughts.
Number one is faith.
We must have faith in karma, that's called the conventional truth.
If we have wholesome thoughts, it will create good karma.
If we have unwholesome thoughts, it will create negative karma.
Believing in the law of causation, that's the basis of our cultivation.
On the other hand, we should believe in the ultimate truth, it's that beyond all the cause
and effect, there is emptiness as the essence of all things.
This emptiness is our pure one mind, the pure nature.
So regardless if you're wholesome or unwholesome, this pure mind never changes, so by believing
and balancing these two truths, our mind will be very strong and powerful, then we
can conquer all doubts, worries, and fears in our cultivation.
Number two is diligence.
We need to put in effort in our cultivation to avoid all evil and cultivate all that is
good.
This diligence is based on strong courage and strength.
This courage and strength actually comes from our belief.
The stronger our faith, the more diligent we will be.
It's not the busier you are, the more diligent you are.
Sometimes a person who's very diligent, but if you look at him, he's very relaxed and
not doing much because he's actually quietly working on his defilements.
That is true diligence.
Number three is modesty.
Number four is shame.
These two often go together.
Modesty is when we are humble and respectful.
It's when we are humble and respectful.
We want to learn from all the virtuous people.
Shame is when we're embarrassed of our wrongdoings.
So these two are both self-reflection.
So when things go wrong, do not blame others or the outside situation.
Always go inward and reflect on ourselves, but this reflection is not a strong sense
of guilt or remorse because those would be defilement and unwholesome.
We want this modesty and shame to be positive and wholesome.
We want to learn from all the virtuous people.
Just note that we're always learning and life is a growing experience.
Number five is non-greed.
Number six is non-anger.
Number seven is non-ignorance.
Greed, anger, and ignorance that's the three poisons.
Without them, that's the three good roots.
That's a basis for all goodness.
Non-greed is when we are content.
We are no longer seeking or craving, we are no longer living our lives.
This is the basis for our goodness.
for things that were not supposed to crave for. There were two monks in the Song Dynasty.
They were fleeting in the wartime. Each one of them was carrying a backpack.
Monk A noticed that Monk B kept looking into his own bag. When Monk B went to the bathroom,
Monk A looked into the Monk B's bag and found a pure gold hairpin. Monk A threw away
this precious metal. When Monk B came back, he was looking for his prized possession.
Monk A told him, We are both monks. We are seeking liberation. How can you still hold
on to contamination? I already threw away that poisonous snake. Monk B realized his
craving, and his fall, and changed his way. So do not be greedy.
Number six is non anger. When things don't go our way, can we not be angry? There was
an ugly small ghost.
ghost that went up to the heavens of the 33 gods and actually sat on the throne. All the
heavenly beings were yelling at her but surprisingly the more they yelled at her, the prettier,
stronger and bigger she got. The king of the heavens of the 33 gods came and saw the ghost
but he was not angry at her at all. He was very polite and very respectful. He just repeated
three times, I am the king of the heavens of the 33 gods. As he was repeating, surprisingly
the ghost shrunk and got uglier and soon she disappeared. Why? Because this ghost symbolizes
our anger. The more you are angry, the more you feel it, the stronger it gets. But if
you don't be angry and be respectful and compassionate, this anger will subside and can no longer
control us.
7. Non-ignorance. Understand the Four Noble Truths. Know what is the cause of our suffering.
For example, we don't want to be grumbling about the past or worrying about the future
or think about all the irrelevant things that cannot be helpful. Only focus on relevant
thoughts that are wholesome, that can improve and transform our lives. So don't dwell
on emotional drawbacks. That's ignorance.
8. Tranquility. That's when we're having serenity. The calmness of our body and mind
because of the absence of defilement. We feel this lightness and carefree blissfulness.
9. Vigilance. This is strong self-discipline. So no matter what, we should remember the
danger of samsara and the fault of birth and death.
10. Self-discipline. This is the most important part of self-discipline. We should remember the danger of samsara and the fault of birth and death.
We don't want to be lazy because we're having short-lived pleasant experiences right now.
We always want to guard and protect our mind. That's vigilance.
10. Equanimity. This is letting go. We have to let go of all our emotional attachments.
Even when you're praying for the sick person, you have to let go. In your meditation, say
to yourself,
Everyone is subject to one's own karma. You'll feel this neutral feelings and indifference.
This is actually the best state of mind when you're not attached and this is actually true
compassion.
11. Harmlessness. We don't want to hurt anyone with our thoughts or with our actions. This
world is already full of suffering and danger. We want people to feel safe when they're with
us.
We know we will not harm them. We will not take advantage of them. We should synchronize
ourselves with these 11 wholesome thoughts. That's how we transform our lives for the
better.
Now let's look at the 10 unwholesome thoughts.
1. Hatred. At the moment of rage when unpleasant situations are happening.
2. Vengeance. When we hold on to the hatred afterwards.
3. Taxation. When the vengeance develops into our anger.
4. Rebellion. When we hold on to the hatred afterwards.
5. Rebellion. When we hold on to the hatred afterwards.
6. Rebellion. When we hold on to the hatred afterwards.
When we hold on to our bodily action and speech, we become very violent.
So all three of these are based off of anger.
Number 4 is concealment. When we try to hide our mistakes, because we
try to protect our image. When we're doing this, we are actually breaking more precepts
and we're just lying to ourselves.
Number 5 is deceiving. It's kind of like concealment but this is straight out pretending
and lying.
So the intention is to lie.
ar müssen aufhören.
lie to others. On the outside, we look very virtuous and wholesome, but the inside is
full of darkness and defilements. Number six is flattery, adulation, brown-nosing to the
boss and the superior to gain favors. Actually, kids do this a lot. They are very sweet in
front of the parents and the teacher just to get what they want, but it's actually very
unwholesome. Number seven is pride, when we're drunken by our own ego, self-infatuated because
of our good looks or success or accomplishments or skills, but this is actually the cause
of suffering and samsara. Number eight is harmfulness, malice, and hostility. This can
be very subtle. For example, I just have a dog. She's so annoying. That is already being
harmful.
Number nine is jealousy, when we cannot bear the success and the accomplishment of others.
This is also because of our selfishness and anger. Number ten is parsimony, when we are
stingy with our money and the dharma because we don't want to share. We just want to hug
it up for ourselves, our family, or our temple. This is all because of our selfishness. These
ten are called minor or secondary.
Okay.
These are all unwholesome mental functions, but they're actually the strongest. So they
break down into the three poisons. Hatred, vengeance, vexation, harmfulness, and jealousy.
That's from anger. Concealment, deceiving, and flattery. Those three are based on our
ignorance. Pride and parsimony, that's based on our greed. So these are all because of
the three poisons.
We need to look into our mind. Be mindful of our thoughts, be mindful when we're having
unwholesome thoughts or wholesome thoughts. We do not want to judge them, just know to
let go of the unwholesome thought and synchronize with the wholesome thought. That's how we
transform our life and purify our minds.
There was a spiritual leader. His name was William Dyer. He passed away a few years ago.
When he was just an infant, his father left him, taking care of his health. His name just
appeared right now, on the tree calls to him Geb chambers. Him you start off inpecting
more compassion. You find yourself personally affected by karmic affects. You see karmic affects,
He grew up in a series of orphanages so he grew up hating his father and the hate grew
stronger and stronger as he got older.
He became an alcoholic, he was overweight and he had really bad relationships.
Everything was not going right.
So until he was 34, he decided to go look for his father.
His father already passed away for 10 years.
He wanted to see his grave.
Finally, he went to Mississippi and found his grave.
He was there for 3 hours.
At the beginning, he was still very angry but at the end, he had an epiphany.
He finally said to his father, I forgive you for everything.
From now on, I only send you love.
From that moment on, Dr. Wayne Dyer transformed his life.
He became a spiritual leader that helped millions grow spiritually.
So we can all transform our lives just by knowing our thoughts and letting go of our
defilements.
In Buddhism, we call it transforming afflictions into bodhi or we call it transforming deluded
consciousness into wisdom.
This is the meaning of life.
This is what we're trying to do to purify our minds with these wholesome thoughts.
So we say pure mind, pure land.
If we want to go to the pure land, we should always have pure thoughts.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community