Today we are going to talk about Eight Schools of Buddhism.
We are going to incorporate the Eight Schools of Buddhism with the Tiantai's teaching of
the Three-Fold Contemplation.
The first one we are going to talk about is the Tiantai School founded by Master Zhi Yi.
Tiantai Buddhism is based on the Lotus Sutra which talks about the single vehicle that
everyone is supposed to be a Buddha and everyone has a Buddha nature to begin with.
We have to find our true nature by the Three-Fold Meditation, the Void Meditation, Unreal Meditation
and Ming Meditation.
Void Meditation is to see that all dharmas arise from condition therefore it doesn't have
any intrinsic nature in itself.
So let go of all your attachment to everything because they are void of a true essence.
So first you understand Void Meditation, understand emptiness, then you have to understand we
still have Unreal Existence.
Everything is empty but we still have to live this life.
We still have to be a Bodhisattva and live the best we can to help all sentient beings.
If you can balance the Void and the Unreal Meditation, the Ultimate Truth and the Conventional
Truth, then that is the Middle Way, the Ming.
This is your true nature.
Now let's look at the Prajna School of Buddhism.
Bodhisattva Nagarjuna.
He is the founder of Prajna, which is the School of Emptiness of Mahayana Buddhism.
He has this famous line, For dharmas arising from conditions, I affirm that they are empty.
They are conventional but yet indicate the meaning of the Middle Way.
The Three-Fold Meditation are actually derived from this verse, All dharmas arise from condition
because it's from cause and effect.
It's rising and ceasing, it's always changing, therefore all conditions arising, they must
be empty.
They are made up of different conditions, different factors.
Of course they are changing, of course they don't have a permanent self, of course there's
not a real me in any of these conditions arising.
That's the Void Meditation, but they do have conventional existence.
Bodhisattva Nagarjuna.
We still have a life to live in this physical appearance, that's the Unreal Meditation.
You just have to live the life the best you can without being attached to anyone or anything.
Everything is Unreal, you are living a dream life.
But make it the best dream that you can to help all sentient beings and bring out your
great compassion.
Then it will be the Middle Way.
We are not dwelling on the Middle Way.
We are not dwelling on emptiness or existence.
We are reaching the Middle Way, our true pure mind.
Number three is the Yogacara, which means consciousness only school of Buddhism.
Of course this is also about the mind, the threefold contemplation.
We talk about everything in terms of the three natures.
One is the fully conceptualized nature.
This is our discrimination.
Our conceptual mind is actually empty.
We don't have this discriminating mind.
Other dependent nature, that's all the conventional existence of our life right now.
We still have to live this life that is dependent on all conditions.
Our body, family, work, society, they still exist.
You have to be a bodhisattva, appreciate, love everyone.
But not attached to anyone.
Or anything.
If you are detached from this world, be a bodhisattva, then you will reach the fully
accomplished nature, which is your true suchness, the mean.
It's all just your own mind.
So everything is based on this threefold meditation.
Number four is the Huayen school of Buddhism, based on the flower adornment sutra, or we
call it the Aventasaka school of Buddhism.
This is the threefold meditation.
This is about the world of the Buddha, the ten dharma rounds.
It's all created by our own mind.
Because the Buddha's mind is perfect, that's why they live in the perfect world.
That's the world of Huayen.
It's also talking about this mind being void, unreal, and mean, but it has its own names
in this Huayen school of Buddhism.
The void meditation is called contemplation.
It's contemplation that the emptiness is devoid of any attributes.
Because everything is empty, it doesn't have any real attributes.
Nothing has an intrinsic nature in itself.
Everything you see, including this body, your thoughts, they have no real essence.
Why attach to your opinion?
Why attach to everything that you think is yours?
Nothing is yours because the concept of the self is empty.
I'm not going to talk about the concept of the self.
But I understand the Vibe Meditation is the basis of being enlightened.
The Unreal Meditation is called the Contemplation that phenomenon and noumenon are unobstructed.
Phenomenon is everything that's existing.
The conventional truth.
The Noumenon is the emptiness.
The absolute truth, but they are integrated as one.
For a Bodhisattva.
A Bodhisattva lives in muha, which means emptiness.
A creation of EBputim.
It means taking one rice clean is a hiện living world.
A bread.
So to speak, it means taking one rice clean.
That means taking one rice clean.
live in this world of phenomena but they understand emptiness. That's why there is no obstruction.
That means there is no interference. You can live in this world, be a bodhisattva, have
a great wonderful life without being deluded, without having defilements. It's just you
have to believe in it so there's no hindrance of living out your true Buddha nature. The
Ming meditation is called contemplation about universal integration. At the end, the whole
universe is your mind. You are in me, I am in you. That's the Buddha mind. Everyone
is connected with you, even a mosquito. Anybody and anything, they are all interconnected
universally in this one mind. That is the Ming meditation.
The first four schools of Buddhism is based on the teaching of Buddhism. The last four
is based on the actual practice. Number five, the Naya, which means holding precepts. Some
people, they focus their whole life on holding precepts, the moral regulations Buddha set
for us. It has three pure precepts. Basically, to do no evil, to do good, to do good, to
save all beings. A bodhisattva, they hold these three precepts. That's all they think
about every day. So the void meditation, understanding emptiness, that's how you do good deeds. You
do good deeds without having a self. Not what I can get in return, that's real goodness.
To save all sentient beings, the unreal meditation is a bodhisattva. Like a doctor, a doctor,
dispersing medicine according to the illness. Everybody needs different medicine. A bodhisattva
sees what everybody needs and they act accordingly. That's how you can really save sentient beings,
not be confused in this reincarnation anymore and reach enlightenment. The Ming meditation
is to do no evil. When you do not kill, you do not steal, you do not have sexual misconduct,
you do not do anything bad, you are already the Buddha. Number six, Zen Buddhism, or we
call it Chen Buddhism. They focus on meditation to find this mind. When the sixth patriarch
of Zen Buddhism, Hui Nan, he became enlightened. He said five verses. Three verses, I put it
here according to the three-fold meditation. The self nature is originally pure, but the
self nature is not pure. He realized, oh, this true nature of ours is originally pure.
There's not any defilement, afflictions, or delusions. So we don't have any greed, anger,
or ignorance. It's not in our nature in the first place. So that's the void meditation,
seeing the emptiness of our afflictions. Self nature is originally complete. That's the
unreal meditation. Even though everything is pure, it's not pure. The self nature is
already complete. Everything is unreal. You are still endowed with limitless, meritorious
qualities, great compassion, great wisdom that's already complete inside of you. So
do not say you cannot be a bodhisattva in your everyday life. You just have to believe
in yourself. Self nature can generate myriad dharma. Everything is created by our mind.
You can manifest anything by putting your thought into it.
Our mind is the power of the universe. Believe in your mind, that can create everything.
So do not have bad thoughts. Your bad thoughts will come into reality. It all depends on
your thoughts.
Seven is the Pure Land School of Buddhism. That's what we are practicing. We are reciting
Amitabha Buddha's name and hoping to go to his Western Pure Land. That's our life goal.
In the Contemplation Sutra, it says,
If you want to go to the Western Pure Land with the highest grade of lotus flower, you
must have these three minds.
The Void Meditation is the mind of deep faith. You know your mind, the true essence, is emptiness.
That's your true nature. You have no doubt about it. You deeply reside in this truth.
You have deep faith.
The Unreal Meditation is the mind aspiring rebirth to the true nature. You have no doubt
about it. You deeply reside in this truth. You have deep faith.
The
Pure Land Buddhism is out of great compassion.
It's pure liquid.
It is not lead, Holy earlier,ô
and treating everyone equally hoping they will get our reincarnation and
reach enlightenment the mean meditation is the most sincere mind your mind is
the Buddha it doesn't have any wandering thoughts that is called sincere mind not
a single selfish thought not a single deluded thought if you have these three
minds you'll definitely go to the Western Pure land eight is the esoteric
this school of Buddhism holds a lot of special mantras and believes that one
can reach Buddhahood in this very lifetime it's also talking about our
true nature in terms of the three bodies of Buddha all Buddha and all sentient
beings have three bodies dharmakaya manifestation body
Atma원
the incarnation body. Void meditation is our manifestation body, which is talking
about our form. When you have void meditation, you can get rid of your
defilements. That's when your appearance will be like a bodhisattva. We can have
the incarnation body, the function of our mind. Like Shakyamuni Buddha, he was a
real prince in India. He had a wife, he had children, he did all these things
like a normal person. That is incarnation body. He was really existing in this
unreal conventional world. Lastly it's the Dharmakaya. it's our essence body
which is the middleway which is the mean which is this perfect self that
everybody have Everyone has these three Dharma bodies just like all buddhas.
It's just we haven't recognized it. So these are eight schools of Mahayana
Buddhism.
They're all talking about this one mind in terms of the three-fold meditation.
Which school of Buddhism you practice, it doesn't matter.
The ultimate goal is to find your true nature.
Live this life like a bodhisattva.
Detach from everything.
Live the life to the fullest and help everyone you can.
Then you're living out your true essence, your true Buddha nature.
Hope this helps.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.