Today we are going to talk about true happiness.
Buddha is an enlightened being who has the power of meditative absorption and perfect
wisdom.
That is the source of our true happiness.
In this class, we will use the great wisdom shastra to taste the flavor of this true happiness.
Relaxedly meditate under a tree in the forest.
We don't need much to be happy.
We just need to sit in a quiet place and just enjoy our breathing and be present.
That's all we need to be happy and content.
With tranquility and rapture, all evil cease.
The two signs of deep meditation are tranquility and rapture.
Tranquility is the calmness, the peace of our mind, and the rapture is the unconditional
happiness of just being alive and breathing.
When we have this, all evil cease.
Evil actually means the two major hindrances, which are dowsiness and restlessness.
When we have tranquility, we definitely rest.
When we have rapture, we definitely don't have any restlessness.
Our mind is definitely calm and not chaotic and full of wandering thoughts.
When we have rapture, our mind is not drowsy because it's very happy and alive and alert.
So all evil ceases.
The mind enters a spiritual unity.
When we have deep concentration, we will be united with our one true mind, our Buddha nature.
The easiest way to reach this is through meditation.
To reach this spiritual unity, is actually to recite Amitabha Buddha life while meditating.
When we have deep concentration, we will be united with our one true mind, our Buddha nature.
The easiest way to reach this is through meditation.
This name actually means infinite light and infinite life.
Infinite life means infinite wisdom, and infinite life means infinite married and virtue.
This name itself is the spiritual unity of our one true mind.
By this time we no longer think of any goodness or evil.
By this time we no longer think of any goodness or evil without gerwalking toavin woman.
think of any goodness or evil there's no more duality of merit or offenses and there's no form
no name it's just the one true mind so when we reach this spiritual unity the joy exceeds
heavenly joy the heavenly beings in the 28 levels of heaven they still have affliction they still
have an ego and they haven't reached their one true mind their spiritual unity so our happiness
of meditating and being awakened is much more than the happiness of the heavens now let's look at
what we ordinary people think of happiness ordinary people pursue worldly goods mundane
people think the source of our happiness is acquiring possessions we think possessing
material goods, we think we buy and sell natural goods, we think we precious and practice other
We think we possess material goods and we practice other pleasure and patrol is non- sick, leverage,
will make us happy. The examples used here are branding clothing or fashion bed linings.
This actually includes everything. Cars, watches, bags, or a cell phone, houses. These are things
that we pursue. We think it will make us happy. That's why we keep seeking it. But we don't
realize that this happiness we're pursuing actually has two main faults. One, this sort
of happiness is never stable. This happiness is only temporary and short lived. Because
the thing you love, it might be stolen. Someone else has a better one and then you're no
longer happy or they would get old and break. The second fault is never satisfied when pursuing
material good. The desire is insatiable. No one says oh I have enough money or I have
enough goods.
I don't want anything else to break my Esquire. I don't want a swooping Здесьaction county.
need anymore everybody keep pursuing and wanting more and never satisfied when you are not content
you will never be happy this happiness has a lot of problems and this is what's causing
our samsara to keep going once upon a time there was a master named jim b finn he was great at
meditation he can always go into deep concentration his body would disappear and nobody can find him
one day his life was about to end king yama the lord of hell summoned the two ghost manians
to catch him when they got there they couldn't find him so they asked the earth deity the earth
deity said oh he always going to deep meditation and nobody can find him but he has a favorite
precious elms bowl if you can find it and tap on it three times he will exit from his meditation
the dwarves found it and did us instructed
sure
After enough, Jing Bi Feng awoke from his meditation and was caught by the ghost.
Jing Bi Feng silently lamented on how his attachment to the Anus bowl was the reason
why he was still unable to be liberated from Samsara.
Swiftly he threw the bowl on the ground, shattering it into pieces, sat down to meditate, went
into deep concentration, and escaped for good.
So what is your precious Anus bowl?
It can be material good, it can be the people you love, it can be your talent, your career.
If you are attached to anything that is preventing us from liberation, especially for Pure Land
Buddhas, if we still have an Anus of attachment, that will prevent us from going to the Western
Pure Land.
So let go of our attachment to worldly goods.
Above we are talking about concentration, now we are going to talk about wisdom.
We are going to talk about Samahati.
We stay at a quiet, remote place.
Samahati is the robe that monastics wear to symbolize their renunciation of the world.
And we stay in a quiet, remote place to meditate.
All we try to do is to have spiritual awakening.
Train the mind to be stable in action or non-action.
When we are sitting in meditation, it's called non-action.
We are non-active.
We are not moving.
We are just sitting there.
We are just deep into our mind and into our breathing and into the NAMI DAPA.
So it's easy for the mind to be stable when we are sitting.
But when we are in action in our daily lives, it is harder for our mind to be stable.
So we need to train our mind to be stable in six daily actions of walking, standing,
sitting, lying down.
Lying down, working, and speaking.
We should observe all our actions and all our thoughts.
For example, walking.
One should observe the intention arise from the mind wanting to walk.
The body moves forward accordingly.
The movement of the body might be accompanied by mental formation such as good or evil thoughts
from within.
We might be walking to hit someone.
Or walking to help someone.
That are good or evil intentions.
As such, one should raise awareness, see through the intention of walking, understand that
this intention has no form.
There is not a self as the walker or the perception of walking.
Both are empty of an intrinsic nature that is true insight meditation.
So the insight can light up the mind to see through the reality.
When we have this insight, it will illuminate our mind and we will see the truth about
everything which is emptiness.
Nothing is as real and permanent and independent as we think.
So when we see emptiness, then we are liberated.
When the mind can investigate various dharmas with equal insight, always observe everything
in this manner.
Use the equal insight, empty of the self, empty of all dharma, that is called equal
insight.
When we have this emptiness wisdom, then we will no longer be caught up by anything.
Your mind will not be moved by external situations and factors.
You will always be in deep meditation and deep wisdom, arising wisdom to overcome delusions.
With this insight, we will overcome delusions.
We will overcome all our delusions because there is actually no delusion.
We understand the emptiness of our delusions.
There's no real anger, there is no real greed.
When you understand they are just conditions of existence, you will no longer be capable
of anger or greed because they are not the real you.
You no longer are attached to this personality and all of these afflictions.
An inner spirit will no longer be in touch with you.
all these afflictions now disappears. This happiness surpasses the three rounds. When
we have this wisdom, this happiness will take us beyond samsara, which is the three rounds.
There's no more the round of desire, the round of form, and the round of formlessness.
We go beyond reincarnation and samsara. So all Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, they practice
meditation because they know that deep meditation and wisdom is true happiness. And for a Bodhisattva,
if you really want to help sentient beings, the only way is when you have deep meditative
absorption, all your prayers and your vows will really come to fruition and other people
can really benefit from your prayer. So this is the kind of happiness that we will experience
when we practice meditation.
We go to the Western Pure Land. Right now, we might experience it for a short moment
of time, but over there, you will experience it every day and constantly. You will have
deep concentration and deep wisdom. So let's practice right now with all our power. Then
we'll definitely be going to the Western Pure Land and reaching enlightenment.
So that's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Hope everybody have true happiness.
Amitabha.