昔日 respect 계속的文化
Today we're going to talk about the ten farmer grounds, the ten places that we physically
exist in. The ten places or ten conditions, the ten worlds that we create for ourselves.
Why is it called Dharma Round? Because Dharma is what we call everything. And this everything
is created by our minds. That's why it's called Dharma Round. So it's all created by us. From
the bottom to the top, there are ten places. The first is called hell. Who creates hell?
Hell is when you're very angry all the time. Or you're depressed. Or you're feeling very
bad. Or you have a lot of negative emotions. This is a place where we're very miserable.
And you feel like you're in the present. Even when you're living as a person, you can be
in hell because of your emotions. You live in a beautiful place. You live in a mansion.
But your heart is full of turmoil and depression. Then you're still in hell. So hell is created
by yourself. The second is called Hungry Ghost Round. The Hungry Ghost World is when we're
very selfish. We're always desiring things for ourselves. You're always thinking of what
do I get? A craving. And you're all constantly dominated by this feeling of craving for things.
The third is the Animal Round. So you say, why is animal not good? No, they're so cute.
Animals, they can reason. They can think. They're kind of ignorant. They can think
like humans. We have the ability to reason and have a lot
of reason and think logically. Animals follow their instinct. They have a lot of sexual
behavior. They just follow whatever they're craving. When we are very emotional, we are
in the Animal Round. When we're just constantly being very ignorant and foolish and living
by our instinct. The more craving you have, the more selfish you are, the less happy you
will be. So these three rounds are the non-virtuous
rounds.
The bad rounds. And these three are the virtuous or good rounds.
So the fourth round is called the Asura Round. Asura Round, they do good deeds, but they're
always jealous of others. They do good deeds, but they want to be number one. Number one
on whatever good deed they're doing. So that is still a good round, but it's not perfect
because you have a lot of jealousy of others doing better than you are. If you're always
jealous of others, you lose.
You live here. You're always jealous of others.
And the fifth is the Human Round. Human World. We are physically in the human world right
now. Human is a mixture of good deeds and bad deeds. Sometimes we are good, sometimes
we're bad. The good thing about humans is we can reflect and we can change our ways.
A lot of other rounds, they can do that. We are the only one that can really improve ourselves
and become a Buddha. We become a true enlightened being. The human round is actually the best
round to cultivate. Because we have a lot of tragedies and difficulties in our lives
too, but we also have a lot of wonderful experiences too.
The last good round is the Heaven. The heavenly beings, they're very compassionate. They always
think for others, help others. They're full of loving kindness and always do things for
others. So if you're always kind and loving, you live in a good life.
Thank you.
And then the heavenly round, the Heaven. You're in the Heaven. So these are the six rounds
of reincarnation. When you die, next lifetime, you can go to any one of these rounds. But
if you cultivate Buddhism, you can go up to even higher and get out of the reincarnation.
These four are the rounds of sages and enlightened beings.
The seventh is called Arhats, or Sound, Hear, Arhats. They are ones that really help you
to be a Buddha. They really learn the Buddhism, understand the impermanence of life, and they
let go of the idea of self. They let go of their ego. They're no longer having their
own desire, their own emotion, and everything about themselves. They let go of the idea
of personhood and their ego, and become Arhats. The next one is the Pratyekabuddha. They're
like the Arhats. They're like the Arhats, they'll be self-paritié. They have to be
self-paritié. They're like the Arhats. They're like the Arhats. They're like the Arhats. They're
But they don't need to listen, but listening to the teaching of Buddhism. They can become enlightened by themselves
Just by looking at the trees looking at the mountains and they realize oh everything is changing
Everything is impermanent
Everything is based on cost condition and there's not a selfish me that's inside of this thing
So they become completely aware and realize the true nature of the universe
So they are called the Pandayaka Buddha become fully realized. These two they only focus on their own
Practice they don't try to help others to become enlightened
But Bodhisattva not only do they want to have enlightenment for themselves
They want other people to be enlightened. They want to help others to come into full enlightenment
Okay, so they help others. Last one is the Buddha round
This is the combination
of
Our hats and because they come to self realization about themselves
They also help others when you're in the perfect complete balance between these two you become the Buddha
because you have the complete wisdom and the complete
Compassion that is perfect and supreme and then you become a Buddha all of us have the quality of
the ten rounds inside of us
We all have the potential to live in this ten rounds to fully
understand all
Buddha's of the three periods of time to fully understand what is a Buddha Buddha is basically a person
if Buddha is not a god
anyone can be a Buddha so for the three periods of time the past and the
present and the future
So you want to know how do the past present or future Buddha came about?
you have to continue
the nature of the dharma realm. You have to understand what's the nature of these ten
places. The nature is everything is created from the mind. So what's the true nature?
All these are created by your mind. You have ten doors. Which door you want to open, it's
up to you. Buddha still live in this world, do everyday activity, still go to work and
still have family. But it's just they are full of compassion and wisdom and let go of
the idea of the self. And they are a Buddha. Full of compassion, courage, love, life force
and creativity. But they are just normal person. You have the potential to be a Buddha all
the time. As long as you contemplate on the idea that you have the Buddha nature. All
you have to do is contemplate on the fact that I am a Buddha. I have Buddha nature.
So when I deal with everybody around me, I want to be compassionate. I want to let go
of my anger. I don't want to be greedy, foolish. I don't want to be in other realms. Because
I create my own Buddhahood. One realm contains all other realms. For example, I am a human
right now. But if I always think about helping others to become a Buddha, I don't want to
become enlightened. Then I am a human, what? Bodhisattva. I am a human but I always think
about helping others. But if I am always fighting, always angry, then I am a human's what?
Hell. One contains the other nine. But it's up to you to always choose to be in the higher
world. There is a French man. He works in a department store. One day he was fired because
he had no job in his poor. His wife took the kid and left him. So he felt like it's the
end of the world. He wanted to commit suicide. He talked to his best friend. I am going to
kill myself because I feel life is meaningless. I am at the bottom of my life. It's meaningless.
I want to kill myself. And his friend told him, I know this great psychic. Maybe you
should go to the psychic first. You know, he can tell you something about your life.
So he went to the psychic and the psychic told him, you know, last lifetime you were
Napoleon. And you can do great things. You'll be very successful whatever you're doing.
And then he said, oh, I am Napoleon. Okay. So he decided not to kill himself. And he
started working. He said, I am Napoleon. Every day he kept telling himself he is Napoleon.
And then he started looking for another job in the department store. And now he is the
owner of the largest department store in France. How does this come about? Was he really Napoleon?
In his last life? We don't know. But he thought he is. And then he changed his life.
It's all up to you to change your life just by how you think. If you think I am a Buddha,
then I am a Buddha. Nothing else will interfere with you of your dreams. And you can make
all your dreams come true and live a joyful life. Okay. So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening. Amitabha.