Today we are going to talk about anger.
Anger is a big hindrance that blocks us from being enlightened.
Why do we have anger and how to deal with our anger?
Let go of anger so that you will be joyful and free.
Anger is the root of poison and it destroys every good.
You have to let go of all your anger.
That includes a little irritation when there's traffic,
when you get upset at the drivers or that unreasonable boss, co-workers.
A lot of people in your life that makes us angry.
You have to let it all go in order for us to be joyful and free.
Especially if you want to have a healthy body.
A lot of our disease comes from anger, especially cancer and depression.
It's all a result of anger.
If we want to be healthy and happy, we have to let it go.
It is the root of poison.
In Buddhism, we talk about three poisons.
Greed, anger and ignorance.
Anger is the root of toxicity that is making us sick.
We create the poison for ourselves.
It destroys every good.
All our virtue, kindness, compassion.
Because we're angry, it's all destroyed.
We have to deal with our anger.
Why do we get angry?
We are angry at things that's not going our way.
We don't get angry at things that's very satisfactory.
So it's actually anything we consider adversity or difficulties or challenging.
Anything we don't like, we get angry.
So what do we do?
How do we eliminate the anger?
That's the big question.
So we have four ways today for you to deal with your anger.
The first is don't accept the package.
This is from a Buddha Sutra.
One of the sutras is called the Sutra of 42 Chapters.
There are 42 verses that talk about how to cultivate.
And one of the verses says someone was insulting Buddha.
And Buddha said to the person,
if you give a neighbor a package,
if the neighbor does not accept,
do you have to take it back?
And the person said, yes.
You insulting me today, I do not accept.
So you have to take it back.
We have the choice not to accept any package that you get.
If you don't accept, you don't open it,
it goes back to the center.
We're in total control of our emotion.
If you get angry at that person mistreating you,
you are accepting the package.
We don't want to accept the package that is actually like a bomb that's destroying us.
We have a better life to live.
We don't want to let anyone ruin our own happiness and peace of mind.
So protect your emotion and protect your own happiness
by not accepting the package.
The second way is paying back karmic debt.
When someone is insulting us, mistreating us,
doing bad things to us,
it's actually paying back the karmic debt.
In Buddhism, we talk about karma.
Karma means everything that's happening to you right now.
It's a result of our past doing.
So this person is treating us like this today
is because we've done the wrong before.
So it's coming back to us.
So by them treating us badly,
it's actually paying back debt.
It's like all your mortgages or your loans
or your credit card debt is being paid off.
When they yell at you, it's actually a good thing.
Once you pay it back,
oh, you're going to have a great future ahead of you
because you're going to accumulate a lot of money.
You're going to have a good asset.
That means our merit and virtue and good karma will come out
and all your bad karma will go away.
So be glad that people are treating us bad
because you're getting rid of the debt.
So that's the second way of looking at it.
The third way is see it as a virtuous friendship.
Buddha says when someone is mistreating us,
see it as a great thing.
No one can become a Buddha if you have a charmed life.
Everything is smooth sailing.
That's not any way for you to grow.
A person grows in hardship,
in difficult times, in obstacles.
That's how you reach your potential.
That's how your compassion, kindness,
and your great wisdom comes out.
In the Lotus Sutra, Buddha talks about a king.
This king really wanted to learn Buddhism and the great Dharma.
So he announced to the entire country,
whoever teach me the Buddhist Dharma,
I will be his slave.
I will be his servant.
A sage came forward and said,
I have the Buddhist teaching and you should be my servant.
So the king went and be his servant.
He has to chop wood for him and pick a lot of fruit.
Even he has to let his back be a bed for the sage to sleep on.
And he didn't do it for a day or two.
He did it for a thousand years.
Because in the olden days, people would live a long time.
And Buddha said, that king was me.
And that sage was Dibbentata.
Dibbentata is a Buddha's nemesis.
Every time Buddha says anything,
he will just oppose.
He's always in contradiction with Buddha.
Whatever Buddha says, he will say the opposite.
And he's trying to sabotage everything that Buddha is trying to teach.
So every Buddha has a Dibbentata.
You might have one in your life.
That is a good thing.
You want to consider it a virtuous friendship.
Without that person, you cannot be a Buddha.
So think the relationship.
It's a great thing that you have this person in your life
to help you grow yourself spiritually.
So be thankful of that person in your life.
And the fourth way is called non-self emptiness.
In Buddhism, we say there is not really
a self that should be getting angry.
Because everything is based on cause and conditions.
I have this body because of the air,
the water, and the food I eat.
These are all conditions.
And all the conditions change.
So there's not an unchanging me
that I should be protecting.
So when people are insulting me,
who are they insulting?
There's not really a me.
So who is getting angry, right?
It's not a me.
So why should you be angry?
There's not a person for you to protect.
Our own identity that we think there is a me,
that is not your higher self.
Our higher self is without the personal selfish feelings.
And when we get angry,
that's because we're trying to protect something
that we think is unreasonable
or it's not going the way that we like.
And that is all the ego speaking.
So understand non-self is the highest kind of wisdom.
And you will understand the emptiness,
the emptiness of all things.
Don't let anybody control your peace and happiness
because everything is empty.
It's forever changing.
There's not a me for you to insist on and protect.
Okay, so these are the four ways
for you to not get angry anymore.
And lastly, pure mind, pure land.
We want to go to Amitabha's pure land
after this lifetime.
Pure land is actually made out of your own pure mind.
Your pure mind without anger and without greed,
without all the poisons,
you create the pure land for yourself.
Even when you're on this earth right now,
if you're being pure without any anger,
then you are creating heaven.
You're living in heaven
when your mind is at peace and without anger.
Okay, so that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening on the telephone.