Today we are going to talk about the Heart Sutra.
It's called the Heart Sutra for three reasons.
One is the heart of a much larger Maha-Prajna-Paramita Sutra.
Two is the heart of all Buddha's teachings.
Three is talking about our pure heart, the Buddha nature.
In the beginning of the Sutra, it says,
when Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva was practicing the profound Prajnaparamita,
he illuminated the five skandhas and saw that they are all empty,
and he crossed beyond all suffering and difficulty.
Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva is who we call Guanyin Bodhisattva.
He was practicing profound Prajnaparamita.
What is Prajnaparamita?
Prajnaparamita is supreme, unique wisdom.
And Paramita is from the shore of suffering to the other shore of Nirvana.
So we need to practice this Prajnaparamita.
There are actually three kinds of Prajnaparamita.
One is the Prajnaparamita of language.
The words that we see here in the Sutra, that is Prajnaparamita of language.
Two is the Prajnaparamita of contemplative illumination.
We need to contemplate on the words.
Then we will reach number three, the Prajnaparamita of characteristics of actuality.
Our true nature, we call the real mark or actuality.
So we need to have the words, then the contemplation to reach the actuality.
Just like we have a car and we have a driver, then we will reach the destination.
This Prajnaparamita is called profound because it's not superficial.
It's not superficial wisdom or intellect.
It's actually totally aligned with our true treasury of Tathagata, our true Buddha nature.
That's why it's called profound.
What do we see with this Prajnaparamita?
We actually see the emptiness of our five skandhas, the body and mind we're using right now.
It's not the true self.
So that's what we see when we really have the wisdom.
It goes on to say that,
the five skandhas are empty, no form, feeling, cognition, formation or consciousness.
This body is called the form.
We have feelings of pleasure and displeasure.
We have our perception and we have our deeper mental formation, deeper attachment.
Then we have our storehouse, the alaya consciousness.
None of this is me.
All these are just conditioned existence.
It goes on further to say,
the six sense organs, no eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body or mind.
And there's not the six sense objects, no sight, sound, smell, taste, touch or dharma.
Together, the six sense organs and the six sense objects are called the 12 bases.
And then no fields of the eyes up to and including no field of mind consciousness.
We have the eye consciousness, ear consciousness,
all the way up to the mind consciousness.
This is called the 18 realms of beings.
This is how we experience the world.
We think this is me.
This is my life.
But we need to understand that this is not my life.
This is not the real me.
If you are more attached to the mental experience,
we will tell you about the five skandhas.
Because four out of five is mental.
If you are more attached to physical,
then we will tell you about the 12 bases.
Because 11 out of the 12 are physical.
Only the mind is mental.
If you're equally attached to the mental and the physical,
we will tell you about the 18 realms altogether.
Depending on what you're more attached to,
then Buddha tells you different things.
Only to let you see that they are empty and it's not the real you.
When someone has prajna,
it doesn't mean they do not hear and do not see and shut off everything.
It means they still see and hear,
but they use their heart.
For example,
if someone utter some words that's insulting to us,
humiliating us,
a saint will hear it differently.
In the Sravagama Sutra,
it tells us how Guan Yin Bodhisattva became enlightened.
He said,
I entered the flow through hearing,
forgot objective states.
So he entered the flow,
of his Buddha nature,
the treasury of the Thakta,
through the sense of hearing.
He forgot all objective states.
The hearing with the ears,
what is being heard,
both disappear.
They're empty.
Moreover,
emptiness and what's being empty also cease to be.
That's when you really see the emptiness of the five skandhas.
You will not hear things the same way anymore.
It says in the Heart Sutra,
Bodhisattva through reliance on the Prajnaparamita
is unimpeded in his mind.
Because there's no impediment,
he is not afraid,
and he leaves distorted dream thinking far behind.
So a Bodhisattva rely on this Prajnaparamita of emptiness.
He has no more impediment in his mind.
He's not worried about this person's insulting me
or humiliating me.
He has no more worry or stress,
about these words.
He's not afraid of what other people say
or whatever happened to him.
That's why he has no more deluded false thinking,
the distorted dreamlike thoughts.
He leaves it all behind.
When you use the Prajnaparamita,
that's when we really live a carefree and happy life.
So a true Bodhisattva is very flexible,
tolerant,
full of love and compassion and gratefulness
for all.
He's very open minded,
and he gives you all the answers
to all sentient beings.
They live life through a whole different experience.
The top part here is the attachment of the mundane people to the five skandhas.
The bottom part is the attachment of the saints to the Dharma.
So the Buddha further breaks down our attachment to the Dharma.
First, the 12 dependent origination.
No ignorance or ending of ignorance up to and include
or ending of old age and death.
The 12 dependent origination starts with ignorance
and it ends with the 12th link of old age and death.
So there's not the samsara going down
or the ending of ignorance or ending of old age and death,
the nirvana going up.
So none of this is real.
Just like everything is happening in the dream,
whatever that samsara that's going out in the dream to awaken person
is not important.
So we need to see the emptiness to break free from our attachment to the dream.
In the Heart Sutra, it says form does not differ from emptiness.
Emptiness does not differ from form.
Form itself is emptiness.
Empty itself is form.
You can replace the form with anything.
In here, you can replace it with samsara or nirvana.
For example, samsara does not differ from emptiness.
Emptiness does not differ from form.
That's not different from samsara.
Samsara itself is emptiness.
Empty itself is samsara.
There's no production of samsara and there is nothing destroyed.
You don't destroy the samsara to get nirvana.
Samsara is not defiled and nirvana is not pure.
Samsara is not diminishing and nirvana is not increasing.
So we need to break all the duality.
That's prajna.
And in here, there's endless suffering and there is no justification and full of emptiness.
Everything is gone.
There are no end to suffering and where to suffer.
All is less than the same.
You have to rid of all your sufferings and just leave all the changes in your life.
And let go of all your sufferings and are never alone in method of Jennanya.
And that's the kinda of emphatic Sufi in there.
With the samsara, it's clear that you are a multitude with each other and justENA
انكل westernا
emptiness, empty itself is suffering and suffering is not produced and cessation of suffering
is not destroying the suffering. Suffering itself is not defiled and cessation of suffering
is not pure and suffering is not diminishing and ending of suffering is not increasing.
We need to break from all duality of good or bad or increasing, diminishing. That's
when you're really free. So let go of our attachment to the dharma. Then Buddha says
there's no six pyramidas, no understanding. This is the last pyramid. Bodhisattva, they're
attached to their six pyramidas of giving, holding precepts, endurance, diligence, concentration
and wisdom.
wisdom. This understanding is the wisdom. So do not be attached to prajna either. There
is no prajna to gain or to have or to cultivate. It is what it is. So let go of our attachment
to the understanding, the last pyramid. Lastly, there is no bodhi to gain. There is no Buddhahood
to attain. There is no attaining. So the conclusion is because nothing is attained. So there is
nothing to gain, nothing to have, nothing to attain. When you reach this level of wisdom,
you will truly be carefree and you will have no more impediment of any kind and no stress,
no worry, no problem. Long ago, Guanyin Bodhisattva already made
great vows to save all sentient beings from suffering. But he saw so many of the people
that he saved went back to their old ways of greed, anger, and ignorance and kept reincarnating.
He felt great despair in his heart, finally gave up and relinquished his bodhi resolve.
At this moment, his body shattered into a thousand pieces. That's when his teacher Amitabha
Buddha came to the rescue and told him,
Remember the emptiness.
The emptiness of the self and all sentient beings are just conditioned existence not
to be attached to. That's when he had a moment of epiphany. And his body reconstructed and
transformed into one thousand hands and one thousand eyes. That's why you see the one
thousand hands and eyes Guanyin Bodhisattva.
So have prajna. Do not be attached to anything or anyone. That's when you can really save
everybody.
In conclusion, all Buddhas of the Three Periods of Time attain Anuttara Samyaya Sambodhi through
reliance on Prajna Pyramida. All Buddhas of the past, present, and future attain Buddhahood
through prajna. Anuttara Samyaya Sambodhi means unsurpassable, complete, and perfect
enlightenment only through prajna.
So reside in your own innate prajna.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
carefree life without any problems or any worries. That's when you found your true
heart. That's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.