Today we are going to talk about Pure Sixth Sense Organs.
We create karma that perpetuates rebirth through our sixth sense organs, but it is also through
our sixth sense organs we become enlightened.
Therefore we take the same road back home.
We will use the Shravagama Sutra to understand how to purify our sixth sense organs.
First we need to understand the origins of our afflictions.
The main problem is our sixth sense organs, they always chase after sensory objects.
Now let's look at the sensory objects.
Every organ has two types of objects.
Our eyes, when there is light, we see everything.
When there is darkness, we see blackness.
Our ears, when we hear sound, it's called movement.
When there is no sound, it's called stillness.
Our nose, when it's clear, it's called penetration.
When it's congested, it's called obstruction.
Our tongue, when we taste plain food, it's called blandness.
When we taste a lot of variety of different flavors, such as spicy, sour, sweet, sour,
bitter, it's called variety.
Our body, when it's in contact with object, it's called union.
When it's in isolation, it's called separation.
Our mind, when it has thoughts arising, it's called production.
When the thought disappears, it's called extinction.
So we're forever chasing after the sixth sense objects.
There's two kinds of sensory organs, one is called the pure sensory organs and one is
called the super sensory organs.
Superficial sensory organs, the superficial sensory organs is what we see on the outside.
And the pure sixth sense organs, they are the refined, invisible elements of our organs.
So let's first talk about the superficial organs.
They are easy to understand.
For example, our eyes are shaped like grapes.
Our ears are shaped like fresh coral leaves.
Our nose is shaped like a double hanging claw.
Our tongue is shaped like crescent moon.
Our body is shaped like a table.
Actually it's not a table, it's like a drum that is narrower in the waist, like the shape
of a human.
Our mind is like seeing in the dark room.
So these are very vivid descriptions of our sixth sense organs.
But in the inside, we actually have pure elements of our sixth sense organs that's attaching
to the sensory organs.
Our sensory objects are pure organs combined with the form.
For example, we might be attached to what we see all the time.
Some people, they might be attached to social media, always watching for other people's
comments because that's what they think will give them happiness.
Or when we see a medical report, all the numbers that is getting worse, then we might become
very depressed.
Whatever we see, it totally drives our senses.
It drives our emotions.
Our ears resounds with sound.
So our ears pursue after the sounds.
For example, if you hear that you are being promoted, you're very happy.
If you hear that you're getting laid off, then you become very upset.
So our emotion follows what we hear every day.
Our nose, it takes incense.
For example, if you smell a homeless person, the odor is not very strong.
So our nose, it takes incense.
You might have negative feelings or look down on the person, but you forgot that this person
has the Buddha nature, and you, as someone who has the Buddha nature, should not look
down on anyone.
Our tongue is entwined with flavor.
When we taste our favorite food, such as chocolate cake or ice cream, we're full of desires.
Our body seizes upon contact.
We love to touch soft things or soft skins.
that's also because of our greed and our mind grabs onto the dharma we have a lot of thoughts
a lot of time our thought is full of negativity and we can think ourselves into depression
so we are always grabbing on to the sensory object that's why we cannot be enlightened what we need
to do is to go inward stop seeking outward everything should be inward to your own self
nature see the essence there's actually this essence in our sixth sense organs the closest
thing to our buddha nature it is actually still the alaya consciousness before it start thinking
discriminating and perceiving or ignorant that's the closest to who we really are
to the body and our heart we have an essence of seeing we have essence all hearing essence of
smelling essence of tasting essence of sensation essence of knowing only if we go inward
can we see our essence when we do not follow the 12 conditioned appearances
of the objects our pure essence will emerge when clarity is pure to its essence no matter what
happens there is a decisiveness as you can see in udahika's life happens to need the information
and soon as the Laguna times started I realized there were a bunch of asian Yasmin or as the
is no affliction how do we come back to this essence now let's look at the
efficacy Buddha gives every organ a score the perfect score is 1200 how do
we come up with 1200 is the four directions of east west north south
times the three periods of past present and future times the ten dharma rounds
of the physical world times the ten dharma rounds of the inner truth level so
together it has a perfect score of 1200 looking at our eyes it only gets 800
because we see the front and left and right we do not see the back so it's
deficient by a third therefore it only gets the score of 800 merits our ear it
can hear everywhere all directions
therefore it gets a perfect score of 1200 our nose is deficient at the point
between inhalation and exhalation therefore it's deficient by a third as
well it gets a score of 800 our tongue gets a score of 1200 the perfect score
because it can proclaim all worldly and transcendental wisdom and our body only
gets 800 because when it's in union with the earth it only gets 800 because when it's in union
with in contact with objects it can feel pain or pleasure so each deserves a
third, when our body is separated it's not functioning so it is deficient by a
third as well so it gets a score of 800 our mind gets a score of 1200 because it
can know all the worldly and transcendental Dharma therefore it gets
a perfect score of 1200 so how do we learn from the previous 3 dharma lines
do we use this is to help us narrow it down to one sense organ to go inward so
to narrow down further we should know that the nose tongue and body need to be
united with the object for it to be useful so we eliminate them the eyes
ears and mind they are more useful because they don't need to come in
direct contact with the object. We narrow down to these three the mind itself
is more deep and the eyes and ears are more shallow the deeper ones are harder
to control because our mind our thoughts change all the time so we are left with
the eyes and the years the eyes has 800 points and the ears gets a perfect score
therefore the final result is the ears. We
need to
go back to you and try to do the same thing
same thing again again and again so always I encourage you to expect ging to go and Morgen to wear your ears because I need you inside
back to our essence through our hearing. This is the way that Guanyin Bodhisattva cultivates.
He enters the flow through the hearing and forgot all sensory object. So we need to return
the hearing, listen to the self nature till it reaches the supreme way. Do not go outward.
Listen to all the sound. What this person is saying, not saying. Always go back to who
you are. Know your essence. That's when you will reach the supreme way, the perfect enlightenment.
This way of cultivation is the best way to return to our nature because it's very easy
to concentrate our mind inward through hearing. When you have the way cultivating for one
day, you will be able to go back to your essence. You will be able to go back to your essence.
You will be able to go back to your essence. You will be able to go back to your essence.
It's the same as cultivating for eons. That is the same way as great strength Bodhisattva's
way of Buddha remembrance Samadhi. He chanted the name Amitabha, gathered in all the six
sense organs, have continuous pure mindfulness of the name Amitabha. That's how he reached
Samadhi and perfect penetration. We can all do this by going inward.
So the conclusion is, as soon as one sense organ return to the source, the entire six
are liberated. It just takes one, the years, then you are liberated. Enter one falsely
and all six sense organs simultaneously become pure. It is how we return to our source,
to our essence. This is called entering emptiness from existence.
That's how we become self-enlightened. But when we want to go help all sentient beings,
we need to turn it around. Enter existence from emptiness. That's when we use the six
sense organs. Lodge at the organs is the revelation of the brightness that permits the mutual function
of the six organs. When your six sense organs are perfectly pure, they can be used interchangeably
. Your ears can see, your eyes can taste, so everything is possible. Why? Because you
are no longer attached to the objects. You are not bound by this world anymore. This
is the power that we all have inside of us. We just forgot it because we are so attached
to the world. As soon as we go inward, we will have this ability back. That's what happened
to all the big bodhisattvas.
Always know what your six sense organs are doing. When they are chasing outward, bring
them back. Extract them inward and free them. Subdue them from the inner core. Once it's
subdued, it will return to the inherent truth and radiate with its inner brilliance.
So that's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.