Today we are going to talk about the Formless Three Refuges.
We take refuge in the Buddha, Dharma and the Sangha.
That is how one becomes a Buddhist.
Take means to turn back.
Refuge means to rely on.
The Triple Jewels as our guidance in our lives.
We will discuss the Formless Three Refuges together with the Three Bodies of Buddha,
the Trikayas in Master Huinan's Platform Sutra.
When we think of the Buddha, we might think of Shakyamuni Buddha who is our teacher.
When we talk about the Dharma, we might think of his teaching, his sutras and the Sangha.
We think of the monastic community.
But this is the Triple Jewels in its form.
When we talk about the Formless Triple Jewels, we are talking about the Buddha, the Dharma
and the Sangha within ourselves.
There is no other place to retreat to because there is no Triple Jewels outside of us.
Buddha means the enlightenment nature in our own mind.
We rely on this awakened nature so the evil and the lucid notion do not arise.
The Dharma increases, the content is unknown.
Lust and greed do not bind us.
That's the culmination of our merit and wisdom.
When we rely on this awakened nature, we are at the peak of our virtues.
We will not have delusive cravings and bad thoughts.
Then we rely on the Dharma which is the orthodoxy, the right views.
We are free from wrong views such as egotism, arrogance and craving.
When we are free from wrong views, we are free from negative views, such as selfishness,
arrogance and craving.
this is the best way to get rid of our desires our desires are insatiable we might be greedy
for food money or fame or lust all these desires rob us of our serenity we want to use the dharma
to get rid of our desires we also want to rely on the sangha which is our own purity we have
innate purity within us no matter what circumstances we're not contaminated by
wearisome sense objects and craving and desires that's the noblest quality of mankind when we
have purity we are not contaminated by our world experience that's when we are most noble we want
to rely on the triple jewels within us it's nowhere to be found outside it's not
the temple a statue or a master it's all within your own mind that's true refuge according to
hui nan the sixth patriarch of zen buddhism in summary we want to take refuge in the buddha
dharma sangha within us which is the enlightenment the orthodoxy and the purity
of ourselves and within our own mind take refuge within means to be in control of our
and without it means to be respectful to all others now we will discuss trikaya
take refuge in the buddha of our own essence means the three bodies of buddha the dharmakaya
the sanpukakaya their narvanakaya the essence body the manifestation body
and the incarnation bodies the trochaya is within all of us the physical body
of our buddhas the s match the method of movement the scientific research works on thesemos and the
the essential elements and images its characteristics ofプ quero toil de hoi capitalist art technique
takes refuge in the buddha and the Buddha of哦n essence means the three bodies of Buddha the dharmakaya the
ours is only temporary. We cannot take refuge there. The tracaya is our true body. So within
the essence of our mind, these tracayas are to be found common to everybody. We all have
the three bodies, not just Buddha, but an ordinary man labored under delusion. He does
not recognize his inner nature. He erroneously believes that the tracaya is to be thought
from without. He doesn't recognize it's within himself. So we need to recognize we all have
the three bodies within us. The Dharmakaya is our essence body, which is the formless
Buddha nature. The Sambhogakaya is the manifestation body, which is the reward body, or
the perfect wisdom. The Narmanakaya is the incarnation body, that is my rape. There are
millions of incarnation bodies, that's the compassionate appearances responding to sentient
beings. It's not Buddha having these, it's us right now having these three bodies in
the essence of our own mind. The Dharmakaya is the essence body that is intrinsically
pure in all of us. Good deeds and bad deeds are not related to the real world. They are
are from our good thoughts and bad thoughts.
Dharmakaya is like the radiance of the sun and the moon.
But our bad habits and delusions are like the clouds
covering the sun and the moon.
We just need to use the orthodox, the Dharma,
to put in effort so we can get rid of our delusions.
Then the sun and the moon will be radiant.
That's our Dharmakaya.
We have the Sambhogakaya,
our reward body, which has perfect wisdom.
It's like the light of the lamp can break away darkness
that has been there for a thousand years.
A spark of wisdom will take away our ignorance
that has been there for ages.
So it's all up to our one mind.
Our one thought of wisdom will break away
all the ignorance and delusions.
Similarly, an evil thought will spoil our good merits,
accumulate, and destroy.
Our good thoughts can expiate all our sins.
So it's all within our one thought.
The power of our mind is incredible.
So believe in our own reward body.
Then we have the Namanakaya, the incarnation bodies.
Every thought that arises is a transformation body.
That is my way because there's millions of thoughts.
It's the millions of bodies.
That's my way.
One evil thought, hell arises.
One good thought, paradise appears.
Dragons and snakes are transformations of our hatred.
Bodhisattvas are personification of our mercy and compassion.
The higher realms are the crystallization of our prajna.
And the lower realms are just another form assumed
by our ignorance and our infatuation.
So every thought is a transformation body.
Understand how your Three-Body is working is all within your mind.
Our good thoughts and bad thoughts they have no dualism in its nature, but that's why
we need to work on it, to remove all our negative thoughts.
Our good thoughts and bad thoughts they have no dualism in its nature, but that's why we
need to work on it, to remove all our negative thoughts.
Remove the evil mind, the jealous mind, the flattering and crooked mind, egotism, deceit
and falsehood, contemptuousness, snobbishness, malicious views.
Remove all our negative thoughts.
Remove all our evil mind and good thoughts.
malicious views, arrogance, and all other evils.
Remove these negative minds, then we are taking true refuge in our own Buddha nature.
Evil mind, including the three poisons of greed, anger, and ignorance,
our jealous mind is a big obstacle for all practitioners.
We are envious of others' success.
There was a very diligent practitioner.
He stayed up in the snow mountains and meditated for years,
told great precepts, and let go of all the worldly desires.
One day, one of his disciples went to another temple.
He came back and told the master,
Dear master, your Dharma brother, so-and-so, has reached enlightenment.
Because of this news, he could not meditate and cultivate anymore.
His mind is overwhelmed with jealousy.
So you know the severity.
It's the self-jealousy that's consuming us.
We need to let go of our flattering and crooked mind.
At work or in the temple, we might be flattering and not being sincere.
That is not in accordance with our true mind.
Egotism, we are full of the self.
Even when we are doing good deeds, we are affirming the selfhood, deceit, and falsehood.
We might be lying or cheating, thinking nobody will know what we are doing.
Behind their backs, all your thoughts are transparent.
If you put all your thoughts under the sun, you would be so embarrassed.
So do not have deceit and falsehood.
Contemptuousness, that's when we express hatred or disapproval of others.
Snobbishness, we think we are elitist, we are higher than others, and we have fallacious views.
We are so attached and caught up with the world.
We don't understand that the world is an illusion, that's our false view.
And we have great arrogance, very conceited, and think we are better than others.
All these are evil views, evil mind.
If we can get rid of them, we are taking refuge in the triple jewels and in our three bodies.
To take refuge in our self is to be constantly alert of our mistakes
and refrain from criticism of others' merits or faults.
He who is humble and meek in all occasions and is always polite to all,
he so thoroughly realizes his essence of mind that he will no longer have any more obstacles in his cultivation.
This is the Sutton Enlightenment that Master Hui Nan is talking about.
To see face to face, moment to moment,
with our essence of mind, then we are at once with the Buddha.
Master Hui Nan says, if we really put this into practice,
even if we are a thousand miles away, we are always in his presence.
If we do not practice this and take true refuge in ourselves,
even if we are with him face to face, we are miles away from him.
There is nothing we should be afraid of, your situation, your obstacle.
We are all self-sufficient.
As it is, there is nothing else that should be in our way.
If we take refuge in who we really are, then there is no more obstacles that we should be afraid of.
And if we chant the name Amitabha, we will definitely go to the Pure Land that is our own essence of mind.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.