Today we are going to talk about Peaceful Practice.
How do we have peace and happiness in this chaotic world?
We will learn about Chapter 14 of the Lotus Sutra in order to understand peaceful practice.
Basically, we need to develop four kinds of peaceful practices.
Number one, peaceful deeds.
Number two, peaceful words.
Number three, peaceful thoughts.
Number four, peaceful vows.
Let's look at number one, peaceful deeds.
It has two subsections.
Number one, sphere of practice.
This is the overview of a Bodhisattva practice.
We need to abide in the stage of perseverance and be gentle and tranquil.
This means that we should constantly dwell in our Buddha nature, the suchness, and be
patient and tolerant toward those who harm us, insult us, or slander us.
Oftentimes when other people hurt us, we might just try to hold the precept and force ourselves
not to get angry.
But deep down inside, we still have a lot of resentment and opposition.
But if we really reside in our true nature, then we will be peaceful.
This means that we should constantly dwell in our Buddha nature, the suchness, and be
patient and tolerant toward those who harm us, insult us, or slander us.
Then we will naturally be gentle and tranquil.
This gentleness is not fearful.
We are gentle because we are selfless.
And we are tranquil because we are calmly staying at home and our true nature is unmoved
by the external environment because we know they are impermanent.
So, this is the basis of our practice.
Number two is sphere of relationships.
How do we practice?
daily basis. We need to stay away from 10 kinds of people and situations. I will just
disclose three. Number one is to stay away from high government officials because they
might bring out our desire for fame and fortune. We might not be able to convert them. They
might be converting us. So we want to stay away. Number two, we want to stay away from
violent games such as wrestling or boxing because it might bring out the belligerence
in us. Number three, we should stay away from promiscuous men or women because they might
bring out our lust and feeling of desire. So we need to be very selective. We still
love everyone equally, but we need to choose our environment in order to protect our bodhisattva
practice. Then we need to have confidence.
We need to have contemplation. We need to regard all dharma as being without substance
like empty space. So this is void meditation. We want to see the emptiness of all things.
Our mind should have a quality like the sky that is empty and boundless.
Fifteen years ago, we were living in an apartment in the city. There was an apartment manager.
His name was Sid. He was 90 years old and he was still very active and healthy. He was
managing many apartment complexes. So I asked him, what is your secret of longevity? He
told me, oh easy, nothing up here. So he doesn't keep anything in his mind. When we don't have
a lot of deluded thinking, our Buddha nature will naturally surface. Number two is peaceful
words. No slander or talk of the good or bad, strong and weak points of others. If you want
peace, do not speak ill of others. We do not want to make remarks about other people's
good or bad conduct or talk about the strong points or the shortcomings of others. When
we are judging others, usually we have affliction, either love or hate. Our only goal is to eradicate
our own afflictions. We are not so concerned about the right or wrong of others. You might
say, what is wrong with this.
with praising the strong points and good qualities of others isn't that good we should still be
discerning and see it's proper make sure we are not saying it to flatter we want to benefit them
in their cultivation want them to be liberated our heart must be straightforward and genuine
and if we are straightforward and genuine even if we scold someone in order to teach them that
doesn't break this precept so precept is all dependent on your intention we want to learn
the spirit of the precept which is to benefit and help all sentient beings there was a master
named Hong Yi he helped pure precepts whenever his disciples have afflictions or not getting along
having problem he would not say anything all he does is refrain from eating
you
when he did that everybody knew there's something wrong with the disciples sincerely confess their
sins that's when he would start eating so that is a great virtuous teacher number three is peaceful
thoughts we often say if there's no affliction inside then there is no problem outside all problem
comes from our own afflictions inside so we need to understand our afflictions here it point out four
major
afflictions first is jealousy we might be jealous of others who are doing better than us this is out
of our selfishness in the Bodhisattva precept it says a Bodhisattva should take the blame for others
and always let other people have the glory we should rejoice in other people's success and other
people's good cultivation number two is anger we do not want to disparage other people's faults number three
is no vaccine. We do not want to vax other cultivators to render them skeptical or remorseful
about their own practice. For example, we might say things like, all of you are far
away from the Bodhi or you will never be enlightened. These are all words that are sabotaging other
people's practice. This is a big offense. We do not want to cause any vaxation in other
cultivators. Number four is no contention. We do not want to discuss the Dharma for the
purpose of competition. We do not want to say Atharvada is better or Mahayana is better.
I'm a better cultivator. So all of these are competing. We do not want to have any kind
of contention with anyone. Always be in harmony and no argument. That's a true Bodhisattva.
All of these, they might be refined afflictions. They might be very subtle and unnoticeable
sometimes. True Bodhisattva, they will have very deep meditation and become very mindful
of their own affliction. They will see even the slightest impurities in their mind. Just
like we have a water filter. Before the holes are very big. They only filter the big pieces,
but now the filter is getting smaller.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
more refined we are able to detect even the smallest impurities in our mind so
always watch out for our afflictions how do we conquer these problems we can have
unreal meditations we just conjure up an image to overcome our jealousy of others
we should nurture the thinking of great compassion be compassionate for the
other person we want them to be happy rejoice in their success in order to
have no anger we should nurture the thinking that they are our benevolent
father love them like our father so we should not be angry not to vast other
cultivators think of them as great masters stay humble know that everyone
else is my master and we shouldn't have any contention nurture the thought of
equality
because we are all equal in our Buddha nature we want to be able to detect and
eradicate our afflictions
that's peaceful thought number four is peaceful vows bodhisattva always have
aspiration to be a saint to help all sentient beings here it points out two
ways one is to have great kindness to those who do not ask believe or
understand
number two
to have great compassion to those who do not hear, know, or realize the Dharma. So great
kindness is toward other cultivators. They already know and have been practicing for
a long time but they still might not ask you or believe you about the single vehicle of
the Mahayana Buddhism, about the Buddha nature. So we need to have great kindness in every
way we can to help them understand the Dharma. Then we should have great compassion toward
those who do not know the Dharma. It might be our family and friends. We should help
them because they have never heard of the Dharma and they don't know the Dharma and
they don't realize the Dharma. So they are suffering. We should feel their pain that
they don't know how to be liberated from reincarnation. We should try everything we can to help them
learn the Dharma.
To learn the Dharma and to learn Buddhism is all based on our kindness and compassion.
So it all brings us back to the overview which is staying in the stage of perseverance and
be gentle and tranquil.
Once upon a time there was a monkey who had great strength, wisdom, and a heart full of
kindness. One day while this monkey was climbing a tree, he saw a hunter who was trapped in
the deep valley.
The hunter was crying out for help. Wanting to rescue the hunter, the monkey climbed along
the cliff and reached the bottom of the valley. Then he carried the hunter on his back, climbed
through the rattan and bushes, and finally reached safe ground.
The hunter was trying to catch his breath while resting. He thought to himself, I am
really tired and starving. Let's just kill this monkey to feed myself. So he took a rock
and hit the monkey in the head.
The monkey was in shock, bled profusely, and was dying. Despite the ungrateful return of
his kindness, this monkey still managed to maintain a clear mind free of hatred. He felt
pity and compassion for the hunter and thought, today I cannot help him to get rid of his
evil ways, but I hope he will have the opportunity to meet a Buddha or Buddha.
Buddha or Bodhisattva one day to learn Buddhism, be liberated from anger and hatred, and attain
Buddhahood. So this is the Bodhisattva way, full of compassion and perseverance.
If we have these four peaceful practices, we will be able to have virtue and let other
people rely on us. Those people who are angry, when they see us, they will naturally feel
kind and loving, and those who are afraid, when they see you, they will feel secure and
protected. Those who are depressed, when they see you, they will feel happy and positive
and full of Dharma joy. Even poisonous animals, when they see you, they will feel gentle and
kind. So in order to have peace and happiness in this world, we must have peaceful deeds,
peaceful words, peaceful thoughts, and peaceful mind.
Thank you.
These four vows, this is actually practicing, and we will eventually attain compassion
samadhi. Then we know we are fully in accordance with our true nature, the pure enlightened
mind. So this is the secret to peace and happiness. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.