Today we are going to talk about cultivation.
Now we know we have the inherent enlightened mind, how do we bring it out?
We need to cultivate.
Cultivation is putting Buddha's teaching into practice on a continued and regular basis.
Masters often say, when cultivation has merit, the inherent will surface.
So according to the Tiantai sect of Buddhism, there are five ways to cultivate in order
to bring out our inherent enlightened mind.
Let's look at the five practices.
One, joy from according with the truth.
There are three things to do here.
One is to hear of the truth, two is to accord with the truth, and three is to be joyful.
Now let's look at what is the truth.
We have the one true mind, or we call it the single vehicle of Buddha's teaching.
It's the perfect teaching which tells us that we have the Buddha nature, the true mind,
or the suchness that's the same as all enlightened Buddha.
So in the Lotus Sutra, it gives a wonderful example.
This Buddha nature is a balance of the void and the unreal.
So it's called the mean or the middle way.
We need to enter the chamber of Tathagata, which is great compassion.
So the room of Buddha, that Buddha dwells in, is great compassion.
That is our middle way.
We need to wear the garment of Tathagata, which is gentleness and perseverance.
We naturally, wearing the clothes of gentleness and perseverance, we don't have any anger
in our Buddha nature.
And we need to sit in the seat of Tathagata, which is emptiness.
We need to sit in the seat of Tathagata, which is emptiness.
Dwell in the wisdom of emptiness, so that we will not be attached to worldly things.
So this is our true nature, that is called the inner truth.
We need to accord ourselves with this inner truth all the time, like tuning to the right
station of the radio, or typing the right address, so we get into the right website.
So align and accord ourselves with this inner truth.
Lastly, we need to be very joyful.
We need to be in a hysterical state.
We need to be in a state of happiness, to be dwelling in our inner essence.
And now we need to do five sub-practices.
Number one, repentance in principle and practice.
Repentance is changing the past and cultivating for the future.
So in principle, we don't really have any negative karma to repent.
We have to just be with our Buddha nature, be with our sessionist, and there's nothing
to repent.
But in practice, we have to be with our Buddha nature, and there's nothing to repent.
In practice, our six organs are always seeking external stimulation that is already creating
negative karma for us.
Anytime and anywhere, we need to repent because we're always seeking outside.
Number two, we need to be imploring.
We want to request the Buddha to remain in this world.
Just like if there's no student who wants to learn, then the teacher will not stay to
teach.
So Buddha is the teacher.
We need to sincerely want to cultivate, then we will have the dharma in this world.
So Buddha's teaching and wisdom is like a torch of light illuminating the world.
Without the dharma, without Buddha, this world will forever be in darkness.
So request the Buddha to remain in this world by our own cultivation.
Number three is rejoicing, to rejoice and congratulate and respect everyone's Buddha
nature.
We don't judge different schools of Buddhism or any other practices because everyone has
the same Buddha nature as us.
When someone is aligned with their inner truth, they will never feel envy or jealous toward
anyone.
They will always be rejoicing for other people's success and their practices.
Merit transference.
Every time we do any kind of merit or chant Buddha's name or do any kind of meditation
or do good deeds.
We want to dedicate this merit to all sentient beings.
We don't want to hack it up all for ourselves.
We want to give it to everybody else.
That way they will have good merits and they will be able to reduce their negative karmas.
A Bodhisattva always transferring merit to everyone.
When you transfer the merit, a little good kind deed will multiply into a big huge merit.
The magnitude of your transference is depending on how aligned you are with the Buddha.
To make vows, we want to make four great vows to save all sentient beings and all our afflictions.
To learn all the Dharma doors and we want to attain Buddhahood.
We constantly have to have these vows to motivate us to keep going, keep practicing and never
retrogress.
So bring the vows back to your inner self to contemplate your inner truth.
Every one of your thoughts is a sentient being.
That means you are a Buddha.
If you want to attain Buddhahood, you need to be saved.
We don't have any afflictions in our true Buddha nature.
Go back to your inner self and know that you don't have any afflictions.
And learn all the Dharma doors, all the wisdom and all Dharma's teaching are already in our
pure mind.
So we actually don't need to learn so much, you just have to dwell in your inner true
being.
And then you want to attain Buddhahood.
We already have the Buddha nature within us, so always bring your vows inward to your own
sense.
That's the five practices that will bring us joy from according with the truth.
So all this is doing is bringing out a single thought of willing acceptance of the inner
truth.
We just need this one single thought, one moment that you have this full willing acceptance
of the truth.
Every moment you are just wanting to align yourself with that one thought of total acceptance
of who you really are, your true self is omniscient, it's like a Buddha.
For example, if you have a boss that's always reprimanding you, at that moment he is yelling
at you, you have to bring yourself to this one single thought of willing acceptance.
You have to say to yourself, I have the Buddha nature within me.
I need to sit in the sea of emptiness.
My boss' harsh words are not real.
They are just attention.
They are temporary existence.
It's nothing for me to worry about and wear the garment of gentleness and perseverance.
I don't have an ounce of anger in me.
I'm always gentle and have perseverance.
So let go of all the anger, dwell in the chamber of great compassion.
My true mind, I have great compassion toward all beings, including my boss.
So when you are at this moment, one single thought of willing acceptance of your inner
being, then you are back to your self nature.
You are enlightened for that moment.
So practicing moment to moment, just like when we chant Amitabha Buddha's name, if we
accord with our inner inherent mind, we are Buddha for that moment.
And if moment to moment, we are dwelling in our inherent enlightened mind, we are Amitabha
Buddha moment to moment.
So that's how we practice from moment to moment.
2.
We need to read and recite the Mahayana Sutra, especially the Lotus Sutra.
Just by reading the Lotus Sutra, it's incredible merit because you are preserving the Dharma
of the single vehicle, like holding the Tathagata in respect on your head.
You are putting Buddha on your head.
That's how magnificent it is just to read the Dharma.
When we are reading, we are silencing our mind, following the words.
That is called the literary prajna, really tap into our inner truth, our true suchness.
Chanting and reciting is a very good habit to do it on a regular basis.
The Lotus Sutra has 28 chapters.
You can do one chapter a day for 30 days or half a year, or you can do different chapters
every day.
It's up to you how you want to read the Sutra, but you want to do it on a regular basis.
That was a big lesson.
There was a practitioner in the Song Dynasty.
He always said, life is just like someone who's traveling for a hundred years.
What is there to be contentious about?
He's very carefree.
He just reads the Lotus Sutra and Chant Amitabha Buddha's name every day.
And one day the universal worthy Bodhisattva appeared riding a six tusk white elephant
and spoke to him, Mr. Fan Yan, because you read the Lotus Sutra and Chant Amitabha Buddha's
name every day, soon you shall go to the Pure Land.
The next day he sat on a chair with his palms joined together.
He Chant Buddha's name and went to the Pure Land.
So by reading the Lotus Sutra, it's like osmosis of our true suchness.
So it's a great practice.
Number three is teaching the Dharma.
Not only do we have to read, we have to teach it to others.
You don't have to be a monk to do it.
You don't have to be a monk to teach the Dharma.
You just have to let people know about this single truth.
All you have to say is, did you know that your true mind is the same as Amitabha's true
mind?
Just one mind and there's no difference at all.
That's all you have to say.
That will help others to know, oh, I'm the same as Amitabha.
It will give people faith and to know what is real chanting, what is real enlightenment.
And you know, teaching the Dharma really help us conform to the Dharma.
You know, we have to be wise, we have to be good in our own way.
We have to be wise in our own way.
But we also have to be able to perform our own understanding as well.
We want to teach the Dharma in accordance with the questioner's capacity.
Everybody's understanding and capabilities are different.
So you want to teach accordingly.
Tailor your answers toward everybody's differences.
You use illustrations or examples and stories to make them understand.
You don't expound the Dharma, just what you want to say.
You only say things to make them really understand and to feel joy in their heart by asking the
Dharma.
That's all you have to say.
Number four is learning.
heart by understanding. Number four is practicing the six pyramidas simultaneously. So our main
practice is still contemplating on our true suchness. That's our main practice all the time.
So that's your major. But now you have a minor. You want to practice the six pyramidas to help
others. We want to be giving, have whole precepts, have endurance, have diligence, concentration,
and wisdom. If you're aligned with your true suchness, your pure mind, you will realize that
giving is natural because there is no greediness whatsoever in your true mind. And holding precepts
would be simple because in your true mind is incapable of breaking the precepts. Endurance is
easy because in your Buddha nature, there's not an ounce of anger in you. Diligence is usual because
you don't have an ounce of anger in you. And you don't have an ounce of anger in you. And you
don't have an ounce of laziness in you. Concentration is effortless because your true mind is always
focused and never scattered. And your wisdom is natural. Without any ignorance, you're perfectly
enlightened and have great wisdom. So when you're aligned with your true mind, your pure suchness,
you can practice the six pyramidas naturally. Number five, correctly practicing the six
pyramidas. Now you can double major because
your contemplation of your inner truth is now very mature you're able to help others and do the six
pyramidas correctly now that your self-cultivation and teaching of others both totally fulfilled
in principle and practice your true mind is unhindered you're able to control all your
delusions we have five delusions according to the tian tai teaching the first one is delusion
of view the second one is delusion of thought in the world of desire the third one is also
the delusion of thought but in the world of form fourth one is also the delusion of thought in the
world of formless and the last one is the delusion of ignorance so now you're able to control all
five delusions because of your practice this is called the five preliminary stages of disciples
you're able to control all five delusions because of your practice this is called the
five preliminary stages of disciples the sixth one is the delusion of thought but in the world of form as
After this stage, we become true Bodhisattva entering the 52 stages of Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.