Today we are going to talk about Consciousness Only.
Everything is created by our mind alone.
We are going to look at the three kinds of states,
three modes of knowledge and three moral natures.
First, let's look at our Eight Consciousness.
We have the Eye Consciousness,
Ears Consciousness,
Nose,
Tongue,
Body.
These five experience the external world,
sight,
sound,
smell,
taste,
and touch.
Then we have the Six Consciousness,
the Mind Consciousness,
that discriminate and have perception.
Then we have the Seventh Consciousness,
which is the Mindless Consciousness.
It perceives the Eight Consciousness as the Self.
Then we have the Laya Consciousness,
which is the big storehouse that stores all our karmic seeds.
All Eight Consciousness can be aligned with these three kinds of states,
three modes of knowledge,
and three moral natures.
Three kinds of states are the perceived objects of our mind.
The three modes of knowledge are the subject,
the thinking mind that perceives the objects.
First look at the three kinds of states.
The first state is Real State.
It's the truthful state that is happening right now in front of us.
For example, our eyes,
sees,
ears,
hears,
nose,
smells,
tongue,
taste,
and body,
touches.
All these at the very first instance.
That is called the Real State.
But this state is only the first instance
when you have no thoughts at all.
For example, you see a house.
Before you even have the idea that this is a house,
before you give it a name,
that is called the Real State.
We hardly ever see this Real State.
Once we start discriminating,
once we start thinking,
and give a name,
labeling,
give it stereotyping,
then it's called the Distorted State.
So this state,
the Real State,
is no longer real.
It's now distorted.
It's transposed by our thoughts.
Because our first five consciousness,
the second instance,
is already working together with the sixth consciousness
because they are in intimate connection with each other.
The first five cannot really function by themselves.
They always have to work with the sixth consciousness.
Therefore, the sixth consciousness grabs onto
the shadows of the first five consciousnesses
and it creates an image in its mind.
So we only experience the Distorted State
in our sixth consciousness.
We never really see the Real State that is outside.
So we're always living in a Distorted State
which has our own thinking,
our own perception.
And this Distorted State includes our seventh consciousness.
The seventh consciousness,
only cares about the eighth consciousness.
It doesn't go outside to experience the world.
It only takes the perceiver of the eighth consciousness
as the self.
So its object is the image of the self.
But this is already a Distorted State.
Number three,
we have the Imagined State.
This state is only imagined by our sixth consciousness.
Even without the help of
the first five consciousnesses,
we don't have to experience the world.
We can be thinking all the time.
This includes our memory.
It's kind of like the Distorted State
but it's actually only an Imagined State
because nothing is in front of you.
You can remember things from a long time ago.
For example,
a lot of people remember the childhood abuse
or someone who has done us wrong
and we remember it for our whole life.
And it will give us anxiety,
fear,
or emotional burden.
Most of us,
we only live in our Imagined State.
Our mind is mostly negative in its thoughts.
Imagined State includes our dreams,
hallucinating,
or daydreaming.
That's all Imagined State.
As you can see,
we want to be in the Real State.
Enlightened beings are saying
they are usually in the Real State.
They're always right here, right now.
Someone asked the Zen Master,
how do we know if we're enlightened?
The Master said,
eat when you're hungry,
sleep when you're drowsy,
then you're enlightened.
Most of us,
we cannot eat when we're hungry.
We always have to discriminate.
This food is good or bad.
It's too salty.
It's too sweet.
It's too bland.
Keep giving opinions.
You can never eat as it is.
And we can't really fall asleep
when we go to bed
because we keep thinking.
A lot of us cannot accept
and work with the reality.
We lose our peace and equanimity.
But a Zen Master or Enlightened Being,
they look like average person,
but their mind is always at peace
because they always live in the emptiness awareness.
They are not giving judgment about things.
They always live without vaccines.
They don't have any attachments.
Now let's look at the three modes of knowledge.
The subject,
the perceiver.
Our perceiver can have three modes.
The first mode is veridical,
which is the truth,
genuine,
the fact,
not illusory.
So it always go with the real state.
Veridical is the state we want to be in
when we are meditating.
That's right here and right now.
If we're having wandering thoughts,
then it's no longer the veridical state.
We want to bring ourselves to the breathing,
to the present moment,
to the name Amitabha.
That's when we are right here and right now.
You know who else is always in the state?
Babies.
So we should learn from babies.
When they're hungry, they eat.
When they are sleepy, they sleep.
They do not discriminate much
and they do not think too much.
That is actually
the best state of mind.
We have inference
when we are having assumptions
about situations
and we have logical thinking.
When we are analyzing,
when we're planning,
when we're studying,
that's the state of inference.
When we assume correctly,
it's called inference.
When we assume incorrectly,
it's called fallacy.
It's wrong.
For example,
the seventh consciousness,
thinking that the perceiver
of the eighth consciousness
is the self,
that is a fallacy
because there's no actual thing as self.
The seventh consciousness
perceives incorrectly.
It's a false self.
We all live in this false self.
That's why we are always living
in the mode of fallacy.
We experience the world
from the point of view of the self.
The seventh consciousness
is always influencing
and telling the sixth consciousness
what to think.
All our emotion is based on
how tainted and polluted
our seventh consciousness is.
So the distorted state
can be inference or fallacy.
The imagined state
can be inference and fallacy
or veridical sometimes
when you're in meditation.
There is a Chinese fable
called
Cup Bowl Snake Reflection.
There is a person
named Wen Gong.
He went to his friend's house.
The friend gave him a cup of tea.
In the cup of tea,
all of a sudden,
he saw a little snake.
But he doesn't want to hurt
his friend's feelings,
so he drank the whole cup of tea.
After he went home,
he felt very sick.
A lot of doctors tried to heal him,
but nobody can help him.
The friend asked him
to come back to his house again.
So he went back
and he sat in the same seat.
In the cup of tea,
there is a snake again.
He was scared,
and he told his friend,
oh my god,
there is a snake in my tea.
His friend said,
look,
there is actually
a bowl hanging on the wall
behind the chair.
The snake is only
the reflection of the bowl.
Wen Gong felt very silly,
and he no longer felt sick.
So his mind is taking
the distorted state,
and he is living
in the mode of fallacy.
So this is a perfect example
of how our mind
affects our body.
Whatever we think,
it will affect how we are.
Be careful of our thoughts.
The subject and the object,
together,
we will have three kinds of thoughts.
It's called the three moral natures.
We can have wholesome thoughts,
unwholesome thoughts,
and neutral thoughts.
The first five consciousnesses
can have all three natures,
wholesome, unwholesome,
or neutral.
The first five,
they have minimal ability
to have wholesome
or unwholesome thoughts.
Mostly,
it's working together
with the sixth consciousness
that has these three modes.
The first five consciousnesses,
they are mostly in the neutral mode,
which is not wholesome
and not unwholesome.
Wholesome means
we are benefiting others
now and in the future.
Unwholesome means
we are harming others
now and in the future.
Neutral means
it's not wholesome
and not unwholesome.
For example,
when we're bored,
we're not doing anything.
We're just standing there
or we're just daydreaming
or we're just sleeping.
But that is still
a kind of ignorance.
You will still create
negative karma
because you're not doing things
to help yourself
being enlightened
or helping others
or doing good deeds.
We all have these three natures
of thoughts.
The key is
we want to know
what we are doing
and what we are not doing.
So,
the first five consciousnesses,
we will have
these three natures
of thoughts.
The key is
we want to stay wholesome.
So anytime
when we're positive,
we're faithful,
we're cheerful,
we're grateful,
when we are unwholesome,
any negative emotion
when we're depressed,
we're stressed,
we're fearful,
we have anxiety,
bitter,
angry,
jealous,
that's all
unwholesome thoughts.
Wholesome thoughts
will create
wholesome deeds
and wholesome karma.
Unwholesome thoughts
will create
unwholesome deeds
and unwholesome karma.
So,
every thought
has effect.
All these,
they are collected
in the
Alaya consciousness
as karmic seeds.
When the conditions ripen,
they ripen
into results,
into the world
that we experience.
So,
all the outside world
is created
by our
Alaya consciousness.
This is a big cycle
of reincarnation.
Everything is created
by our mind
and everything
is experienced
by our mind.
Nothing is really
outside of our mind.
That's why
it's called
consciousness only.
So,
realize
that
all
the consciousness
are empty
in nature.
They are
the deluded mind.
This is not
our original self.
We are
actually
the enlightened
mind
that is
without
the A consciousness.
All the A consciousness
are
purified
into wisdom
and we
are empty
in nature.
That's our
true suchness.
We want to
bring ourselves
to the state
of true
veridical
and real state.
Even all these
are empty
in nature.
You want to
bring back
the state
of true emptiness.
That is
Nirvana
or
enlightenment.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.