Today we will be talking about Tranquility and Insight Meditation.
Tranquility is about the calmness of our mind and Insight is about the clarity of our mind.
In other words, one is concentration, one is wisdom.
We need both of these in order to become enlightened.
Like two wings of a bird, they are complementary and inseparable.
Today we will be learning about five Tranquility Meditations and three corresponding Insight Meditations.
The first Tranquility Meditation is contact the mind with an object.
Our mind is forever busy thinking, so we need to give it something to focus on, a designated object.
For example, your breathing or the name Amitabha.
When you focus on your breathing, you can focus your attention on the tip of your nose,
or you can focus on this area between your nose and your mouth, this free space here.
Feel the air in and out of the space.
That way you can go into a deep concentration.
Some people say, I cannot find my breath, so what do I do?
It's very easy. The trick is not to chase after your breathing.
The trick is to relax, stay put, and let your breathing come loose.
It's very easy.
The second Tranquility Meditation is looking for you.
And sure enough, it would be easy and effortless.
So have a gentle, simple, calm, and beautiful mind, and meditation would be natural and easy.
So this is like keeping a wild monkey under lock.
Our mind is like a wild monkey.
It's forever busy jumping around thinking.
So we need to lock it with our breathing or lock it with the name Amitabha.
The third one is stop the mind from following scattered thoughts.
Even if you have a designated object of meditation, it will still run around.
So the monkey is wild. It's not that good.
So what you need to do is to do the second meditation is to observe your mind.
Have the ability to be mindful of your thoughts.
We have this habitual continuous thinking.
We need to break this chain, break this habit of scattered thoughts.
Be aware of it. Let go of the thought.
Focus back on your breathing and on your object of meditation.
So this requires intense training.
Training every day is like shooting arrows.
When you have intense training and you work hard every day, you'll be able to shoot the bull's eye.
So we need to learn how to master our mind.
Our mind is a master of our five senses.
Our eyes, our ears, our nose, our tongue, our body.
The mind is the master of the five organs.
When we control our mind, let it come back in and stay with our quiet mind,
then we will no longer be outside all the time, clinging onto the world.
So learn to master your mind by stopping shattering thoughts
and focus on your breathing, on your object of meditation.
Number three is cessation of the true essence of reality.
The first two are techniques.
Three, four, five are the theories behind the techniques.
Number three is to stop your mind on the reality of things, which is emptiness.
Everything is conditioned existence.
Therefore, they don't have the essence.
They are empty of a controlling self.
Everything in your life right now, they are borrowed from conditions.
Your husband, your children, your career, your money, your car.
Everything is borrowed from conditions.
It means your karma, your good and bad karma.
Everything is borrowed.
When everything is borrowed, that means you don't own anything.
You don't have possession of anything.
It's only a temporary existence.
So realize this emptiness.
This emptiness is great.
It will free you from the concept of an ego and a self.
If you ever think about it,
and a lot of us, we use our children as our tool to confront ourselves.
If our kids are doing great and doing great,
and doing very well,
we are very proud because we are great parents.
Or our husband or spouse loves us a lot.
We feel worthy of love.
Or we have a lot of money.
Or we have success.
We confront and nourish our ego.
But we actually don't need these things to confront the ego.
Because the ego itself is an illusion.
We don't have a perceived self.
So emptiness means empty of a self,
of an ego that we are grabbing onto.
So be detached from everything.
Know that it's all conditioned existence.
And it doesn't really affect your true existence,
your true self.
This is a great meditation for us to do.
And the related inside meditation is in red.
So it's a contemplation of emptiness.
So it's basically the same thing.
But cessation is more about stopping,
calming the mind of all the wandering thoughts.
Contemplation is more about gaining wisdom.
So it's a different focus.
But the theory is the same.
We need to do both of these.
If you keep focusing on emptiness,
not just doing meditation,
but through every day of your life,
think of your life.
Know that this is a dream.
Then you will no longer be so attached.
You will no longer have so much love and hate
and so caught up with the happiness and the pain.
It's all just a conditioned existence.
Focus back on your meditation.
By doing this,
you're breaking the chain of samsara.
You're breaking the chain of reincarnation.
When we have the self and the ego,
and we're following everything that's going on in the world,
we are following the current of samsara,
of reincarnation.
But if we think about emptiness,
focus on non-self and conditioned existence,
we are swimming against the current of samsara.
So just focusing on this for ten minutes and five minutes,
you are ending samsara.
It's great that we have this wisdom
and Buddha taught this to us.
So always focus and see the world in this light.
See the world as a dream.
See the world as non-existing essence.
That's the key of wisdom of living.
Number four is
cessation on the expedient means
in accordance with conditioned.
So four is opposite of three.
Not focusing so much on the emptiness,
but focusing on all the conditioned existence.
Even though the true nature,
the essence is empty,
but it still has a temporary existence.
Everybody in your life right now,
they are still here.
And their suffering is still real.
So a bodhisattva,
use the conditioned existence
as expedient means
to nourish and boost your compassion,
to really cultivate
and to love everyone
and contribute to the world.
For example, right now our conditioned is
we have the coronavirus on this earth right now.
So what you can do is use this conditioned
to bring out your compassion
when you meditate.
This is actually go with the contact meditation.
So you contact with the object of the visualization.
Basically in your meditation,
you visualize sincerely
that every human being is free from coronavirus
and everybody has happiness,
health and safety.
So if you keep visualizing on it,
it will become reality.
The power of our mind is amazing.
Even though everything is empty,
but the power of our mind can create miracles.
Our mind, our thoughts create reality.
So do positive thinking.
Do visualization.
This is not the ultimate me,
but this is the expedient me.
So use our conditioned wisely
to really bring out our compassion,
our great vow and our diligence.
So the corresponding inside meditation
is called contemplation of unreal existence.
The key is existence.
Even though everything is unreal,
but they do exist right now.
So you can think of
a lot of things to help you
with your cultivation.
You can even visualize Amitabha Buddha,
his light shining upon everyone.
And you can even visualize the Pure Land,
how it has the palm of seven jewels
with the water of eight merits.
You can use your mind to make miracles come true.
The more vividly you think about this meditation,
the more it will come alive.
It will become reality.
Believe in the power of your mind
and use and borrow the conditions right now
to boost your vibration
and you can contribute to the world.
Number five is cessation
that avoids two extremes
and develop the right insight on the middle way.
So it's now the balance of three and four.
So we stop our mind,
we quiet our mind
by avoiding the two extremes.
The emptiness and the conditioned existence
So some people are too extreme into the emptiness.
This is more like the Theravada Buddhist
because it's so much about emptiness,
impermanence and suffering.
We might be very empathetic about the world.
We might not have the great compassion
to save all sentient beings.
So that's one extreme.
The other extreme is Bodhisattvas.
They're too involved in saving everybody
in this current condition
and they're too caught up
and they have no more wisdom.
So both of these extremes are not good.
We want to avoid them
and develop the right insight
which is without the two extremes
but recognize the inside of emptiness
and the inside of conventional existence.
Then that's the middle way.
When you're able to balance the two,
that's great wisdom.
And that's how Buddha thinks.
So think from the perspective of Buddha.
That's how Buddha sees the world.
Buddha sees the middle way.
So Buddha is able to
accord with all conditions
but never change,
remain steadfast
while according with all conditions.
So don't you want to be just like Buddha?
And we can all do it
because we all inherit
with the middle way,
with the suchness,
with our true mind
and our true essence.
So number five is actually
stopping the mind meditation
because you want to stop the mind
from going to the two extremes.
The two extremes are now
the scattered thoughts.
You don't want to be too empty
and you don't want to be too caught up
in the worldly existence.
The related inside meditation
is called contemplation of the means.
Always stay with the middle way.
Always stay with balance
of the inside emptiness
and conventional existence.
So that's how Buddha thinks.
That's how we should be thinking.
So we should reside in this mentality
at all times.
In conclusion,
tranquility and inside meditation
is already inherited in our true mind,
our true self.
Our mind is both cohesed
and yet ever shining with awareness.
Both shining with awareness
and yet ever cohesed.
So our mind is cohesed
that means it has tranquility.
It's quiet and calm and all move
but it's ever shining with awareness.
It can see everything clearly.
You can think of yourself like a mirror.
Reflect everything clearly.
Everything that's happening in your life
is the image in the mirror
but it doesn't affect you.
All the love and hate,
happiness and sorrow in the mirror
is just going on conditionally.
You do your best
but you're the mirror
that's not affected by what's going on
in the image,
in the reflection.
Live in this mentality
that is how Buddha thinks.
And if you chant Amitabha Buddha's name
and recite in this mentality
then that's the true Buddha remembrance Samadhi.
The goal of our Pure Land practice.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.