Today's topic is the Bodhi Mind.
It means to bring forth the Bodhi resolve to be self-enlightened and to enlighten others.
We will use chapter 11 of the Avatamsaka Sutra to learn how to generate Bodhi resolve in our daily lives.
This chapter has 141 verses. We will only look at four in terms of walking, standing, sitting, and lying down.
Let's first look at walking.
When walking on the road, I felt that sentient beings were roaming the pure Dharma realm, their minds free and unhindered.
This Huayin school of Buddhism, it talks about the Dharma realms.
There are fourfold Dharma realms or called the Dharma Tattoo.
Number one, the Dharma realm of phenomenon. That's the physical world of existence that we experience.
Number two is the Dharma realm of the noumenon. That means the principle or the inner truth or we call the mind.
Number three is the Dharma realm of non-obstruction.
The Dharma realm of non-obstruction between the phenomenon and the noumenon, which means everything is created by the mind.
So all phenomena is created by the noumenon.
All phenomena are expression of the mind.
They cannot be separated. So there's no obstruction between them.
Number four is the Dharma realm of non-obstruction among phenomena.
All phenomena mutually contain each other.
Inside all matters is everything else.
It is called the perfect infusion or balance without any contradiction or conflicts.
This is the world that is the reality of the one mind.
This is the actual world of existence.
So when we are walking, when we make a sincere vow, then this vow will actually benefit all sentient beings.
Because this vow penetrates throughout the Dharma realm.
And empty spaces.
There's no limitation of our mind in terms of space or time.
Our mind is boundless.
In this Dharma realm, all sentient beings merges together.
You in me, I in you.
In a cold winter morning, a lady went to the deli to get a hot toasted bagel for breakfast.
After she got out of the deli, she saw a poor old man sitting at the bus stop.
Knowing it will probably be his only hot meal for the day, she gave him the bagel.
Another customer in the deli side came out and gave her half of her bagel.
So we should all love and be kind to each other because we are really together as one.
The concept of the Dharma Tattoo is to help us expand and enlarge the measure of our mind.
Because we are really interconnected.
That's why we use the metaphor of the Indra's net.
Indra is the heavenly king that casts a vast net down the mountain that extends in all directions infinitely.
Each knot of the net actually contains a jewel.
And each jewel contains and reflects the other jewels.
It's a complex web of reflections.
We call this the cosmos of infinite rounds upon rounds.
So that's why we call this the pure Dharma realm.
Next, standing.
When I entered a residence, I felt that sentient beings will enter the Buddha vehicle and equal the Buddhas of the three periods of time.
When I stand and enter a home, hope everyone will enter the Buddha vehicle.
There are three general vehicles.
One is the vehicle of the Shravaka.
Two is the vehicle of the Pratyekabuddha.
These two practice for self-enlightenment.
Number three is the vehicle of Bodhisattva.
Practicing for the enlightenment.
Practicing for the enlightenment of others.
Best yet is the Buddha vehicle which is about the one mind or the Dharma realm of one reality.
That's the true mind because we all have the Buddha nature that's already present in us.
So practicing is easy.
In this sutra, it says as soon as a Bodhisattva has the initial resolve to achieve Buddhahood, he becomes a Buddha at once.
That's the incredibleness of our mind.
It also says the initial resolve and seeking of the ultimate realization have no difference.
However, to arise the initial resolve in the mind at the beginning is much more challenging than the latter,
which means that a novice Bodhisattva is the same as a mature Bodhisattva who is about to reach final enlightenment.
The initial resolve is actually harder and more powerful.
It's not precious to have.
So that is just to tell us we should really practice this every day because our initial resolve is very important.
And then you will realize you are actually the Buddha.
If we recite the Amitabha Sutra, it talks about the Buddhas of the six directions of the east, south, west, north, below, and above.
They are exalting Amitabha's Pure Land.
You might think, oh, this has nothing to do with me.
We just recite it.
But this actually means that there are infinite number of Buddha worlds with infinite number of Buddhas.
And all these Buddhas, they are us.
We are the Buddhas.
That's the meaning of the Sutra.
So we actually equal to the Buddhas of all three periods of time and the ten directions.
Next is sitting.
When sitting upright and proper, I felt that sentient beings will sit on the Bodhi seat with no attachments in their mind.
So we want to sit on the Bodhi seat.
The Bodhi seat means awakening.
When we have no more attachment to the world, that's awakening.
To know that all forms are illusions, that's how we are awakened.
In the Sutra, it talks about a young man, Sudhana, his quest for enlightenment.
He visited 53 teachers.
One of them was actually a young boy and a girl.
The boy is named Virtue.
Born.
And the girl is named Virtue.
Obtained.
They live in a beautiful city full of gardens, beautiful fragrant flowers, green hills, and clear water flowing through the courtyard.
But that's how they realize everything in the world is illusory.
That's how they reach enlightenment.
Because they know everything is impermanent and it's just cause and conditions.
So that's what they taught Sudhana.
So we need to know everything is unreal.
That's how we will have no more attachment.
When we are sitting in meditation, if we're thinking about the trouble at work, then the entire dharma realm is at work.
If we're thinking about the friend that's far away that is sick, then the entire world is over there being worried.
When we are not present, our mind is minute and it becomes petty.
But if we be in the present moment.
In the present moment, focusing on the object of meditation, such as the name Amitabha.
The name actually is in every household, every city, every country, all the Buddha worlds, and everywhere.
Because our mind is boundless.
It has no obstructions.
You will know you are in Amitabha's Pure Land at this moment.
Lastly, lying down.
When it's time to sleep and rest, I felt that sentient beings will be peaceful and secure.
In their bodies and not be moved or confused in their minds.
When we're going to bed, we also want to make vows to help all sentient beings feel safe and calm.
When our vows are sincere, at that moment, we are really helping millions of people that are having insomnia, depression, or anxiety.
When our mind sees true emptiness, then it's free to create wondrous existence.
That's the incredible nature of our mind.
This is also called meditation.
This is called the Ocean Seal Samadhi.
The calm ocean water symbolizes our pure mind.
When it's calm, it reflects everything as it is, like a clear mirror.
However, when the wind of ignorance starts blowing, the surface of the water becomes agitated.
It can no longer reflect clearly.
So we need to be unmoved and stop the wind of ignorance.
Restore the calmness of the water.
Then the water becomes a seal.
Or a stamp that reflects everything like a copy.
Exactly.
That's when we create wondrous existence.
In conclusion, our mind is the dhamma realm of one reality.
It is incredible liberation.
When we make sincere vows in our daily actions, such as walking, standing, sitting, and lying down, we are experiencing life as a Buddha.
When we practice one verse of the sutra,
we are actually practicing the sutra in its entirety.
We unite and merge with the sutra completely.
You are really a Buddha and all your bodhi vows and wishes will come true.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.