Today we are going to talk about this precious life.
Most of us never stop to think about how precious our lives are.
Hopefully this class will help us to realize the value of this life.
We have a verse in Buddhism. It says,
It is rare to be reborn as human, but I am living as one now.
It is difficult to encounter the Dharma, but I have come across it now.
If I do not cultivate this lifetime, when would I have a chance to be liberated?
It is rare to be reborn as a human being.
Buddha said it is very difficult to have the human rebirth.
Buddha gives the example of a blind turtle.
As if there is a plank floating in the vast ocean,
and there is a hole in the middle of this plank.
The chance of us reincarnating as a human is as rare as a blind sea turtle
who is surfacing above water once every 100 years,
coincidentally its head poking through the hole of this plank.
That's the chance of us becoming a human again.
The second example is thread needle.
As if we cast a thread down the mountain,
and when it reaches the bottom, it threads through the eye of a needle.
Buddha gave another metaphor, a handful of soil.
One day Buddha was teaching his disciples.
He grabbed a handful of soil and asked his disciples,
Is there more soil in my hand or on the ground?
A disciple replied, There is more soil on the ground.
Buddha proclaimed,
To have the human rebirth is like the soil in my hand.
To lose the human rebirth is like the soil on the ground.
The number of humans compared to all other sentient beings are very small.
But there's billions of people on this earth.
How can that be?
But if you think about it, there's a lot more bugs, plants, and organisms on this earth than there are humans.
So we know that the number of humans are very small
relative to all other sentient beings.
So why is it so important to be a human?
Because if you're an animal, you don't have the wisdom to cultivate.
If you're in the hungry ghost or hell realm,
you are having too much suffering to cultivate.
And if you're a heavenly being or in the asura realm,
you are too happy to cultivate.
Only humans have sorrows and happiness.
We have just enough so we can cultivate this lifetime.
And we have three things that are better
than heavenly beings.
One is our memory.
We can remember what we did wrong
and we can reflect and change our ways.
Number two, we can hold precepts and learn to be virtuous.
And number three, we are very diligent.
We can diligently practice.
These three things were actually better than heavenly beings.
All the Buddhas, they became Buddhas in the human realm.
So it's very precious that we have this human life right now.
It is difficult to imagine
to encounter the Dharma,
but I have come across it now.
Buddha is not here right now,
so it's very difficult to hear the Dharma.
Now we still have the Dharma,
but to hear the Dharma and to believe the Dharma
and actually practice it,
it is actually very rare.
We are very blessed to have this opportunity.
That means we already cultivated many lives before.
We have to treasure the Dharma that we have right now.
Especially we know of the Pure Land Buddhism
that is like winning the lottery.
In the commentary of Amitabha Sutra by Ohi Master,
he said to recite Amitabha Buddha's name
and to go to the Western Pure Land,
we immediately have the certain complete attainment
of the three non-regressions.
One, precision.
Two, practice.
Three, mindfulness.
Non-regression is never fall back.
First, we will never fall back in our position.
We will always be an art hat
who is a saint,
who already got rid of the ego
and have no more self.
We will never fall less than a saint,
than an art hat.
So that's the non-regression of precision.
Number two, we will never fall back
in our Bodhisattva practice.
Here, we are always falling back.
When we try to help someone,
when someone yells at us
and we don't want to do it anymore
because we give up.
But over there,
we will never diminish in our Bodhi resolve
and our compassion for all sentient beings.
So we'll never fall back in our Bodhisattva practice
and our Bodhi resolve.
Number three,
we will never fall back in our mindfulness.
Our every thought is like a Buddha.
We enter the ocean of all knowledge.
That's the Buddha's wisdom.
In all other practices,
these are three different stages of Bodhisattva.
But in Pure Land Buddhism,
by reciting Amitabha Buddha's name,
we have all three of these all at once.
It's like you are going to elementary school,
high school and college all at one time.
Why?
That's because of the ultimate reality
of the true nature of the mind
and the special effect of reciting Buddha's name
and the great vows of Amitabha.
Because of these three inconceivable powers,
that's why we can have certain complete attainment
of the three non-regressions all at once.
That's the amazing thing about the Pure Land Buddhism.
If I do not cultivate this lifetime,
we really need to cultivate right now,
this lifetime.
According to the visualization sutra,
it says if you want to go to the Western Pure Land
with the highest grade of lotus flower,
you have to have this pure land.
These three minds.
One is the most sincere mind.
Two, the mind of deep faith.
Three, aspiring rebirth by transferring merits.
Number one, most sincere mind.
This mind is without any wandering thoughts,
wholeheartedly at the present moment,
chanting the Buddha's name.
You are no longer caught up with the worldly dramas
and the entanglements of the world.
You are fully residing
in your spiritual practice,
chanting the Amitabha Buddha's name,
and you are with your Buddha nature.
That is called the most sincere mind.
We also have the mind of deep faith.
This faith is so strong that you're full of joy
every time you chant Buddha's name.
It's the goodness of all goodness,
the virtue of all virtue.
You love to chant.
You can recite the Buddha's name
when you are sick,
when you are dreaming in your sleep,
and when you're dying.
How do we know we really have this in our head?
It's when you first wake up in the morning
and your first thought is Amitabha.
That means you are pretty much there.
So that's the deep faith.
Number three is aspiring rebirth by transferring merits.
To transfer all the merit to all sentient beings.
Every Amitabha is for all sentient beings
because that's the same heart as Amitabha.
He created the Pure Land for us.
The Pure Land for us to become Buddha.
We should have the same great compassion
as Amitabha Buddha.
Last year, my aunt who has lung cancer
and stroke was in the hospital.
Her life was in danger.
All the doctors said there's nothing to do for her.
She's going to die any moment.
So we decided to take her back home.
Immediately when she arrived,
she started opening her eyes
and started talking to us.
We weren't sure what's going on,
but we were all chanting Amitabha.
Amitabha Buddha's name single-mindedly.
And every day she started getting better.
Now it's already May and she's still fine.
Through this whole experience,
what I learned is she is like a bodhisattva
that brought out the three minds in me.
I brought out my most sincere mind.
I have nothing else on my mind for those days.
I only thought about her and chanting for her.
And it brought out the mind of deep faith.
I completely relied on Amitabha Buddha.
If her time is up,
please take her to the Pure Land.
If it's not her time yet,
please make her recover.
So I completely trusted Amitabha.
And that's all I did every day is to chant for her.
So that's my deep faith.
And I brought out my great compassion.
I dedicated all my merits to her,
hoping it will help her to go to the Pure Land or recover.
And sure enough, there was a miracle.
So we should use life situation
to bring out our three minds.
Lastly, if I don't cultivate now,
when would I have a chance to be liberated?
We need to seize this opportunity to practice.
This is our last chance.
There's no more tries.
Buddha often gave the metaphor of the four types of horses.
The first type of horse,
when they see the shadow of the whip,
they start running.
That's as if someone who hears the Dharma
immediately knows that they should cultivate diligently.
The second type of horse,
when the whip barely grazes over the horse's hair,
it knows to start running.
That's the second type of people
who actually see people that are dying and suffering,
they know they should start cultivating.
The third kind of horse is
when the whip cuts through the flesh,
it starts running.
These are like people who already have their loved ones
suffering,
sick,
and dying.
That's when they start practicing.
The last kind of horse is
when the whip already pierces through the bone,
as if we are already sick ourselves,
and we are already dying.
Then we start practicing.
What kind of horse will you be?
Do you want to cultivate now,
or do you want to wait until your last moment?
Treasure this life that we have.
Don't be depressed or upset
about your current life situation.
It's all secondary.
What's most important is your own enlightenment,
is you going to the Pure Land
and becoming a Buddha.
In the Amitabha Sutra,
it says no one can be born in the Pure Land
with minor good roots,
blessings,
virtues,
and causal connections,
which means we need to have a lot of good roots,
merits,
and good conditions
in order to be born in the Pure Land.
We have all of that right now.
We are human,
and we believe in the Pure Land chanting,
and we are actually practicing it.
So we got ample of good roots right now.
We just need to hold on to our practice
and never give up,
and no matter what happens,
we just keep practicing until our last day.
Buddha will pick the time.
He will come take us to His Pure Land.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.