Today we are going to talk about eradicate desires.
The purpose of being a Buddhist is to reach Buddhahood.
How do we cultivate into Buddhahood?
Dedication is actually a process of eradicating our desires.
How do we do that on a daily basis?
In the Flower Adornment Sutra, it says when tempted by the five desires, vow that all
living beings will pull out the arrows of cravings and attain the ultimate peace.
This is Bodhisattva Manjushri praying for all sentient beings.
He vowed that myself and all sentient beings will pull out the arrows of cravings.
The cravings and desires are like poisonous arrows.
We think having all these desires will make us happy, but it's actually harming us.
So we need to pull out the arrows.
That's how we attain ultimate peace.
So the ultimate peace is actually free ourselves from desires.
So what are the five desires?
The first is wealth.
We spend a lot of time trying to make money, trying to buy that big house, that fancy car,
the latest gadgets, because we think that's perfect life.
But if we spend all our time trying to have these material goods, we don't develop spiritually.
We're wasting our life on these material goods that's unreal.
Confucius' best student is Yan Hui.
Yan Hui is a Buddhist.
Yan Hui is extremely poor.
He used the bamboo skin as his bowl.
He used the melon shell as his spoon, and he lives off the street corner.
Confucius says nobody can endure the suffering he's going through, but he is the happiest
person alive.
Why?
Because he found his spiritual self.
He found his soul.
He found his perfect virtue, wisdom, and compassion.
That's how he found his happiness.
So get rid of our material desires.
That's how we can reach our spiritual enlightenment.
Second is the desire of lust.
All of us have sexual desires.
That's why we are always reincarnating, living the samsara life.
That's the biggest problem.
Shurigami Sutra, it talks about a practitioner named Bhukushini.
Bhukushini, he has strong intense lust.
There was a Buddha named King of Emptiness.
He says anyone who has lustful desires, their body will be a raging mass of fire.
So the Buddha taught him to contemplate on the coolness and the warmness found throughout
his entire body.
So when we have lust, our temperature rise.
When we let go of the desire, it cools down.
Bhukushini keeps contemplating on the feeling and the temperature in his body.
There was a spiritual light that had collated and his fire of lust became fire of wisdom.
And then he reached perfect penetration.
That means perfect enlightenment.
And he became fire head.
That's what they called him.
And he made a great vow.
He was damned by all the Buddha.
He gave me herbs, chiamè,持 minor仇,现 CE.
So there was a spiritual thing Bunny that married the Buddha.
Known asançAT
So it's okay that we have problems, we have delusions, but use the environment to cultivate
diligently, and you will reach enlightenment and overcome defilements
opportunity.
The third one is desire for fame.
We all want to be that famous movie star or professional athlete.
Fame is like a dream abarrad, a bubble.
and a shadow. It's not real. We should live our life and pursue a job that we enjoy contributing
to mankind, not because you're chasing after fame. So know the purpose of our existence
and live a life without pursuing fame. The fourth is food. As a practitioner, if you
really want to cultivate this lifetime, reach deep samadhi or meditation skill, you need
to watch the food that you eat. We need to purify our food in order to develop spiritually.
So if you eat a lot of heavy food, when you meditate, you will become drowsy. If you eat
too little, you will become weak and restless. So we watch exactly what we eat for us to
be in the best physical state possible.
The fifth is sloth. Wasting a lot of time sleeping or resting or lying in the bed and
being sluggish. That's really wasting our life away. A practitioner usually sleeps four
to six hours a day. A good practitioner practices meditation about that amount of time. Your
diligence will make perfect. And that's how you reach deep concentration and how your
wisdom will really grow.
And that's how you reach enlightenment and Buddhahood. What you reap is what you sow.
So three out of these five are essential. We need money, we need food, and we need sleep.
Lust and fame, we don't need them at all. The three that we need, try to minimize, simplify
your life, simplify your needs, and you will have a lot more time to cultivate and enjoy
your practice.
We can also talk about the five desires in terms of our sensory pleasures. Our eyes like
to see forms. We like to look at attractive things. We have a certain way of doing our
hair, doing our nails, or buying the clothes that we wear because we want to be attractive.
But that's actually wasting our time. You can't be cultivating into Buddhahood. So let
go of the desire.
The third is smell. People put on perfumes. We like to listen to music. We are not used
to having silence. Like when you meditate, enjoy the silence of your mind. Just watching
your inhale and exhale. Let go of all thoughts in your mind. So learn to enjoy no sound.
Let go of the desire of sound.
The third is smell.
People put on perfume and burn nice incense or candles because that's how they derive
their pleasure from. But that's a worldly desire that can hurt your cultivation.
There was a practitioner up in the mountain. One day, he wanted to take a break. So he
started walking around and he found a beautiful lotus pond. He went by the pond and smelled
the lotus flower's fragrance.
All of a sudden, the water god came up to him. He said, I want to smell the lotus flower's
fragrance.
The water god came out and scolded him. How dare you steal the fragrance of my lotus flowers.
You should go back and meditate.
This practitioner knows that, yo, I am having a hidden desire that's coming out. I should
let it go.
But when he was about to leave, someone else came by. And this person, not only did he
smell the flowers, he picked them and trampled all over them and made a whole big mess. But,
the water god didn't say anything.
So, the practitioner asked the water god, how come you didn't say anything to him. He
made a whole big mess.
And the water god says, you are a practitioner. You are a cultivator. So you cannot have a
little ounce of defilement in you. That's why I have to scold you. But he is a mundane
person that's not at your level. So I don't want to be under your control. So I'm not
SBS.
This place, he gives lie. He does lies. He also calls me like that. He calls at my ears like
i don't need to say anything to him so when we are a practitioner we need to watch our mind carefully
watch our every thought and every desire because that's how you reach buddhahood by every day
watching your mind and letting go of your desires the fourth one is flavor we all want flavorful
food some people like spicy some people like sour or sweet and we really the right pleasure out of
that but if that's the purpose of your existence you're wasting the spiritual life the fifth is
called tactile sensation feeling of touch we want to lie on the soft bed or sofa we enjoy the soft
fabric that's why we buy very expensive clothing we don't understand we spend so much
time every day trying to satisfy our sensory desires and we have no time to cultivate and
that's our samsara life if you really want to make something out of yourself this lifetime
try to let go of your desire it's like a dog gnawing on a decayed bone okay this metaphor
is extremely vivid a dog gnawing on the decayed bone it chews very very hard lips start bleeding
and he's actually eating his own blood but he think it's from the delicious bone that's what
we are doing we think this desire is making us happy enjoying life but it's actually harming us
that's causing us not reach buddhahood so understand the
truth
about the reality change ourselves and cultivate every day by watching our five desires that's how
we reach ultimate peace of having no desires so good luck with your cultivation you can do it