We're going to hold off on the 14 chapters of Buddhism for now because we have other important topics to discuss.
Today we'll be talking about faith.
How do we stay faithful when we're facing a lot of difficulties and disappointments in life?
First of all, we should know that faith is actually a great virtue. It's very wholesome.
On the other hand, if we have doubt, that's actually an affliction and it's unwholesome.
So always stay positive and faithful.
There was a village that was in drought for many years, so a local pastor decided to hold a prayer meeting to pray for rain.
During the prayer meeting, the pastor noticed there was a little girl in the front row.
She was actually holding an open umbrella over her head
because she knew that God was going to answer her prayers and it's going to rain.
So do we have the strong faith as this little girl?
In the Flower Adornment Sutra, it says,
Faith is the foundation of cultivating the Way and the Mother of Merit and Virtue because it is capable of nourishing good roots.
In the 100 Dharma Treatise, it talks about 11 wholesome dharmas and faith is one of them.
So faith is the basis of all goodness and all virtues.
So we need to have that in the very beginning.
Also in the other treaty, called the Great Treaty on Perfection of Wisdom, it says,
The Dharma is like a vast sea. Only by faith can it be entered.
Only by faith can we enter and benefit from the Dharma.
Just like if we are in front of a mountain of treasures.
If we have no hands, then we are incapable of taking any jewels out of the mountain.
The faith are our hands.
So if we have hands, then we are incapable of taking any jewels out of the mountain. The faith are our hands.
So if we have hands, then we are incapable of taking any jewels out of the mountain.
If we have hands, then we can benefit from the greatness of the Dharma.
So how do we have faith?
It's not blind faith.
Our faith is based on wisdom.
So let's learn how to have faith.
We need to have faith in three things.
Faith in the truth, have faith in virtues, and have faith in the capabilities.
With these three faiths, we need to develop three corresponding traits.
Believing in the truth, we need to develop deep endurance.
Believing in the virtues, we need to develop deep joy.
and believing in our capabilities we need to develop deep desire so let's
look at each one of them in detail first let's look at truth there's two kinds of
truth that we need to really believe in the first one is called conventional
truth and the second one is called ultimate truth the conventional truth is
about what's going on in the world which is called taxation so cause and effect
just like if we do good deeds we will get good results if we do bad deeds we will
have bad retribution that's the conventional truth we need to believe in
and the Ming Dynasty there was a merchant trading goods between the north
south of China he secretly added mercury to the weighing scale so he will make
more money so when he was dying he passed the scale to his son and tell him
to do business with the scale the son was a nobleman
so he burned the scale and sold the scale to his son and sold the scale to the
nobleman so he burned the scale instead and after he burned the scale both his
sons passed away suddenly so he thought there must be no karma I did a good deed
and this is what happened to me one night when he's dreaming the gods came
to him and told him your two sons they were in your family to destroy and
squander away all your family wealth but because you burned the scale we decided
to take them away and you will have two new sons they will be virtuous and good
for your family and sure enough the two sons decided to take them away and you will have two new sons they will be virtuous and good for your family and sure enough
the son had two new sons and they were virtuous and good for the family so if
we keep being good and believe in goodness will result in good karma then
we will have a good life after all so believe in the conventional truth of
causation on the other hand we need to believe in the ultimate truth ultimate
truth is not about what we see cause and effect
good or bad pure and impure it's about ultimate truth who is seeing everything
everything in its totality, so the oneness of things. The essence behind everything is
called the absolute reality, which is basically the one mind. The truth of the universe is
our one true mind, our Buddha nature. That is the center of the universe. So we need
to believe in the ultimate truth. When we are cultivating, trying to get rid of our
afflictions, we use the conventional truth. When we want to believe in ourselves and be
more positive and hopeful, we use the ultimate truth. Really rely on these two truths in
order for us to practice and succeed in our cultivation. We need to develop deep endurance
about the truth. Really believe in them. Rely on the truth, and that's how we cultivate.
In 1977, there were two American Buddhist monks. They did a pilgrimage. It's called
Three Steps, One Bell. So they take three steps and do one bell.
They would do three steps and do one bell. They would do three steps and do one bell.
They went from Southern California and Pasadena all the way to Ukiah, California, which is
a distance of 800 miles. Carrying no money, no talking, a lot of difficulties and weather
and everything, but they did it for two and a half years every day. How do they do that?
Because they believe in the truth. They believe in their bowing will bring world peace. They
really believe in karma, and they believe in their Buddha nature. So that's how they
did it. We need to develop deep endurance, really accord with the truth.
Number two, we need to believe in Buddha's virtues. Virtues include the Triple Jewels.
We need to believe in the pure and the real virtues of Buddha, the pure and real virtue
of the Dharma, and the pure and the real virtue of the Sangha. We call it the Triple Jewels.
So we need to take refuge in the Triple Jewels. First of all, we need to believe in Buddha.
Buddha, he has a lot of virtues. We don't see Buddha right now. We only see Buddha statue.
But do you have faith in his greatness? For example, Amitabha, he made 48 vows in order
to create the wonderful pure land for us. Do you believe that his 48 vows actually have
power in this universe? And every time you chant his name, the power actually comes right
out?
Number 33 of his vow, it says,
Any being if be touched by the ray of splendor of my light should not make his body and mind
gentle and peaceful in such a state that is far more sublime than the heavenly beings,
then may I not attain enlightenment.
So anyone who chants his name will be in touch with Buddha's light. That will make us gentle
and peaceful and warm. All our doubt and our worries and all our negative karma and sins
will go away.
Our body and mind will be filled with Buddha's light and is warm.
So believe in Buddha's vows and believe in his virtues. That's what carries us through
all difficulties.
We need to believe in the Dharma. Dharma is Buddha's teachings. Do you really believe
in Buddha's dharma? For example, his precepts. Precepts are very valuable and very precious.
Only Buddha can set the precepts. Not Bodhisattva or anyone else can set any precepts.
so be definite and hold pure precepts for example if we have a lot of ants or
spiders or mosquito in the house it's very easy just to use pesticide and kill
them but if you really want to follow Buddha's teaching we need to make sure
we do not kill any insects or any sentient beings we love them and we
actually want to carry them out safely one by one if your friend asks you to go
and just have a quick drink you would say no because I really believe in
Buddha's teaching I'm disciplined and I want to do all that is good and virtuous
so you should hold to the virtue of the Buddha and the Dharma and follow it
accordingly lastly we should believe in the virtues of the Sangha sangha is the
Buddhist community they're all these monks who devote their whole life in
practicing Buddhism they are our role models right now we don't see any Buddha
but we should see Buddha for a long time.
the monks as Buddha, being as reverent and respectful as we can. Many kalpas ago, there
was a devoted practitioner, his name was Ru Tong. At that time, there was a Buddha named
Meditating Light Buddha. The Buddha was coming to his country, so everybody in the country,
they were busy decorating for the Buddha. Finally, the Buddha arrived. As he was walking
on the street, everybody was in awe of Buddha's presence. Unfortunately, there was a puddle
of sludge right in front of Buddha. Ru Tong saw it. He immediately unwrapped his hair,
laid his long hair on the ground so Buddha can walk over the sludge without getting his
feet dirty. Buddha noticed his deep sincerity and made a prediction. In 91 kalpas, you will
become a Buddha. Your name will be Shakyamuni and your world will be called the Sokka world.
So Ru Tong was actually one lifetime of Shakyamuni Buddha. So we need to be respectful to all
of us.
At the end, we should have deep joy in our practice. We should love to practice Buddhism.
We should have fun in our practice. The more fun we have, the more we accumulate great
merits. Don't feel like it's so hard and I really don't enjoy it. I just make myself
do the meditation. No, you should love everything. You should love going to the temple, love
to make offerings to monks, love to meditate, love to listen to the Buddha. You should love
to listen to Dharma. The more you like it, the more you will succeed. There's a pianist
named Uma Garrett. She started playing the piano when she was only four years old. This
little girl loved to play the piano. The moment she wakes up, she wants to play and she wants
to play all the way till the middle of the night. So her mom had to give her curfews.
You cannot wake up too early to play. You're going to wake up the neighbors and you cannot
play too late till night because you're going to disturb everybody. If we love to meditate,
love to practice, us Buddhists, we should love to practice. We should love to practice.
As much as Uma loves to play the piano, then we'll definitely succeed in our cultivation.
Lastly, we need to believe in our own capabilities. We are capable and we have the power to have
good karma. If we keep practicing, we'll definitely accumulate good karma. There's no way the
more we practice, the worse our life gets. That's just impossible. So have faith that
you are accumulating much good merit and good karma when you're practicing Buddhism.
And also, we need to believe we'll definitely reach Buddhahood one day. It's sooner or later.
The harder we practice, the sooner we will become a Buddha. So have faith in your own
ability and your Buddha nature. We already have it inside of us. We just need to undiscover
it by our cultivation. When Shakyamuni Buddha was alive, he had a disciple named Mahanama.
One day, Mahanama asked Shakyamuni Buddha, Buddha, this world is so chaotic. I don't know
what to do. I'm afraid one day I will lose my focus in the Buddha, Dharma, and the Sangha.
Where will I go after that? Buddha asked him, if a big tree falls, what direction would
it lean toward? Mahanama answered, it will lean toward the heavier side where many branches
grow. Buddha said, so will you. When you're alive, you've been holding pure precepts,
you've been practicing giving, you've been listening to the Dharma, and you've been contemplating
the profound meanings of the Dharma with all these virtues and good deeds. When you're
about to pass, your consciousness will definitely go to a place of pure peace and joy. And you'll
definitely be reborn in the heavenly realm or the Buddha world, the pure land. So Mahanama
was very happy after hearing Buddha's teaching. So we need to believe in our own cultivation.
We'll definitely succeed. So don't have any worries. And we should have deep desire, really
want to achieve.
We want to accomplish in our cultivation. Some people, this lifetime, want to be a millionaire.
Some people want to win the Olympics or want to be a movie star or want to be a Nobel Prize
winner. But we want to have the selfless desire of becoming a Buddha because we want to really
end the samsara. We want to let everybody be out of the suffering. That's a selfless
desire, selfless goal.
So be firm in your cultivation.
Your desire to cultivate. In the end, the conclusion is a pure mind of faith emerges
real mark.
When we have no more doubt about Buddha, no more doubt about ourselves, and no more doubt
about everyone else, when our mind is pure without confusion, the real mark emerges.
Real mark is the ultimate truth, which is the absolute reality, our Buddha nature, the
one mind.
We will become enlightened because our true self will emerge.
So believe that your faith will help you succeed and become enlightened.
We don't want to be like a feather that is flowing in the air without direction.
Our faith should be strong as a rock and this lifetime we will succeed in our cultivation.
So thank you for listening. Amitabha.