Today we are going to talk about Great Strength Bodhisattva's Perfect Penetration.
This is part of the Shakyamuni Sutra and is also considered one of the five main Pure Land
Sutra.
Amitabha, Guanyin Bodhisattva and Great Strength Bodhisattva are called the Three Sages of the
Western Pure Land.
Great Strength Bodhisattva is called Great Strength because of his virtue and wisdom.
He is so powerful whenever he raises his hand, moves his feet, the entire earth shakes and
trembles.
In the beginning of the Sutra, it says Dharma Prince Great Strength together with fifty-two
Bodhisattva of similar rank arose from his seat, bowed at the Buddha's feet and said
to the Buddha,
I remember when as many eons ago as there are sands in the Ganges, a Buddha called Limitless
Light appeared in the world.
In that same eon there were twelve successive Thus Come Ones.
The last was called Light Surpassing the Sun and the Moon.
That Buddha taught me the Buddha Resonates with the Sun and the Moon.
Then Buddha recitation Samadhi.
Great Strength Bodhisattva is called the Dharma Prince because he's someone who is going to
inherit the throne and reach Buddhahood.
He and fifty-two Bodhisattva, they are basically people who are practicing the same Bodhisattva
way of chanting Amitabha Buddha's name.
That's how they become enlightened.
They are all fellow classmates.
They rose from their seat to describe how they met Buddha.
how they reach Samadhi. Many eons ago, there was a limitless light Buddha. It's the same
name as Amitabha Buddha whose name means infinite light. The last Buddha was called Light Surpassing
the Sun and the Moon. He taught Great String Bodhisattva the Buddha recitation Samadhi.
Samadhi means proper concentration. When you can concentrate your mind on the name Amitabha,
you can reach enlightenment. That's what Great String Bodhisattva did. So he is trying to explain
how he reached enlightenment to us. He used two analogies. Suppose there were a person who always
remembers someone else, but the someone else he remembers has entirely forgotten about him.
One person keeps thinking about someone else, but that someone else forgot about him.
This
person is Amitabha Buddha. He is always thinking about us, but we always forget about him.
We always turn our back on Amitabha. We follow the Sixth Sense Objects of the world. Even
if we are Pure Land Practitioners, we might chant one hour a day, but 23 hours, we are
minding our own business and we forgot about him. But if two such people were to meet,
even if they were to meet, they would never forget about him. They would never forget about him.
They would never take notice. No oneารat problema. They would not figure out the meaning put into their words.
They would not recognize each other. A lot of times, people are afraid or touch Gracias."
That's going to reassure the third relation. They would not recognize each other.
A lot of times, we feel lonely, afraid, and fearful. That's because we don't know
Amitabha is with us all the time. We are never alone. It's always us and Amitabha, but we
don't recognize him. That's why we don't know his presence. He is always with us. We should
never be alone.
If two people remember each other until the Wednesday morning, We are in no hurry. As the
politics are changing, some people might break into the regulations. I feel happy as they did.
Learn about Chinese Yoga will help you learn Chinese Yoga in your life.
people remember each other until the memory of each is deep then in life
after life they will be together like a form and its shadow and they will never
be at odds on the other hand if they always remember each other if I remember
Amitabha and Amitabha of course always remembering me our memory of each other
is very deep always thinking of each other then we will be together like an
object in the shadow and we will never be in opposition or in conflict we
always together in our heart last summer we went to a vegetarian restaurant after
we're done eating but they had to go to the restaurant so we were waiting
outside in the parking lot there came a monk I immediately bow to him and he
started telling me about the Dharma how to cultivate the mind and the body and
our speech he went to his car and took a
car and took a car and took a car and took a car and took a car and took a
big picture of Shakyamuni Buddha and said here this is for you I was so happy
and this all happened in the parking lot of a restaurant I don't know his name he
doesn't know my name but we are connected in the Dharma this is the law
of attraction whatever you think about all day long that's what you will
attract into your life so we need to think about Amitabha all day long the
other example is Amitabha.
Out of pity for living beings that thus come once of the Ten Directions,
are mindful of them as a mother remembers her child.
If a child runs away, of what use is the mother's regard?
Buddha is like the mother, and we are like the child.
If we don't remember him and run away from home,
then no matter how much the mother thinks of us, it's useless.
We'd rather be a beggar in the three worlds of samsara
and turn our backs on enlightenment.
That's how sad it is.
On the surface level, this mother is Amitabha Buddha.
On the deeper level, this mother is our original enlightened mind.
We all have it originally.
We should remember who we really are.
When we start chanting the name Amitabha,
that's the process of actualization
of the three worlds of samsara.
That's the process of actualization of the three worlds of samsara.
That's the process of actualization of enlightenment.
And then we will reach final enlightenment.
The original enlightenment,
and the process of actualization of enlightenment,
and the final enlightenment,
is all one enlightenment.
Because we just have one mind.
So know who we really are.
Do not run away from your own ultimate nature.
But if the child remembers his mother
in the same way that the mother remembers the child,
then in life,
after life,
the mother and the child will not be far apart.
If the child always remembers the mother,
then they will be together forever.
If we remember our true nature,
either we are walking,
standing,
sitting,
lying down,
remember we are the Buddha.
We are the same as Amitabha.
Have Amitabha in our mind,
and be mindful of the present moment,
of what we are doing.
So walk like a Buddha,
stand like a Buddha,
sit like a Buddha,
lie down like a Buddha,
then you are the Buddha at this moment.
You don't have anywhere to go.
You don't have to look anywhere else.
You have already arrived.
That's what the Zen Buddhism is teaching us.
It is exactly the same as Pure Land Buddhism.
So there's actually no sex of Buddhism.
We are all together,
as one,
one whole Buddhism.
We can do this through chanting of Amitabha,
just remembering the Buddha.
Every breath,
we are the Buddha.
So remember the mother.
If living beings remember the Buddha,
and are mindful of the Buddha,
certainly they will see the Buddha now or in the future.
So this means we remember Amitabha.
It's not just chanting his name.
Actually know his heart,
know his vows,
and know his deeds,
and be like him.
Buddha's heart is full of compassion,
sincere,
and pure,
and enlightened.
His vow is to save all sentient beings.
We should have the same Bodhisattva vows.
And Buddha's deed is to follow the precepts exactly.
Then we should follow the precepts exactly.
That is called remembering,
remembering the Buddha,
mindful of the Buddha.
If you do that,
then you'll definitely see Buddha.
We will see Buddha in this lifetime in three ways.
One is in our dream.
Buddha might come into your dream to encourage you.
Two is when you're in deep meditation,
you can see Buddha.
Lastly,
you'll definitely see Buddha in the moment of death.
Amitabha will keep his promise,
he will keep his promise for you to his Western Pure Land.
So we'll definitely see him then.
And we will see him in the future.
That means in the Western Pure Land.
When your lotus flower opens up and you see him,
that's when you're really enlightened.
So if you remember Buddha,
you will see Buddha for sure.
If someone always remember the Buddha,
they will never be apart from the Buddha,
and their minds will awaken by themselves without the aid of expedience.
If we always remember the Buddha,
chant Buddha's name,
think of Buddha's virtues,
his mind and his vows,
then we will be awakened by ourselves.
How do we know if we're awakened?
When we eliminate our afflictions,
situation or affliction that's bothering us will disappear.
We will feel blissfulness and peace in our mind.
Then we know our heart has opened up and we are awakened.
We are one with the Buddha.
A person who has been near incense will carry a fragrance on his person.
It is called an adornment of fragrant light.
So if we chant Amitabha Buddha's name,
it's like we are always near incense.
We permeate with this fragrance.
We don't have to create this fragrance.
It's already created by Amitabha and will be glowing in his golden light.
Everybody that remembers him will have this golden light.
It will naturally manifest.
Great Saint Bodhisattva said on the castle ground,
I use the mindfulness of Buddha to enter into patience with non-protection of Dharma.
For his own self enlightenment,
he used the mindfulness of Buddha to reach the patience of non-protection of Dharma,
which means he understands the emptiness of the self and emptiness of all Dharma.
On the other hand,
to save all sentient beings,
he said,
now in this world,
I gather all those that are mindful of the Buddha and bring them back to the Western Pure Land.
He already made a vow.
In this world,
he will protect all those that chant Amitabha Buddha's name,
help them in their practice,
and at the end,
will bring them back to the Pure Land.
That's his Bodhisattva vow.
So he said,
Buddha asked about perfect penetration.
I was like none other than God,
then gather in the six organs through continuous pure mindfulness to obtain samadhi.
This is the foremost method.
So Buddha asked about how he became enlightened.
He gathered in the six organs and have continuous pure mindfulness of the name Amitabha,
and that's how he obtained proper concentration,
samadhi.
That's the foremost method we can all use.
At least we can all reach continuous link recitation.
That means your recitation can go for a period of time without any interruption,
without any scattered thoughts.
If our recitation is not effective,
we need to find out the factor that is rendering the ineffectiveness of our Pure Land chanting.
So we need to find out why.
If it's a certain person or a certain situation,
that always take your mind away from your chanting,
realize that you are attached to the situation,
not to eliminate the situation or the person,
but to eliminate your attachment to the situation.
Know that it's all conditioned and non-existing.
Why are you bothered and carried away by the situation or this person?
You should come back to your Amitabha.
It is the only thing that should be on your mind,
24 hours a day,
know Amitabha and know you are with him.
Know that you are the Buddha nature.
That's all you have to remember.
That's the foremost important thing in our lives.
So understand what is Buddha recitation,
samadhi,
and if we really do this this lifetime,
our chanting will be effective and we will definitely go to the Western Pure Land.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.