Today we are going to talk about Samantabhadra Bodhisattva.
His name also means universal, worthy. Universal because his way pervades everywhere.
Worthy because his conduct is identical to the conduct of the foremost sages.
Now let's look at ten great vows.
Number one, to pay respect to all Buddhas.
With the awesome spiritual power of Samantabhadra's vow, I appear at the same time before every Tathagata,
and in transformed body as numerous as most of us in all lands, bow to the Buddhas as numerous as most of us in all lands.
So we use bowing to show our respect.
This bowing is not bowing to a statue, it's bowing to the true nature within all of us.
Every Buddha has three types of bodies.
One is the Dharma body, that's the principle and nature of the original enlightenment.
Number two is the reward body, that's the perfect wisdom of the initial enlightenment.
Number three is the transformation body, that's the compassionate appearance responding to living beings.
Usually we use the example of Aporo.
The perfect round essence of the pearl is like the Dharma body.
The pure light emitted from the pearl is like the reward body.
And the reflection of the pearl is like the transformation body.
The three are not one and not yet different.
They are not one because they are three.
They are not different because they are from one Buddha.
We all have the three types of bodies.
As long as we cast out our confusion and deluded mind, we immediately return to the three bodies.
Therefore, we are respecting our own three bodies and respecting the three bodies that's in all sentient beings.
Therefore, an enlightened person will always be loving and respectful toward all sentient beings equally.
Number two, to praise the Tathagatas.
With oceans of sound are everywhere left for words and phrases, wonderful and endless,
which now and through all the eons of the future,
praise the wide deep sea of Buddha's name.
Number three, to praise Amitabha's merit and virtues.
We use our voice to praise Buddha's wisdom, compassion, and his three bodies.
That's why when we chant the name Amitabha, we are praising Amitabha's merit and virtues.
We are also praising the merit and virtues of our own Buddha nature.
When you understand your true nature, all the sounds of the rain, of the wind, of the cars, of the birds,
they are all praising the Tathagata.
Number three, to make abundant offerings.
With a vast, great, supremely liberated mind,
I believe in all the Buddhas of the three periods of time
with the strength of Samantabhadra's conduct and vows.
I make offerings to all the Tathagatas everywhere.
Because Samantabhadra's heart is so big, whatever he offers will multiply infinitely
and be offered to all the Buddhas everywhere.
So we want to embrace the vast emptiness and accommodate the infinitude,
which means our heart is so infinite.
We are able to tolerate, accept all sentient beings and all things.
So we want to have a big heart, able to give everything that we can and give offerings.
Number four, to repent and confess karmic obstacles.
For all the evil deeds I have done in the past, created by my body, mouth, and mind,
from beginningless greed, anger, and delusion, I now know shame and repent them all.
We want to repent all our sins.
The worst is that we do not know our own selfishness that's blocking our Buddha nature.
We want to be awakened.
But we should know that the original enlightenment exists originally,
and the non-enlightenment originally does not exist.
So our sins and our afflictions do not exist in the first place.
So it's easy for us to repent when we know what is real and what is not.
Number five, to rejoice in virtues.
I rejoice in the merits and virtues of all beings in the ten directions,
from the most humble to the Arhats, Pratyekabuddhas, Bodhisattvas, and all the Tathagatas.
I rejoice in all the merits of the ten Dharma rounds.
Even hell beings, they have merits.
So do not look down on any sentient beings.
Moreover, we do not want to be jealous of others,
because the ten Dharma rounds is created by our own mind.
All sentient beings are us.
Know this for a fact.
That way we can eradicate our jealousy.
Number six, to request the turning of the Dharma wheel.
Before the lengths of the world of the ten directions who have just accomplished Supreme Bodhi,
I now request and beseech them all to turn the foremost and wondrous Dharma wheel.
We want to request Buddha to turn the Dharma wheel.
Dharma is Buddha's teaching to help us to become enlightened.
But the Dharma wheel is actually inside all of us.
By contemplating on the Dharma and practicing accordingly,
we are turning the Dharma wheel of our mind.
Number seven, to request the Buddhas to remain in the world.
If there are Buddhas who wish for nirvana,
I request with deep sincerity that they dwell in the world for a long time
to bring benefits and bliss to every being.
I request the Buddha to remain in this world to teach us Dharma.
Buddha cannot wash away our sins or take away our suffering.
What he can do is only to teach us the Dharma,
so we can change ourselves.
So we want to request our own Buddha to remain in this world
by being awakened, understanding emptiness and our true suchness.
Number eight, to always follow the teachings of Buddha.
All future teachers of God and men whose aspirations and vows have been completed,
I will follow and study throughout the three periods of time
and quickly attain great Bodhi.
Follow Buddha's teaching
by always listening to the Dharma.
We want to learn the Dharma and to teach others.
To teach others doesn't mean you have to be on a podium.
It means that in your daily activity,
you are compassionate and wise.
People can learn from you.
Then you're leading by example.
Number nine, to always be in harmony with all beings.
I vow that every being in all directions will be peaceful, happy and without worry.
May they obtain the proper Dharma's profound aid
and may all their sufferings
be wiped away without exception.
We want all sentient beings to be happy.
The only way is to learn the Dharma.
In order for them to learn the Dharma,
we must be in harmony with them,
accord with them.
So the importance of courtesy, forbearance and tolerance is a must.
That's the only way to eliminate all the disasters in the world.
So take on social roles to benefit others
and to find ways to facilitate harmony in the world.
Number ten, to dedicate all merits.
The supreme and endless blessing
from Samatha Bhattra's conduct
I now universally transfer.
May every living being drowning in the drip
soon return to the land of limitless light.
A bodhisattva accrues merits by his vows,
insight and compassion to all living beings.
He does not cultivate for himself.
He's cultivating for everyone
to rescue all sentient beings
out of the ocean of suffering.
Therefore, when we practice these ten great vows,
we are being a bodhisattva.
This is all inherent in our nature.
So we are originally a Samatha Bhattra bodhisattva,
so we understand who we really are.
Lastly, the Huayan School of Buddhism
teaches about the sixfold attributes
to learn about the ten great vows.
Number one is generality.
These ten in general
is called the ten great vows as a whole.
Number two in general,
it has its particularity.
They are all different and unique.
For example, you can repent
about not being respectful,
or repent about not praising,
or repent about not making offerings.
So repent and everyone else
is unique and different.
Number three,
they all have their similarities.
For example,
respect and praise and make offering
is all about our devotion to Buddha.
But number four,
they have their distinctions.
For example,
respect is with our body,
praising is with our mouth,
making offering is more with our heart.
So they are all each unique and distinct.
Number five is their formation
in terms of their function and usage.
These ten are the common cause
for Samatha Bhattra bodhisattva
to reach Buddhahood.
But they all have their own destruction.
They are individually different
and unhindered.
If you can use the sixfold attributes
to learn about the ten great vows,
you will be able to use them integratively.
Samatha Bhattra Bodhisattva, he says,
if anyone devotedly practices
the ten great vows,
I will immediately mount on the six-toothed elephant
and to see the person.
I will secretly rub his head,
protect and comfort him,
so he will be able to accomplish
the ten great vows in his practice.
We can use this in our daily activities,
even amidst of difficulties
in our family or workplace,
we will still be able to activate
our awakened nature
and be a bodhisattva.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.