Today we are going to talk about 14 chapters of Buddhism, chapter 1 meaning of Buddha, chart B and C.
Last time we learned Buddha is someone who eradicated two obstacles and reached wisdom and enlightenment.
Today we will further discuss the two obstacles.
Hopefully we will understand that these two obstacles are basically all our life problems and we can resolve them by practicing Buddhism.
Now let's look at the two obstacles.
We have the obstacle of affliction which is about our lives and we have obstacle of knowledge which is about our world.
Let's first look at our life, our life outlook.
How do we see our life right now?
Do we know that our personal affliction is the cause of all our problems?
Let's look at our current experiences.
Right now we are experiencing a lot of sufferings.
We have 8 kinds of sufferings.
We have suffering of birth, aging, sickness and death, separation from our loved ones, being together with people we dislike and not obtaining what we desire and the imbalance of our body and mind.
These 8 sufferings all of us have to go through them.
So life is very unsatisfactory and unstable.
A lot of times we feel we are freedomless, we are trapped in this cycle and we have no control over when we are going to get sick or we are going to die and we have no control over our own emotion most of the time.
A lot of times we also feel inequality.
Some people are rich, some people are poor, some people are healthy, some are handicapped and the level of our intelligence is all different.
Why is that?
This is all because of our culture.
This is all because of our karma or causation.
It's what we have done before, that's what we are experiencing our life right now.
We do a lot of bad deeds, that's why we have negative karma most of the time that becomes suffering.
In the sutra it says, even though a hundred thousand kalpas pass, a karma which is created does not perish.
When the cause and the conditions come together, retribution will still be personally undergone.
Everything that we do, every thought we think, actually has effect, has consequences.
So let's look at our present action.
What we do right now, creates our future.
A lot of times we are creating cause of suffering which are afflictions.
Are greed, anger and ignorance.
for example if we are greedy, we steal someones things.
Then in the future, someone will steal our things.
You could kill your loved one.
If we been jealous and mistreat other people.
You would be rude when picking up the people.
Us and ourness. And what is this wheel? What can happen things, feel, struggle and distraction as is. Any and all of those things will happen when we act on the move.
people, other people will treat us the same way. Whatever we do will always come back
to us. We also have a lot of discriminations. We have our likes and dislikes and because
of our selfishness, we do a lot of selfish deeds that create negative karma. There was
a 60-year-old female Buddhist. One day she went to an old monk. She cried, I've been
married to my husband for nearly 40 years and I never knew what happiness was. My husband
always scolded and beat me and everybody still thinks he's such a good person. I know I probably
owe him from previous life, but how come it's still not paid off? The old monk calmly said,
long time ago, there was a wealthy businessman. He had many wives and concubine and a family,
but he fell in love with a pretty maid.
He forcefully
took her and agreed to take her as a concubine. So he used her physically when he was happy
and beat her when he was upset. So this maid's hope of becoming a concubine never happened
and she passed away with deep hatred toward this businessman. So you were the businessman
and your current husband was the abuse maid. That's why he's treating you this way. This
woman totally believed in the story.
And she sincerely confessed her sin for mistreating the maid. And she never resent her husband
again. So we need to realize awareness. Number one, we need to know our karmic effects. Awareness
number two, we need to know our karmic causes. It's all because our cause and effect creating
the samsara life that we're experiencing. This is also the void meditation.
Understanding the emptiness of everything, it just cause and effect and let go of our
selfishness, replace our afflictions with virtues and good deeds.
Now let's look at our worldview. How do we see our world right now? Do we know that we
have a lot of obstacle of knowledge blocking us from understanding the phenomenon that's
going on in this world? For example, there's a lot of thing that's unavoidable. Right now,
we're going through COVID-19. This is an unprecedented disaster. Why are we experiencing this?
It's because of our collective karma of all kinds of killing and consuming of animals.
That's why we have to go through this unavoidable disaster. A lot of things are unattainable.
We want a good job, a good marriage, a good life, or world peace, but it just seems impossible
to obtain them. And a lot of things are unattainable. So we need to know our karmic causes and let
it go. Even if we get the good fortune, it doesn't last. How many families you see that
has good fortune for many generations? Not many because it's really hard to retain them.
We need to realize the phenomenon, use the unreal meditation to look at these situations.
Even though we have things that are unavoidable, if we can change our thoughts and be positive,
think, oh, we have the lockdown, we're staying at home. Now is a good time to memorize that
mantra. I always wanted to memorize or to practice meditation and chanting the Buddha's
name vigorously. That way you're using this time to do something great. We're making lemonade
a la lemon. Even though we cannot obtain things that we want, that just motivates to work
harder and never give up. Even though things are not retainable, we lose the good things
that we have that will prevent us from being spoiled and lazy.
So I want to tell you what I want to tell you. I want you to be humble and keep cultivating.
So, Boji Sapha, use the unreal meditation. Know everything is unreal, everything is just
cause and effect, but use the current situation to practice, to cultivate, to make ourself
better and contribute to the world. Now let's talk about relationships and matters. Relationships
are impermanent. There's a lot of divorce and affairs. Love is definitely not forever.
But how we deal with it is very important. If you have a relationship with a married
with this relationship is totally up to us. There was a devoted Buddhist practitioner.
A few years after her marriage, her husband fell in love with another woman. He often
traveled with this mistress. But this wife never complained or had a fight about this
with her husband. She just stayed calm and took care of the children and farm to make
money for the family. This husband and the mistress had a child. They brought the child
back and left the child at home and they went off to play again. This wife took care of
the child and took the child in and out of work and while farming. Everybody in the village
poked fun at her for raising the child of the mistress. She just wanted to raise the
child and the child grew up thinking that this wife is his biological mother. A few
years later, the mistress became a human vegetable from a brain operation. This wife went to
visit her mother.
The mistress said you're not equal in farm work. You're not equal in farm work.
She was disposed of, she was not equal with the ecology, she was not equal in farm work and
was not equal with the dogs and wild animals of the village. But this wife has a sharp
deficit because she too grew up with her husband as husband. It is very true.
In this relationship, we won't have a service here without hindrance. There is
no need for further intervention. The wife and child now grew together with her husband
so everything go through these four stages and the meanings are profound why
these things change is very complex karma is very complex it's really hard
to understand for example we have a whole school study called the
consciousness only school it talks about how our consciousness work we have the
eighth consciousness we call it the Alaya consciousness it's actually the
warehouse that store all our past actions all our past thoughts when the
time comes it ripens into effect it ripens into everything that we are
experiencing in the world everything is very profound so we need to realize
relationships are impermanent events are changing meanings are profound but we
can practice the mean meditation going inward to your Buddha nature that
doesn't
doesn't change with the outside world. Even though outside everything is changing, there's
something that is permanent and is immutable that has a perfect wisdom. That is our true
Buddha nature. So that's called the Ming Meditation. So now let's understand further our life and
the universe. When we talk about our lives and universe, we talk about it in terms of
space and time. In terms of space, there's 10 directions. North, East, South, West. North,
East, North, West. South, East, South, West. Up and down. So in these 10 directions, there's
all kinds of different reincarnations going on. So in every world, in every planet, there's
all kinds of beings and all kinds of people in this world. We are all interrelated because
of our karmic relationship, our karmic influences. For example, we are all interrelated because
of our karmic influences. For example, we have international dynamics. What happens
in one country will impact the welfare and the economics of many other countries. Climate
change in one part of the world will impact another part of the world. Sunspots, their
large dark patches that cover the sun will affect the magnetic field of the Earth. So
everything is interrelated and boundless. Why is it boundless? Because everything is
vibration from our thoughts, from our mind. You probably heard of the 100th monkey effect.
They studied a group of monkeys in Japan. There was one monkey that started washing
the sweet potato before eating it. And 99 monkeys started learning the same behavior.
So at that critical point of the 100th monkey learning the same behavior, every monkey on
the island started doing the same thing. Soon enough, all different islands and all over
the world, monkeys started washing their potatoes. Why is that? Because our thought has vibrations.
So our loving kindness, our good thought can change the world, can vibrate throughout the
entire universe. So know the power of our mind, our true suchness.
Now let's look at it in terms of time. Past, present, and future.
Okay, let's look at it in terms of time. Past, present, and future.
There's reincarnation going on. We have past lives, we have current lives, and we have
many, many future lives. We have different environments. For example, ancient time to
modern time, our politics and culture have changed drastically. Before, it was more about
morals and virtues. And now it's all about technology and personal consumption.
And what's going on in the sixth round? In every world, we have different lifespans.
And different conditions. For example, to spend one day in the ghost realm is actually
30 days in the human realm. That's why in many Eastern cultures, we observe vegetarian
diet on the first and the 15th of the lunar calendar, in respect to the spirits in the
ghost realm. Everything is endless because our mind creates everything. So Buddha actually
understands everything about our space and time. And that's why we are living in this
world. That's why he has the wisdom of space and wisdom of time. So Buddha is omniscient.
He knows everything. But you're like, how can we become like that? We can't. Because
our Buddha nature is exactly this way. We say our Buddha nature, it traverses through
ten directions. It pursues three periods. You just need to believe in it. Use your mind
to change the world. In the Shurigama Sutra, it says the universe
in the enlightened mind is like a single bubble in the sea. So the whole universe inside
our wonderful mind is only like a tiny little bubble. It also says the universe in our mind
is like a tiny cloud floating in the boundless sky. The whole universe inside our mind is
only a tiny little dot. That's how wonderful our Buddha nature is. So believe in yourself
that you have the perfect mind creating the universe.
All we need to do is keep cultivating the void meditation, the unreal meditation, and
the mean meditation. We will rediscover our own true nature. So that's the class for today.
Merry Christmas and Happy New Year. Hope everybody use your mind to transform this world into
a beautiful, loving, pure land. So thank you for listening. Amitabha.