Today we are going to talk about Suffering as Our Teacher Part 2.
Where is our temple?
Our temple is not a physical structure.
It is actually in our daily lives.
This is called cultivating meditation through external conditions.
Today we will talk about the 5 other kinds of sufferings and learn how to use them as our spiritual teacher.
Number 6. When interacting with others, do not seek self-benefits.
There will be some friends and family members who are not always good to you.
They might take advantage of you, betray you, or mistreat you.
If we understand karma, we will know that we actually done this to them in our prior lifetimes.
So gladly pay them back and confess for our sins.
And also we must think that we are now a bodhisattva.
We should not think about our own self-interest but only be concerned with serving others.
In the Ming Dynasty, there was a Mr. Wu Zetian.
When he was young, his mother passed away.
His father remarried to a stepmother.
The stepmother mistreated him and only liked his younger stepbrother who loved to gamble.
When he got older, he married a very virtuous wife.
But the stepmother also mistreated her.
His father passed away and left a lot of land and inheritance.
His stepmother gave everything to the younger brother, only gave him a little shack and an infertile land.
But he did not give up.
He worked very hard for a decade and became a very wealthy man.
At the same time, his stepmother and stepbrother squandered away all their inheritance and became homeless.
Mr. Wu and his wife, without any hesitation, took in the stepmom and stepbrother and helped the stepbrother quit the gambling addiction.
The whole family now lives happily together.
Mr. Wu used kindness to pay back ungratefulness.
That's what we mean by use ungrateful friends as resources to build our loving kindness.
Number seven, do not expect others to be always respectful and cooperative.
People are impermanent.
They might one day like you and the other day dislike you.
They will be people who are against you, criticize you, and disrespect you.
But we should use the opposition as support.
To build our patience.
Master Hua of the City of Ten Thousand Buddhas, in the summer of 1987, he was having an inter-religious conference.
On the first day, there was a group of New Age Christians that were demonstrating outside the temple.
Mr. Hua said, oh great, please invite them in.
His disciples didn't do anything, so he actually went down there to greet them himself.
He brought them in and said, please send them in.
He said, if you want to go to the front row, you can present first to what you have to say.
If you guys want food, beverage, or anything you need, we will provide them for you while you're demonstrating here.
If you want to scold me, you want to hit me, even if you want to kill me, I will not fight back at all.
Just do whatever you like.
Why? Because I have the spirit of Jesus.
They were all dumbfounded and intrigued.
The next day, they came back very respectfully.
They joined the conference, and they all became friends.
So use opposition as support to train our patience.
Number eight, do not expect rewards when helping others.
Some people donate because they want to be famous, or for tax write-off, or just for a sense of fulfillment.
But all these are impure intentions.
Buddha taught us to practice threefold wheel of life.
Threefold wheel of essential emptiness.
With the threefolds are the giver, the receiver, and the gift.
We should not be attached to any of these three things when we are giving.
We want to be away from all forms that is true giving.
Just like those teachers and doctors who volunteer to go to the rural villages of third world countries for most of their careers,
with minimal pay and no recognition.
Just do it because they care.
That is true altruism.
That is true giving.
So use giving as abandonment.
It's like a pair of worn out shoes.
You just throw it away.
You don't really care about how much you helped others.
You should forget about it.
So use giving as abandonment.
Number nine, beware of beneficial temptations.
This is called holding precepts.
We do not want to be greedy for things we're not supposed to have.
We don't want to corrupt our moral values because of personal gains.
There was a virtuous person in the Song Dynasty.
His name is Fan Zhongyan.
When he was young, he was poor, so he had to study in the back of a temple for three years.
All he ate was porridge and some vegetables.
One day, there was two rats that came in and stepped all over his porridge.
One is a white rat, one is a yellow rat.
So he chased them outside and they all scurried into a wattle tree.
He went to the wattle tree.
He saw two rat holes.
One rat hole is shimmering with golden light and one is shimmering with white light.
So he dug open the hole.
Sure enough, he found a pot of gold and a pot of silver.
But he was not moved by the precious metal.
He covered them up and pretended it never happened.
Thirty years later, there was a great fire that devastated the temple.
So the monk wrote to Fan Zhongyan asking him for help.
By now, he's already a prime minister.
Fan Zhongyan did not offer any help.
He only wrote back a letter.
He says,
West side of the wattle tree, there is a pot of gold.
East side of the wattle tree, there is a pot of silver.
Use half of it to rebuild the temple.
Half of it for all the monks.
Mr. Fan Zhongyan,
he was not greedy for money because he wanted to hold on to his moral values.
That's most important to him.
So we want to resist temptation as wealth.
Our biggest wealth is when we don't have any greed.
We're content with what we have and we hold on to our ethics.
Number ten,
do not be troubled by false accusations.
Of course,
if it's about the well-being of the people of your country,
or the world,
you have to speak up.
But if it's about yourself,
you can choose to use the injustice as practice for our concentration and wisdom.
In the early 1900s,
there was a famous monk in Taiwan, Master Guangqing.
Master Guangqing cultivated up in the mountains most of his life.
When he come back down to the temple,
he basically just stayed in the main hall and meditated all day and all night.
One day,
the money in the donation box was taken.
Everybody thought Master Guangqing stole the money.
So they treated him like a thief and treated him with disdain.
Weeks later,
a monk from the temple announced that they purposely hid the money to test the master's cultivation.
Now everybody is praising the master for his great cultivation.
But the master,
he was not moved.
When they call him a thief,
He went on with his meditation.
When now they call him a great master,
he is still not moved.
He went on with his routine meditation.
So this is called the real concentration and wisdom.
That's the real samadhi.
So all these life situations,
they are to train us to become a bodhisattva.
Basically the six parameters.
Number six and seven,
it is about the patient's parameter.
Number eight is the giving parameter.
Number nine is precept parameter.
Number 10 is the concentration and wisdom parameter.
And all of them need the diligence parameter
because we want to be mindful of the situation.
So gold must be refined by melting.
The cherry blossom must go through the winter of harsh cold.
Men must go through trials and tribulations to be successful.
All these life situations,
which we know they are impermanent and unreal,
but we take the opportunity to use them
to train us to grow into a bodhisattva
and soon we will reach Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.