Today we are going to talk about forgiveness.
How do we forgive ourselves and others of the mistakes and faults done to us?
We are going to use the Four Noble Truths to discuss forgiveness.
The first Noble Truth is called suffering.
We are currently experiencing the suffering of having anger and resentment in our hearts.
Then we need to find out what's the causes of suffering.
What is the exact cause of this anger?
And our goal is cessation of suffering.
We want to end this pain. We want to resolve this anger.
The path to end suffering.
What do we need to do right now to resolve this anger?
So let's look at this in detail.
First is suffering.
We will experience five kinds of suffering related to anger.
The first two are internal suffering.
The next two are external suffering.
And the last one is future suffering.
Internal suffering, we will suffer pain in our body.
We are likely to experience fast aging.
If you look at the centurions, they are always happy and never get angry.
If we get angry all the time, we are likely to have sickness such as cancer, heart attack, and stroke.
Number two, we will experience suffering of our mind.
The anger swallows up our peace of mind and robs us of our joy and serenity.
So it's highly destructive.
Externally, number three, we will have poor relationships.
The anger will destroy our relationship with others
and cause more conflicts and fights.
Number four, anger will create karma of natural disaster
such as fire, earthquake, and viruses.
Lastly, in the future, we will experience samsara.
After this lifetime, we are likely to be reborn in the three evil realms
of animal, hungry ghost, and hell.
Especially, hell is caused by anger.
So if you look at the suffering, you will know that nothing good comes out of anger.
It's highly destructive.
It only creates more pain.
Internally, it will harm our body and mind.
Externally, we will have poor relationships and create natural disasters.
And after this lifetime, we will be reborn in the three evil realms.
Now we need to know the exact cause of our anger.
There are also five types of anger
that we might experience.
The first is angry at ourselves.
A lot of times, we're angry at ourselves for getting angry.
For example, I'm holding the bodhisattva precept
but I got mad at my family member
and I'm more than mad at myself.
But if you're mad at yourself, that's double anger.
You're breaking the precept again.
So what you need to do is you need to treat yourself in a friendly manner.
Talk to yourself with encouragement.
You can do it.
You have a big heart.
You can have no more anger.
You're doing a good job.
So always encourage yourself instead of getting angry at yourself.
Number two, we might be angry at others.
We choose the world we live in.
You might choose to live in a hostile world
or you choose to live in a friendly world.
It's all up to us.
Some people, they choose to be offended all the time.
They go to the market.
They're offended by their cashier.
They go to a restaurant, offended by the waiter.
They drive on the street and being offended by other drivers.
Some people choose to be offended and angry at others all the time.
Number three, we might be angry about the past.
Sometimes we have childhood abuse that keep haunting us for the rest of our lives.
Or you might just not be the favorite child in your family.
You just keep playing the scene of your mother treating your brother better.
And you feel inferior and not worthy of love.
So that's angry about the past.
Number four, we might be angry about the present.
Right now, we're having lockdowns.
Everybody is in a confined space living together.
It's really hard to live together in harmony when we're hanging out in a small space.
So, you know, we might be angry about the current situation.
Number five, we might be angry.
We might be angry about the future.
You think about the future and think, oh, that co-worker is going to take over my job.
How dare him?
Or that country is going to go to war with us.
And you feel angry about that.
So the last three, anger about the past, angry about the present, angry about the future.
These three are related to three kinds of distresses.
A is someone annoying me.
Even just a mosquito biting me.
Even just a mosquito biting us, we might be annoyed.
Or someone who insults us in front of a large group of people, we will be annoyed.
Or someone who is always late, we might be annoyed.
So that's the first one concerning me.
B is someone annoying my loved one.
That also makes us angry.
For example, we might have family feuds that last for 20, 30 years.
It might be the uncle or the aunt that took our money and still badmouth our parents.
We will get very angry at that.
And we keep the family feud forever.
C, eulogizing my rivals.
For example, someone that's close to you, that is still a good friend with your enemy.
That will make us very upset.
So angry about the past, angry about the present, angry about the future.
All times these three, A, B, and C.
Together, we call it the nine distresses.
Nine things we might be angry about.
And if you look at all these causes, you will realize the main cause is having the ego of me, of my, and I.
That's why we are experiencing the anger.
If you can just shrink the self, you will no longer feel the anger.
So recognize the causes is very important that help us to cast away the anger immediately.
So our goal is cessation of suffering.
We want to be able to reach number one, forgiveness.
We want to be able to completely forget ourselves and the other person of the faults and mistakes.
Everybody is not yet a Buddha.
So we all make mistakes.
Have the big heart and be able to accept the fault and the mistake and forgive completely.
That's what we call deep healing.
Only when we forgive, then we can get rid of the pain and the suffering.
Number two, liberation from resentment.
Free ourselves from all kinds of resentment.
That's the only way that your cultivation will improve.
Just like if you have a lot of trash in your heart, you cannot put in new merits.
Just like a warehouse.
You need to throw out the old, unusable inventory before you restock and put in new inventory.
So we liberate ourselves of all resentment.
Throw it away completely.
Number three is the ultimate goal of reaching nirvana.
So nirvana, it actually means no samsara, no more life and death.
How do we reach that level?
It means no more self, no more ego, no more defilements such as anger.
That's what we call nirvana.
Most importantly, what's the path to end suffering?
What do we need to do to get rid of our anger?
Usually we talk about the path in terms of
the three aspects of learning.
Morality, concentration, and wisdom.
In this case, the morality would be compassion.
As a bodhisattva, we hold the precept of great compassion.
We love all sentient beings equally without any feeling of anger or resentment.
We need to put ourselves in other people's perspective.
That person's yelling at me because they had a bad day,
or they're sick, they have a headache,
or they just have low self-esteem.
That's how they feel better when they yell at us.
So when you feel their pain, you will feel sympathy,
and you will not be angry anymore.
So that is a bodhisattva's way.
And a bodhisattva will sincerely pray for the other person,
will end his suffering, get rid of the pain inside of him,
and reach enlightenment and happiness.
That's great compassion.
Number two,
we need to practice concentration.
This concentration means great tolerance.
In the Sutra of 42 chapters,
it says tolerance under insult is great power
because it harbors no hatred, only peace and fortitude.
When we are able to tolerate all insults
and all unfavorable situations,
that is great power and great strength.
In Japan,
there was a Zen master in a small village called Haikun.
One day,
his next-door neighbor's teenage daughter
told the parents that she was pregnant.
The parents were furious,
asked her who the father was.
But the daughter wouldn't say.
After much harassment,
she finally said the father was Haikun.
The parents were furious,
went to Haikun and berated him.
All Haikun said was,
Is that so?
After the child was born,
they gave the child to Haikun.
By this time,
his reputation was all ruined.
Everybody despised him in the village,
but that did not trouble him.
All he did was take very good care of the child.
After a few years,
the girl finally told her parents the truth
that the father of the child
was a young man from the fish market.
The parents were embarrassed,
went to Haikun,
and apologized in great length
and begged for forgiveness.
At this time,
Haikun all he did was smile
and said very calmly,
Is that so?
So Haikun,
he's able to endure
all kinds of false accusations
without feeling any anger inside of him.
That is great concentration
and great tolerance.
Number three is wisdom.
We need to have the wisdom
of the Four Noble Truths.
Knowing exactly the cause of my anger
and the suffering we're going through
and what do we need to do
to end the suffering,
that is true wisdom.
When you clearly see
all the cause and effect about everything,
that's when we will be enlightened.
So this is how we use the Dharma
and use the Buddhism
to solve all our life issues.
That's a true practitioner
on the way to end samsara,
and reach nirvana.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.