Today we will talk about Chapter 1 of 14 Chapters of Buddhism, Meaning of Buddha.
All of us are searching for happiness.
One Zen Master said, Happiness without worries is Buddha.
So that is the goal we are trying to reach.
With that in mind, let's talk about the meaning of Buddha.
Buddha actually has two meanings.
One who has wisdom and one who has reached enlightenment.
Let's first talk about wisdom.
There are three kinds of wisdom.
Number one, general and all-knowledge wisdom.
This is the wisdom about emptiness.
Emptiness doesn't mean things don't exist.
It just means things don't have an independent existence.
Everything in this world, both physical and mental,
are interdependent with everything else.
That's what we call conditioned existence.
So it's empty of an intrinsic nature.
With this knowledge, we will let go of our ego and all our attachments.
One day, there was a mother.
She brought the body of her son to Buddha.
And she cried, Buddha, my son suddenly passed away.
Please revive him.
Buddha said, I can only help you if you go into the city and borrow a torch of fire,
from a household that never had a death in the family.
So this mother went into the city, went door to door,
trying to look for a household that never had a death in the family.
But she couldn't find anyone.
So she went back to Buddha empty-handed.
Buddha said, you cannot find any family that never had a death, right?
When there's birth, there will be death.
Everything that looks permanent right now will eventually fall apart.
The rich and the noble right now
will one day become poor.
People that are together right now will one day be separated.
The person that's strong right now will be old and frail one day.
This is the truth about all things.
So you should let go of your attachment to your son.
This mother wouldn't listen.
She cried, Buddha, but I love my child to the bones.
I just want to save my son.
So Buddha manifested big fire pits around this mother.
The mother couldn't stand the fire.
So she couldn't help but use the body of her son as a barrier to block the fire.
And Buddha said, I thought you would rather die in exchange for your son's life.
How come you're using his body as a barrier now?
This mother finally realized her delusion and let go of her attachment to her son.
She started practicing diligently and later she reached first level of arhatship.
So with this wisdom, we will let go of all our attachments.
And let go of our suffering.
This is the wisdom of our arhat.
Number two, differentiation wisdom.
This is the wisdom of a bodhisattva.
Although everything is empty in nature, but it has its conventional truth.
Which has its appearance and form.
So we need to acknowledge everyone's difference and their wonderful existence.
And tailor toward everyone's need.
The best example is Professor Li Binglan.
He went from China to Thailand.
Taiwan when he was already 60 years old in 1950.
He started expanding the Dharma and established Taichung Buddhist Lotus Society.
Which helped more than 300,000 people learn Buddhism.
He also established child care center, orphanage, senior home, hospital and library.
Along with teaching Buddhism, he also taught Chinese medicine and Confucianism.
He was also a great poet.
In one of his poems he wrote,
May the light of Dharma reach far away.
I'm willing to burn myself as a candle.
He passed away when he was 97.
His last words were,
Chen Amitabha Buddha's name single-mindedly undisturbed.
This is a real bodhisattva who has the differentiation wisdom.
And tailored toward everyone's need.
Number three is the overall and perfect wisdom.
This is the wisdom of a Buddha.
Who can balance.
The emptiness and the wonderful existence.
In other words.
Balance, letting go and living life to the fullest.
So in order to reach this wisdom.
We need to acknowledge that we have the Buddha nature.
Which is the synthesis of emptiness and wonderful existence.
In the sutra it says,
Buddha is a realized Buddha.
I am an unrealized Buddha.
But our essence is exactly the same.
So we need to really believe in this.
In the Lotus Sutra.
It talks about a person.
Who had a wish-fulfilling pearl.
Sold inside his clothes.
Without realizing it.
He roamed around in a state of poverty.
Begging for food.
Until one day.
A wise man told him about his pearl.
He exchanged the pearl for great wealth.
Then he realized the pearl did not come from outside.
He had the pearl with him all this time.
The pearl symbolized our Buddha nature.
We all have it within us.
So we need to use our pearl.
And live like a Buddha.
That's the wisdom of overall and perfect wisdom.
Now let's talk about enlightenment.
Enlightenment is more about the cause.
And wisdom is about the result.
So in order to reach enlightenment.
We need to be aware and realize.
We need to be aware that we have the obstacle of affliction.
We have the affliction that's blocking us.
From our general and all knowledge wisdom.
We have a lot of afflictions.
Usually we call it delusion on views and thoughts.
We have the view that we have the ego as ourselves.
So we are all very selfish.
That's our deluded view.
And we also have thoughts.
That's usually full of greed, anger, ignorance, arrogance and doubt.
Especially arrogance.
We are not aware of it.
When Napoleon was the emperor of France.
One day he decided to take a trip by himself.
He went to a small town.
He checked into a hotel.
And he started walking around the area.
But he got lost and couldn't find his way back to the hotel.
Good thing there was a soldier that was standing there.
So he asked the soldier.
How do I get back to the hotel in the city?
The soldier didn't care for Napoleon.
He just casually stretched out his hand.
To point to the road on the right.
Napoleon said politely.
Can you please tell me how far is it from here?
The man said impatiently.
A mile.
Even though he was very rude.
Napoleon said thank you.
And may I ask.
What rank are you in the army?
The soldier said.
Why don't you take a guess?
Napoleon said.
Are you a lieutenant?
He said no.
Keep guessing.
Are you a captain?
No.
Keep guessing.
You must be a major.
The soldier nodded proudly.
Then the soldier asked Napoleon.
Are you also in the army?
What is your rank?
Napoleon said.
Why don't you take a guess?
He said.
Are you a lieutenant?
No.
Are you a captain?
Are you also a major?
No.
You must be a general.
Keep guessing.
Are you the emperor of France?
Napoleon nodded.
The major's voice trembled.
And said in a panic.
Your majesty.
Please forgive me.
Napoleon said.
My dear major.
You didn't commit any crime.
So I will not punish you.
But I advise you.
You should treat other people.
With respect.
Please forgive me.
Napoleon said.
My dear major.
You didn't commit any crime.
So I will not punish you.
But I advise you.
You should treat other people.
With respect.
And be more modest.
So we need to let go of our arrogance.
Because that is blocking us.
From our enlightenment.
Our obstacle of affliction.
Is like a thief.
That's stealing from us.
We are not aware.
We have this thief.
Stealing our pearls.
And we still treat the thieves.
Like our beloved children.
We need to capture the thieves.
So they will not steal from us anymore.
That is called awareness.
And then we have to do.
We have to do.
And then we need to realize.
That we have.
Obstacle of knowledge.
Is delusion.
That's blocking us.
From knowing.
What we're supposed to know.
So there are two kinds of.
Obstacle of Knowledge.
One is called.
Mineal dust-like delusion.
We have.
Discrimination.
About everything.
To everyone.
And this discrimination.
Is numerous.
Like the dust in the air.
We are not aware.
That we have.
These delusions.
That is blocking us.
From our differentiation.
With tension.
ABD crowded us.
We are becomingouched.
Stuck in the abyss.
them. There was a general in China called Li Guang. He was a great archer. One day he
thought he saw a tiger far away so he shot an arrow toward the tiger. When he went to
retrieve the kill he realized it wasn't a tiger. It was actually a great boulder. He
was amazed how the arrow penetrated the rock. He went back to the same area trying to produce
the same result but for the life of him arrows just keep deflecting off the boulder. Because
now that he knew it was a rock he assumed that arrows cannot penetrate rocks. That's
why he couldn't produce the same result again. So our knowledge and our delusion and discrimination
is blocking us from what we are supposed to know. That is called obstacle of knowledge.
We have another kind of obstacle of knowledge that is called delusion on fundamental ignorance.
This is what's blocking our overall and perfect wisdom.
We have fundamental ignorance. We have fundamental ignorance. We have fundamental ignorance.
fundamental ignorance of not knowing our true Buddha nature. Our true Buddha nature is actually the synthesis of
emptiness and wonderful existence. We have this mean or this middle way of the truth that we call suchness or
absolute mind. We don't believe that we have it. That is our biggest
ignorance. We are sleeping. We are in a dreamlike state and don't know we're sleeping.
So we need to learn Buddhism to wake ourselves up, to be awakened from our sleeping and dream state. That is called
enlightenment. So in summary, there are three kinds of enlightenment. Number one is self enlightenment.
This is the enlightenment of our art hat who
eradicated their delusion on view and thought and reached general and all knowledge wisdom. Number two is
enlightenment of others. That's the enlightenment of a bodhisattva
who overcame their minute dust-like delusions and reached
differentiation wisdom. Number three is a perfect and complete enlightenment.
That's the enlightenment of a Buddha who have eradicated their delusion on
fundamental ignorance and reached overall and perfect wisdom. That's the meaning of Buddha in a nutshell.
Next time we will talk about chart B and C of chapter one which talks more about our obstacle affliction
and our obstacle of knowledge. So that's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.