Today we are going to talk about moments before death.
Everyone has to face death eventually, so the question is how do we prepare for death?
We will use the verses from the Practices and Vows of Universal Worthy Bodhisattva to understand death.
As one is dying at the last moment, first we have to realize that no one can escape death.
In the Dharma Pada Sutra, Buddha tells a story about four brothers with supernatural powers
who knew their demise was coming in seven days, so each tried to escape.
The first brother hid himself under the sea, so death cannot find him.
The second brother hid himself in the highest mountain.
The third brother went up into the sky and hid in the clouds.
The fourth brother blended himself in the bustling street markets.
After seven days, all four of them still died, so death is inevitable.
In Buddhism, we meditate on death.
There are three steps to this death.
Meditation.
One is to think that we will die for sure.
In your mind's eye, visualize the people that you knew who are already dead.
Think of the people who are alive right now.
They will die one day.
Then think of yourself disappearing from the earth.
That day will happen.
So that's the first step.
The second step is to know death.
Death can come anytime.
You can die when you're very young or you can die when you're 100.
It can happen anytime.
Every breath can be our last breath.
We have to cherish every moment that we're living right now.
Every moment we should live fully.
Number three, when I'm dying, nothing can help me except the Dharma.
Only my understanding of the Dharma can stay with me when I'm dying.
Especially for Pure Land Buddhism, I believe in Amitabha Buddha.
Take refuge in his name and in him.
You end this meditation with a few recitations of the name Amitabha.
And then you finish up this death meditation.
Don't be afraid of the death meditation.
If you do this every day, you will have profound liberating insight into impermanence.
When you really understand impermanence
and understand that all conditional existence are elusive in nature,
you'll no longer be attached to anything,
that's actually nirvana or we call the state of no birth and no death.
What happens when we pass away?
At the last moment when all one's faculties scatter and decay.
This is talking about our body.
This body is like a machine.
Now it's shutting down.
We don't want to be attached to this body that is temporary.
We should see our body like a traveler that's staying in a hotel.
Or we can see our body like a rental car.
We're just renting it for a few days.
This body is borrowed from us.
It's in a normal karmic condition.
It is impermanent.
To all the relatives, one has to leave behind.
All our relatives, including our parents, spouse, children, siblings and loved ones,
nobody can go with you when you pass.
The key is to cherish every moment that you spend with them.
Stop arguing about the trivial matters of life
because all of us are going to pass one day.
So we want to have no regrets toward anyone.
On the other hand, we also do not want to be attached to anyone.
It should be love without any attachment.
So we want to have no regrets and no attachment.
That is the middle way.
Number three, all powers and status are lost.
Everything that you have, your position, your power,
everything will be lost the moment that you die.
It talks about four subcategories.
One, one's prime ministers and officials.
As if we are a king of a country.
All the people that are working for you, they will no longer be with you.
Two is your inner palaces and outer cities.
That's like your land, your house, your properties.
Three, elephants, horses and cars.
Your favorite car, your favorite vehicle will no longer be yours.
Number four, precious jewels and hidden treasures.
All your jewelries and money will no longer matter anymore.
So in conclusion, all can no longer accompany one.
Nothing can accompany you.
In the Yokakara Bomi Shastra, it talks about three improper meditative reflections.
One is reflection on never dying.
This is like the first one.
We think our body is going to live on forever.
That's why when we're meditating,
we cannot concentrate.
Number two, reflection on our relatives.
We are always thinking about how our relatives are doing,
their happiness and sorrow.
That's why we cannot concentrate when we're meditating.
Number three is reflection on our country.
It's like the third one.
We're always thinking about what's going on in this country,
our possessions.
That's why we cannot concentrate when we meditate.
So all these improper meditative reflections,
they will also come up when we're dying.
They will become karmic obstacles.
They will hinder our rebirth to the pure land.
So what will actually help us?
Only one's vows will not forsake and leave one.
The only thing that will help you is your bodhi resolve,
your bodhisattva vows.
That's the only thing you can take with you
because that's the most wholesome,
most virtuous thought you can have.
This is actually talking about the ten great aspirations
of universal, worthy bodhisattva.
Number one is to pay respect to all Buddhas.
Everyone is a Buddha.
We need to love and respect everyone.
That's the first vow.
Number two is to praise the Tathagata.
Use your mouth to praise all the people
who are going to be Buddha,
all their good qualities and all their virtues.
Number three is to pray.
To make abundant offerings.
We want to be as giving as we can.
Number four, repent all our sins.
Change all our bad ways into wholesome conduct.
Number five is to rejoice in other people's merits.
We don't want to be jealous of anyone.
We want to be a real bodhisattva
that's without jealousy or envy.
Number six, request the turning of the Dharma wheel.
Right now you're listening to Dharma.
God is requesting the turning of the Dharma wheel.
Number seven is to request the Buddha
to remain in this world.
You are the Buddha,
so you want yourself to be with the Dharma.
Then you are a Buddha living in the world.
Number eight is to follow Buddha's teaching all the time.
Always learning the Buddha's teaching
and always have the Dharma in our hearts.
Number nine is to constantly accord
with all sentient beings.
We want to be in harmony with everybody in our lives.
Number ten is to dedicate all our merits
to all sentient beings.
We love and we give all our merits
to everyone that is in our life
and to everyone in this world.
So that's the ten great aspirations
of a real bodhisattva.
If you can do this all your life
at the moment of your death,
that's the only thing on your mind,
then you'll definitely go to the Western world.
Go to the Western Pure Land.
At all times,
the vows will guide one forward
and in an instant,
one will be reborn
in the land of ultimate bliss.
All your vows,
they will guide you forward
when you're dying.
And in one instant,
you will be in the Western Pure Land.
But you will ask,
the Western Pure Land
is 100 billion Buddha lands away.
How can we get there in an instant?
It's because
everything is happening in our mind.
That's why in one instant,
you will be there
in the land of ultimate bliss
where there is no more birth
and no more death.
Pure Land Buddhism is about
faith, vows and practice.
What is this vow?
This vow is actually
the Bodhi resolve,
the ten great aspirations
of universal worthy bodhisattva.
So going to the Pure Land,
it's not just
we want to go to the Pure Land.
It's going to the Pure Land
to complete our bodhisattva path.
Our Bodhi resolve is our anchor
at the brink of our death.
That's how we connect with Amitabha Buddha.
Lastly, I want to share
about the Infinite Life Sutra.
Amitabha was a king.
He left his kingdom to become a monk.
His name was Dhammakara.
At that time,
there was a Buddha.
His name is
Lokavara Raja.
He said,
If one scoops water out of the ocean
with the cup,
he will reach the bottom
after many kalpas.
Likewise,
if one sincerely,
diligently and unceasingly
seeks the way,
he will be able to reach his destiny.
So what vow is there
that cannot be fulfilled?
If one uses a cup to scoop water
out of the ocean,
will he be able to
scoop it all?
Yes, he will.
Because of his perseverance
and Bodhi resolve,
you can accomplish anything.
That's when Dhammakara
officially made the 48 vows
and created the Pure Land.
So we want to have the same mind,
same spirit as Amitabha Buddha.
That's how you will be reborn
in his Pure Land.
So Pure Land Buddhism
is not just about chanting
the Buddha's name.
It is about bringing forth
your real Bodhi resolve.
You really want to become a Buddha
to save all sentient beings.
And you want to be enlightened.
When one obtains enlightenment,
one will realize
there's actually no birth
and no death.
Because our true nature
is the nature of no birth
and no death.
That's originally Nirvana.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.