Today we are going to talk about identity in 6 degrees.
The question is, who are you?
Are you your body?
How good looking you are?
Are you the social status?
Or are you your talents?
Your achievements?
Your athlete?
Your artist?
We are none of that.
Those are just identity that we take on this lifetime.
That's not your real identity.
Our real identity is Buddhahood.
We are Buddha.
We are awakened one.
We are the consciousness of the world.
First, it's called identity in principle.
Before any cultivation, we have to know that everybody is a Buddha in principle.
Even a criminal, a dog, or even an ant.
They are Buddha originally.
That is the principle we have to believe.
When you believe in that, you will treat everyone differently.
Because you see everyone as a Buddha.
And we call this Buddha nature true suchness.
It is the truth.
It's not the fake self.
It's the real self, the real identity.
Suchness means it is what it is.
Originally, you are this higher self, the higher spirit of the universe.
Know that for a fact.
That's the first stage of identity.
The second is called identity in words.
This is when you never heard about Buddhism or any of the Dharma,
which is Buddha's teaching.
At this stage, you actually hear about Buddha's teaching.
He kind of confirms that we are the same as he is.
He is the awakened one.
We are not anything less than he is.
He is not anything higher than we are.
We are all the same.
We are all equal in our nature and we are all the perfect self.
So know that in words, which means you believe in the teaching.
When you start listening to Buddha's teaching, you will be amazed.
I wish I learned this when I was little.
Then I would lead a different life because I would know so much more.
Not just like a scholar, like philosophy or psychology.
It's not just a study that you read about.
You practice into your own life and you change your whole existence.
Know that identify yourself as the Buddha
in words, which means in Buddha's teaching.
And then we will come into the third stage, identity in contemplative.
That means not only do we hear about the Dharma
that confirms that we have the Buddha nature, the higher self,
we start practicing by meditating.
Contemplative means we are aware of our thoughts.
None of us are really, really aware.
We are really conscious every day of our thoughts.
But what if every moment, just like you're breathing,
you're conscious, you're aware of all your thoughts.
Change your life for the better.
Let go of the idea of the self and the ego
because the ego is the opposite of our true suchness.
When you're full of the self and the ego,
my thinking and my judgment of the world
you lose your true suchness.
You live a life of misery.
There was a wife in the olden days.
They're kind of poor.
You know, they live in a farm.
The wife likes to go shop in the city
and she usually likes to buy little decorative things
or maybe some curtains and little things to decorate her house
just to enjoy life a little bit more.
Because they have no money
so she usually buys some credit to the shop owner.
One day, the husband went to the shop
and told the owner,
please don't sell to my wife anymore on credit.
She went back to the store,
found out that her husband actually did that.
She was furious.
For the next 50 years,
she never forget about this.
She tells it to everybody.
My husband did this to me.
How can you have done that?
Because she's full of her ego.
She's living in her world.
She only knows of herself
and cannot live in her true suchness.
So when we are contemplative,
we are aware of our thoughts.
What is the ego thinking
or what is our true Buddha nature thinking?
You have to be mindful of your thoughts.
Quiet your mind.
That's the only way to be mindful.
Okay, and then we come to the fourth identity.
Identity in similarity.
After this,
you have some cultivation.
You cultivated three ways of meditation.
You are similar like a real Buddha now.
You actually have practiced a lot of meditation
and you change yourself to be in line
with your true suchness.
And we talked about these three meditations
in prior classes.
So now we'll just review a little.
There's three main meditations.
The first is called Void.
Void meditation is knowing the emptiness of the ego.
I am not this ego of my perception of the world.
My perception is not necessarily correct.
That's based on a selfish me.
It's based on your education.
It's based on what people told you when you grow up.
It's not permanent.
The perfect you is permanent
and without all this changing.
So the self that you're using right now,
your thoughts,
let it be empty.
Void means emptiness.
That will give you peace.
When you quiet your mind,
so your mind does not name things,
judge things.
When Buddha was alive,
he told people how to count your breathing.
It's just to stop thinking.
Count your breathing.
It's just another way to say,
don't think.
Don't name anything.
Practice.
When you see someone,
don't say fat or skinny, small.
Small, big, pretty, ugly.
If you don't name things,
aren't you more at peace?
That's your true suchness.
It's void meditation.
Okay, so let go of all thoughts.
Your true self emerges.
The second is called unreal.
So all your thoughts are impermanent.
All your thinking, they're not real.
And this whole world is not real,
but you go on with the conventional life.
You still excel
and be the best that you can be.
And you still do what you think is right.
And you still be great whatever you are,
whatever you do.
A gardener came this morning.
We asked him to cut the big tree in front of our house.
They did it so fast in less than two hours.
And now it's beautifully shaped.
They did this amazing job.
So you don't have to think so much
or worry or think,
I have to do this, I have to do that.
I have a lot of tension.
But you do everything perfectly
because you're quiet
and you actually become more than you can be.
And the last meditation is called the me.
That means you balance.
You let go, but you excel.
You let go of any stress or ego.
Don't think about the self, but excel.
Do everything that you can do
and manifest greatness for the world.
When you reach this balance,
you kind of align with your true suchness.
We come to the fifth identity.
Identity of partial realization.
After the meditation,
you get rid of all your delusions of the mind.
And you partially become a real Buddha.
You get rid of all your wandering thoughts.
At this level, you do not think,
but you know everything.
Buddha does not think,
but he knows everything that's going on.
In the sutra, it says,
how many drops of rain in this world,
he knows.
Because he doesn't think.
He has no idea of the self.
But he knows everything.
When you come to this level,
you are almost a Buddha.
The sixth stage is called ultimate identity.
It's when you become a real Buddha.
Just like the Buddha
that was in India 2,600 years ago.
He reached his enlightenment when he was 30.
We can all reach this level of Buddhahood
if we just go through the six stages of identity.
In the Christian scripture,
there is a verse,
be still and know that I am God.
I changed it to
be still and know that
I am Buddha.
Be still means being without thinking.
Be in your quiet mind.
And know,
know means a deep knowing.
You know for a fact
that I am,
which is the higher spiritual identity.
Not this body,
not this life,
not this family,
but I am the Buddha.
That is one with the universe.
All our Buddha nature is one nature.
All of us has one Buddha nature.
And that's formless and perfect and complete.
Okay, so that's the lesson for today
to confirm that we are all Buddha
and we can all reach awakening and enlightenment.
Okay, thank you for listening.
Amitabha.