Today we will talk about Love All Equally.
Buddha's mind is a mind of great compassion.
We will use verses of Confucius' teaching to learn about love all equally.
Hopefully it will bring out our great compassion.
Let's first talk about our body.
How do we treat others with great compassion?
1.
Don't flatter the rich or despise the poor.
Great compassion is unconditional love, without any discrimination based on people's wealth
or status.
Shakyamuni Buddha was a prince, but he left the kingdom to search for the truth.
When he finally reached Buddhahood, he went back to his country to teach.
His father, the king, wanted to help Buddha.
So he asked all the elites of the Shakyamuni to become Buddha's disciples.
At the same time, there was a barber named Upali.
He really wanted to become Buddha's disciple as well.
So he asked the elites to join him.
But the elites looked down on him and told him, there is no way that a sutra, which is
the lowest social class in India, can become Buddha's disciple.
But Upali did not give up.
He actually rushed to see Buddha, and of course Buddha accepted him as a disciple.
When the elites arrived, Buddha accepted him as a disciple.
He also asked them to bow down to Upali.
And simply asked them to bow down to Upali.
The elites were furious when they saw Upali and refused to bow down to him.
So Buddha said to them, a man is noble based on his behavior, not on his social class.
You guys are actually of a lower class because you are now slaves of your arrogance.
The elites finally bowed down to Upali.
Buddha is a great teacher that taught us true equality.
Number two, Always Give More and Take Less!
This is a very ancient doctrine.
A Bodhisattva is always giving because they want other people to be happy.
So by giving, they will make others happy and benefit others.
A Bodhisattva is always aware of any greediness that arises in them.
So they use giving to eradicate any of their greediness.
In ancient China, there was a little boy.
His parents passed away when he was young.
So he was raised by his uncle and he lived with his uncle's seven sons.
When he reached adulthood,
uncle wanted to divide up the family inheritance into two shares.
One for him and one for his seven sons.
But this boy told uncle,
I will just only take one eighth of the family inheritance
because I'm the same class as your sons.
Uncle says, no, you represent your dad, so you deserve half.
This boy insists, so the uncle divided up the family share into eight shares.
All seven sons, they were very happy.
This boy later became a prominent government official because of his virtues.
Always give more and take less.
Number three, treat subordinates with kindness and generosity.
In the Bodhisattva precept, it says,
all men are my fathers and all women are my mothers.
We should treat the subordinates as our own parents.
Do not just use them for labors.
There's a family that had a nanny for over 20 years.
They really appreciate the nanny.
The nanny service over the years, when she's about to retire,
they give him a house and a large retirement package.
So we always want to treat subordinates with kindness and generosity.
Now let's talk about it in terms of our speech.
How do we speak to others with great compassion?
Number one, don't expose others' shortcomings or secrets.
In Chinese, we have a saying,
conceal wrongdoing and disclose goodness.
That includes our parents,
or our siblings,
or anyone that we know.
We do not want to disclose their shortcomings.
Also, this is a Bodhisattva precept,
not to disclose any shortcomings of the monks,
or nuns, or laymen, or laywomen.
Make sure that we don't break any precepts.
Do not talk about the wrongdoing of another temple,
and do not talk about the wrongdoings of other Bodhisattva.
These are all large offenses.
Number two, praising the goodness of others is a virtue,
especially when people really need it.
When people are really sick or they're emotionally very down,
if you give them some kind words and say,
you're such a great mother,
we really appreciate all your love and generosity,
and we really love you.
When you give people kindness,
they will have the cheerful heart,
their sickness will recover faster.
Even if they pass away because of their positive wholesome thoughts,
they will be reborn in a good state of mind.
Number three,
if you give them some kind words and say,
you're such a great mother,
you really appreciate all your love and generosity,
they will be reborn in a good state of mind.
So always give sincere praises.
Number three,
encourage virtues and give sound advices
when people are having mistakes.
We do not expose people's shortcomings,
but we have the duty to help them transform and change.
There was two brothers.
The older brother was a government official.
He started taking briberies.
So he thought of a way.
He actually went to be a servant
and worked as a servant for a whole year.
After the year,
all the money that he made,
he brought it to the older brother and said,
dear brother,
we should make money honestly with our own labor
and not to take any money that's not supposed to be ours.
The older brother felt ashamed of himself
and actually transformed.
With sincerity,
great compassion and wisdom,
we can convince others
to transform.
Now let's talk about in terms of our mind.
What is our attitude of compassion?
Number one,
don't impose on others what you do not desire.
This is actually one of the biggest teaching of Confucius.
Confucius says there's one word that you can practice all your life
and that word is tolerance.
Always be tolerant of others.
Put yourself in other people's shoes and see how they feel.
For example,
your parents-in-law should treat the daughter-in-law and son-in-law
as their own children
and not treat them like outsiders.
The daughter-in-law and the son-in-law
should treat the parents-in-law as their own mom and dad.
Respect and love them as if they're own parents.
This is all reciprocal.
Relationship is based on our heart,
view for other people's position.
That is true compassion.
Number two, repay kindness and let go of resentment.
Feeling of gratitude,
gratitude is the key to happiness.
Always be grateful for everybody.
We study hard because we want to pay back our parents' kindness
and we study the Dharma
because we want to pay back Buddha's great kindness to us.
Always feel gratitude and appreciation.
You will live a life on purpose and you'll feel very fulfilled.
Also, we want to let go of resentments.
Do not hold any grudges toward anyone.
Always forget about the wrongdoings.
Be grateful for all the people that love us
and we also want to be grateful for the people that abused us,
backstabbed us and hurt us
because they made us stronger,
have more wisdom,
have more compassion.
So be grateful.
Turn good karmic relationships and bad karmic relationships
into Dharma relationships,
which means we're all growing spiritually.
That's all we're trying to do in this lifetime.
That way, every relationship is going to be a good one.
Every relationship is a good relationship.
Everything that happened to you is a good thing.
So you will be a bodhisattva
and you will practice very carefully and happily.
So treat our loved ones and our enemies equally.
That is true compassion.
In the Diamond Sutra, it basically teaches us
to detach from all appearance and cultivate all goodness.
So we want to detach from all the appearance of
this is my enemy, this is my loved one.
That way, we can really practice all goodness.
Number three, use reasoning, not power, to influence others.
Do not use authority to impose on others.
We always want to use sound reasoning,
such as cause and effect.
We don't want to say,
I'm the mother, I'm the father,
you must listen to me.
If you just use your authority,
even if they listen and obey,
their hearts will not be with you.
There was a little girl, Natalie,
and her younger brother.
One day, the girl was very upset at the younger brother,
so she complained to her father.
Dad, Nathan broke my toy, ate my ice cream,
and drew all over my homework.
The father calmly talked to Natalie,
What about you? Did you do anything wrong today?
Natalie thought about it and said,
Yes, I forgot to fold my blankets this morning.
I lost my homework and I didn't do the dishes.
So the father said,
So you made mistakes too.
We need to forgive ourselves and forgive all others.
Like Bob, one of the little girl's head,
she happily forgave her younger brother.
So the father used sound reasoning to teach his children
and not use his authority.
That is the only way to influence and teach others.
These are simple ways for us to bring out our great compassion.
Just like the Zen master said,
A three-year-old can understand,
but an 80-year-old still can't.
We still struggle to do it.
So we just need to be aware,
practice daily,
and do not give up.
If we conduct ourselves with these standards,
we are already walking the Bodhisattva way.
So thank you for listening.
Amitabha.