Today we are going to talk about Settling the Mind.
In the Lotus Sutra, it states that Buddha peacefully dwelling in the Great Vehicle,
dignified with the powers of meditative absorption and perfect wisdom, saves all sentient beings
from sufferings.
Buddha has meditated absorption and perfect wisdom.
Both of these come from deep meditation.
Thus we need to learn how to meditate and settle our mind.
Today we are going to learn 5 meditations to settle our mind and each of the meditation
tailors for a specific affliction.
Number 1 for greed, contemplate on the impurities of the body.
A lot of people are afraid of this meditation but it is actually a great antidote for curing
our sensual desires, our strongest greed.
For example, if you see someone that is beautiful and you start having sensual desires, what
you can do is say to yourself, since the skin on this body is rotting away, smelly, living
on a filthy body and deteriorating, skin is disgusting to see and touch.
And if you love the hair of this person, you can say to yourself, I love the hair of this
person.
If you repeat the same thing, hair on this body is rotting away, smelly, living on a
filthy body, deteriorating, hair is disgusting to see and touch.
If you keep repeating these verses, you will get rid of all your lusts.
Another way is called the white skeleton meditation.
Basically you have x-ray eyes and you see everyone beyond their flesh and skin.
You see everybody as white bones walking around, sitting still.
That way you will get rid of all your attachments.
So once you reach the root of goodness in this meditation, you will have enlightenment
about impermanence and you will be detached from all desires and the perception of the
self.
Number two, for anger, contemplate on compassion.
Anger when we are angry, our mind is definitely agitated and not settled.
So we need to use compassion meditation.
There is a reason why we need compassion.
There is a great compassion meditation called the seven point cause and effect meditation.
Before we do this meditation, we need to develop the mind of equanimity, which is feeling peaceful
and calm about all sentient beings.
You can think of three people, one, a friend that you love, two, an enemy you dislike,
three, a stranger you don't really know, then you think, one, the person I love right now
in prior lifetime was probably my enemy, so don't be too attached to the person.
Number two, the enemy right now that I dislike in prior lifetime was probably my loved one,
so let go of the animosity.
Three, the stranger I do not care about right now, that's not right in prior lifetime was
probably my loved one, so start loving the person.
If you can treat your friend, enemy, and stranger exactly the same, that is called equanimity.
With this mentality, we start the seven point cause and effect meditation.
You think of all sentient beings.
Ask your mother who gives you motherly love, but if you don't like your mother, then don't
use your mother.
You can use a father or a grandmother or grandfather or even a master that you really admire.
Number two, you will think of the kindness of the mother.
She changed your diaper and fed you and did everything for you.
You really appreciate all the kindness.
Number three, you want to repay her kindness.
You really want to take care of her.
And help her in any way you can because you really appreciate all her kindness.
Then you will develop number four, great love, and number five, great compassion.
Great love is you want to give her happiness.
Great compassion, you want to uproot her sufferings.
Great love, you really want to appraise her, help her, spend time with her, and even teaching
her Buddhism, let her gain wisdom and true happiness.
And you want to give her great compassion.
You want to uproot all her sufferings as if she's falling off a cliff and you want
to save her.
Number six, you will develop exceptional resolve.
You feel this responsibility, I'm the only one who can save my mother.
You feel this urgency and you're on a great mission to help her.
Number seven, you will develop Bodhi mind, that is called the Bodhi Chitta, the true
mind of a Bodhisattva who really wants to become a Buddha to save all sentient beings
from suffering because all sentient beings are my mother.
If you can go through the seven point cause and effect meditation, you will no longer
have any anger toward anyone.
So once you develop the root of goodness in this meditation, in real life, you'll be able
to treat all people with love and kindness.
Number three, for lack of focus, count the breath.
A lot of us lack focus.
Often we have so much thing going on in our lives.
We cannot sit down and start meditating.
What we can do is Anapana meditation, which is focusing on our breath.
Inhale, exhale, one, inhale, exhale, two, all the way up to ten.
If you have wandering thoughts in between, just start over from one.
And if you don't like counting, you can use a mantra or use Amitabha Buddha's name, inhale
ah, exhale me, inhale two.
Inhale ta, exhale ba.
In Chinese, it will be omi tofo.
If you keep repeating this process, you will be able to anchor and focus your mind and
go into deep meditation.
When you're really good at it, you no longer need to count and you'll be able to follow
your breathing easily and effortlessly.
Once you reach the root of goodness in this meditation, you will have inconceivable joy,
clarity and tranquility.
Every hairbrush will be filled with joy.
Every pore of your body will relaxingly open and your inner eye will be able to see all
36 things inside of your body like an open fridge.
Number four, for ignorance, contemplate on cause and conditions.
Ignorant, we don't mean someone who don't have knowledge.
You can be a PhD and is still considered ignorant, which means someone who has a strong sense
of the self and their ego.
Then we need to focus on cause and conditions.
Cause is the most important thing.
Cause is basically the main factor of everything and conditions are the helping factors.
For example, you have an apple seed, that's the cause.
You plant it in the soil, you give it sunlight and water and it grows into a tree.
So everything in this world is basically cause and conditions.
In this cause and condition, there is not a me, so it's empty of a self.
So Buddha says to contemplate on all things and see the cause and conditions that is empty
of a self.
We should think about our body and mind the same way.
So Buddha called the body and mind the five aggregates or the five skantas, which are
form, feeling, perception, formation, and consciousness.
You should think all your body and mind as empty.
For example, you see your form, this is just a body, it's not my body.
When I'm sick, it's just cause and conditions.
This is not me.
I am the Buddha nature.
I am the treasury of Tathagata.
Number two, my feeling.
This person criticizes me, I'm upset.
This feeling is not me, it's just cause and conditions happening.
I'm much bigger than this.
I'm not this feeling.
I am the treasury of Tathagata.
Number three, my perception is not me.
How come in my mother, Yao Ling, and my brother, I don't feel anything, but mother Yao Ling
and me, I'm insulted.
I'm insulted and upset, it's because I have a false sense of the self.
Let go of this because it's just cause and conditions happening.
Let go of my perception.
I am the treasury of Tathagata.
Number four, mental formation.
All my attachments of likes and dislikes, love and hate, all this is not me.
It's just my false sense of the self.
I am much bigger than this.
I am the treasury of Tathagata.
Number five, all my consciousness.
Including my alaya consciousness, it's not the true me.
It's just a whole big complex cause and conditions going on.
That's not the real me.
The real me is the perfect consciousness, what we call the treasury of the Tathagata.
So if you can think of all your body and mind in this manner, you will understand non-self.
There's not a me.
If you reach the root of goodness in this meditation, your heart will be filled with
abiding joy.
Join in the dharma and you'll be free from all desires and detached from the self.
Number five, for karmic obstacles, be mindful of the Buddha.
Karmic obstacle, it means when you have all of the above, you're greedy, angry, lack
focus and ignorant, then you have strong karmic obstacle that's blocking you from enlightenment.
What we can do is be mindful of the Buddha.
This doesn't just mean chanting the Buddha's name.
It means recollecting on Buddha's merits.
For example, all Buddhas have ten general names.
One is called worthy of offerings.
Buddha, like an art hand who's worthy of all kinds of great offerings because they are
slayers of evil.
They get rid of all their afflictions and they have no secret afflictions.
So if you open up their mind, it's perfectly wholesome and mindful.
That's my favorite part.
So contemplate on it.
Think about it in great detail.
And then you will feel like you really want to be a Buddha.
And an art hand is also someone who is no longer subject to life and death.
That's also great.
And another name of a Buddha is called excellent trainer.
Buddha knows everybody's every lifetime of karma, their affliction, their personality.
So Buddha is able to give the right medicine, the right Dharma to each person accordingly.
Think about the merits of Buddha.
Concentrate.
See the benefits of the de-selected.
Benefit from the dry cold.
Know your body, know your existence.
Know your soul.
How you can be aware of whether you love
the good in one's life.
Ho Priya!
all phenomena are just cause and conditions in this cause and condition is empty of a self
of a me so there's no owner we do not own our body or mind there's no ownership of anything
it just cause and effect we need to realize emptiness so resting the mind to reach its
essence resting the mind let go of the idea of the self if you can let go of your identity
when you meditate 90% of your wandering thoughts will disappear if there's not a me there's nothing
to wonder about let go of the identity of the self then your essence will emerge your true self
your buddha nature your suchness your treasury of tathagata and will emerge then one is known
as a shaman which is a true practitioner who practice the morality concentration and wisdom
and who is
ascetic
who has spiritual discipline and is on the way to enlightenment so it's not hard to settle
our mind we just need to deal with our afflictions with the proper meditation and let go of the
idea of the self so that's the class for today thank you for listening Amitabha