Today we are going to talk about the Ten Vows of Universal Worthy Bodhisattva.
This is the last lesson.
The last three is number eight, nine, and ten.
And today we are going to complete the Ten Vows.
The eighth one is to always follow the teachings of Buddha.
We want to always follow Buddha's teachings so you don't forget how to be a Buddha.
We learn Buddhism, we cultivate, so we can all become Buddhas.
How do you become Buddha? You gotta always follow the teachings.
There are six ways you should always watch yourself.
Do I look like a Buddha?
Walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, talking, working.
Do I act like a Buddha? Am I being a Buddha?
Always check yourself. This is a meditation in itself.
Every time we're walking, you ask yourself three things.
First, am I doing good deeds or bad deeds by walking?
Am I walking to help someone or am I walking to hit someone?
What am I doing?
So first, ask yourself, is it moral what I'm doing?
And second, ask yourself, is this walking in line with my deep concentration?
Step by step, can I feel my feet on the ground and I'm being calm and stable just like I'm meditating?
Third, ask yourself, is this walking in line with my wisdom?
Do I have the wisdom of knowing it's not just me walking?
I am walking.
I am walking like a Buddha with my own Buddha nature inside.
So walking, is it a cultivation?
Yes.
Walking is a cultivation.
Standing, you ask yourself the same three questions.
Am I standing to do a good deed or is this a bad deed?
Is it in line with my calmness and my meditation practice?
Am I standing upright and doing it like a Buddha?
And third,
Do I have the wisdom of Buddha when I'm standing here?
I am as a spiritual person, as a Buddha.
No matter if you're walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, talking, working, you want to be like a Buddha.
So learning the Buddha's way.
It's very important that we get close to virtuous people.
If you don't listen to the teaching all the time, you will go back to your old ways and you'll lose your good practice.
For all mundane people, it's really hard for us to keep aware of what we're doing.
Human beings are very influenced by our environment.
So we need to get close to good people.
There's a story about this elephant.
This elephant is very, very big and very belligerent.
Whenever he sees a person, he just stumps on the person and kills the person.
So the king uses this elephant as a weapon
to kill all the criminals and enemies.
One time, the place the elephant was staying was burned.
So they moved the elephant to another location.
This location happened to be next to a temple.
The elephant listened to the monks chanting every day.
After a while, every time he sees people, he just uses his trunk and smiles at them.
He doesn't stomp on them anymore.
Because why?
He's been next to the temple.
So the king found out.
We can't have an elephant coming like that.
So they moved the elephant next to the slaughterhouse.
The elephant listened to the butcher and slaughtered the animals every day.
Sure enough, he became belligerent again.
And he starts stumping on people again.
So we are very influenced by our environment.
If you don't have good people to get close to,
listen to the Dharma, to the teachings all the time.
So you'll acquire what the Buddha likes
and change our way for the better.
That is the main reason we want to go to the Western Pure Land.
Because Amitabha Buddha built this world for us,
the perfect school to cultivate into Buddhahood.
Nobody over there is a bad influence.
Everybody is a Bodhisattva.
Everybody wants you to become a Buddha.
That's why we vow to go to the Western Pure Land of Amitabha.
So that's the first one, to always follow the teachings of Buddha.
Second,
to be always in harmony with all beings.
A Bodhisattva is always in harmony with everyone.
Why are we in disharmony with people?
Because we don't like people that are different.
We have conflicts because they are different.
We don't like them or we judge them or we discriminate.
But that's not a Bodhisattva's way.
A Bodhisattva is always in harmony with everybody.
Because why?
He wants to help everyone.
A Bodhisattva is someone that always helps others.
We not only go out of our way to help them.
It says in the sutra,
Buddha vows to help the sick, the lost, the depressed, the poor.
In his heart, he wants to be a good doctor to the ones that are sick.
What does that mean?
When someone is sick in their mind,
for example, we have our defilement,
we're greedy, we're angry, we're ignorant.
That's our sickness.
A Bodhisattva will try to help the sick get rid of their defilement.
And we want to help the lost find their way.
Sometimes we lose our moral judgment and our values
and we do things that are immoral.
The Bodhisattva will try to help so you will no longer be lost
and find the right path.
And whenever someone is depressed,
a Bodhisattva will give them light and help them be confident,
be by their side and make them feel better about themselves
so they will be happy.
And whenever someone is poor,
we want to help them find the treasure inside of them.
Everyone is a Buddha.
Nobody should be poor.
If you believe in yourself,
then you can make millions of dollars and just believe in yourself.
We all have the Buddha nature.
We should all believe in ourselves.
So a Bodhisattva will help people to believe in themselves
and to become rich and have abundance.
So always try to help others and be in harmony
with all beings.
So that's number nine.
Lastly, a Bodhisattva learns to dedicate all merits.
All ten bells, there's merits.
From the first one to the ninth,
everything that you do here,
accumulate great merits.
Whenever we have merits,
we dedicate this to everybody else.
It's like earning interest.
Tenfold, a hundredfold, a thousandfold.
If you keep dedicating the merit,
you will not lose it.
You will not lose anything for yourself.
You will make it bigger and bigger
and keep growing to this huge infinite merit.
So how do we dedicate the merit?
First, we dedicate to all beings.
That means dedicating from the self to others.
Not just for ourselves.
We want to give it to everyone else.
From the self to others.
Help others gain happiness,
gain wisdom,
because of our merit of chanting,
of helping others,
if we dedicate and pray for them,
they will really receive the merit.
So dedicate to all beings.
Second, dedicate to Bodhi.
Bodhi means becoming Buddhahood.
So every merit is a cause.
We want to give this cause
and dedicate it to the effect.
What's the effect?
It's becoming a Buddha.
Reach Buddhahood.
So no matter what kind of goodness
you dedicate this merit to becoming
and reach enlightenment and Buddhahood.
That's our ultimate effect.
Third, we want to dedicate our merit
to true suchness.
This means our own Buddha nature.
That's the true suchness of all things.
Suchness means it is what it is.
It's the true Buddha nature.
That is the only thing that really really exists
in this entire world.
It's your own self nature.
No matter what kind of good deed
you dedicate so you can open up
your own true self nature.
We dedicate all the phenomenon
to inner truth.
Phenomenon is the actual event
or activity or the good deed.
You want to dedicate this actual physical event
to the inner truth
which means our own Buddha nature.
So no matter
what a little thing you do.
Maybe today you just smiled at someone.
This little physical phenomenon
of smiling at someone,
you dedicate this to your own Buddha nature.
It's not just me smiling at someone.
It's me and my Buddha spirit,
my inner true spirit
smiling at this person.
Then this merit will be gazillionfolds
because you understand the truth about life
which is called the inner truth
or we call it true suchness.
That's the essence of bodhisattva
universal worthy.
If everybody vow to become
like worthy bodhisattva
we can all make this world
a better place and everyone
will become a great bodhisattva.
So thank you for listening.