Today we're going to talk about
inner peace.
How do we have true inner peace?
We have inner peace only when we're in line with our true self nature.
We have inner peace by not being affected by the outside circumstances.
In Buddhism we talk about the outside circumstances in terms of these eight winds.
Our goal is to be unmoved by the eight winds.
So what are the eight winds?
They are four pairs, favorable and unfavorable circumstances.
This is a pair, this is a pair, this is a pair, this is a pair.
So there are four pairs that everybody goes through.
But how do you deal with it to have full inner peace?
That's up to you.
The first is when people praise you.
A lot of times you'll get praised, you know, you look beautiful today or you're doing well
in your job.
Your boss, your teacher, your parents or your loved ones give you compliments.
When we receive compliments, we become very happy.
But that is not true happiness because that is just from the outside.
When people compliment you one day, they can give you ridicule the other day.
So it's not safe.
If you depend your happiness only on other people, then you'll never have inner peace.
When you get praised, stay calm like a mountain and don't be moved by it.
Other people do not define you.
You are perfect and complete.
As it is without other people's compliments.
So hear it.
That's good.
And keep going on with your life.
On the opposite, if people ridicule you, people blame you for things that you didn't do.
Your boss criticized you.
They give you negative comments.
What do you do?
Usually it will be upset right away, but that is not a good reaction of a meditator.
A meditator will know that this is just words.
People's words should not affect how you feel.
You are who you are as it is.
Your self-nature, like we said last time, it is naturally complete.
It's always complete.
No matter what other people say about you, you are still complete and perfect.
So know that for a fact and not be disturbed by any ridicule.
The third one is called fame.
Fame is when you have a good reputation.
You are well accepted by this society.
You might be great at your work.
You might be a great artist.
You might be a great singer, or you're famous in a certain area of your life, but if you
depend your happiness on your reputation, you can still be very depressed one day.
If people don't give you the recognition, you can be sad, like a lot of movie stars.
What happens to them?
Kill themselves.
If they don't receive the fame anymore or people look down on them, they can't take
it.
This is all because they don't have the strong meditative mind.
They don't have the inner peace in themselves.
Do not be happy about whatever reputation you have.
That's fine as it is, but you go on being happy and be with your self-nature without
being affected by your status and fame.
The fourth is the opposite.
Sometimes the society does not accept you.
You're a disgrace.
Nowadays we're all on the media, Facebook.
Sometimes you'll get negative comments.
A lot of kids.
Teenagers.
They really affected and all this peer pressure build up.
They want to come to suicide too.
That's all because they don't have the mind to know that they have the self-nature that
is perfect and complete.
You don't need other people's recognition to give you happiness.
Even in disgrace, you still are the perfect self-nature that's perfect and complete and
pure.
The fifth one is prosperity.
We might be prosperous.
You can have a great job, you can buy a big house, fancy car.
Things are going well, we tend to be very happy, but your happiness is dependent on
things going well.
But what if things don't go well?
What if there's decline?
Sickness, get a divorce, bankruptcy, lose your loved ones, everything happens.
Like happened to me.
My eyes went bad when I was in my 20s.
What would you do?
Right?
If you would have prosperity, you would have declines.
Everything is impermanent.
Nothing will last forever.
Know everything is dependent on cause and conditions and not be caught up with what's
happening to you because you have the perfect and complete self-nature.
It does not rise or perish dependent on how good or bad your environment or how great
your life is.
The seventh one is called pleasure.
Sometimes we depend on our happiness.
Our happiness on material goods.
You go traveling, you have great food, you go to the movie, or you have to drink coffee
to be happy.
That's pleasure.
That's fine, but if your happiness is solely dependent on material goods, then that's
very dangerous to you because you'll never be fully satisfied and it can become an addiction.
What if you don't need these things and you can still be happy?
You're always happy without any outside factors.
Isn't that better?
Okay, we call that enlightenment.
When you're truly enlightened, you don't need these material goods and you are perfect
as yourself.
So the last one is pain, the opposite of pleasure.
Sometimes you will be in sickness, sometimes you will be in great pain, a lot of suffering,
or you're materially very lacking, no money or no food.
It's true in a lot of things.
But like we said, our self-nature, everything is generated by your thoughts.
So if you have positive thoughts, you will create positive life and you will not be affected
by this pain.
If you stay positive when you're in pain, the pain will go away.
Know that your mind creates this whole universe.
Living in your true self-nature and not be affected by any positive or negative consequences.
So about a thousand years ago, there is a Chinese poet.
He's really good at meditating.
One day, he was meditating.
He thought he'd reached his full level of enlightenment and great samadhi, great concentration.
And then he wrote a poem.
He said, I bow to the god amongst the gods.
His hair light illuminates the world.
I'm moved by the avian's blow.
Upright, I sit in the purple dome.
Golden lotus.
He's bowing to all the Buddhas.
And because he's never affected by the avian's, he's sitting upright on the lotus flower.
He was so proud of himself, he sent this letter to his best friend, who is a monk.
That's across the river.
So he had someone carry the letter over.
And a few days later, he received the letter back.
And on the letter, it only has one word.
And the word, it says fart.
Which means utter nonsense.
And he became really upset.
He was moved.
So he didn't know he was moved.
He had to ride a boat and went across the river.
Because he felt really insulted that he has to talk to his friend.
And his friend, the monk, knew that he was coming.
His friend wasn't there.
But he rolled on the sand and said, I'm moved by the avian's wind, but blown across the river by a fart.
So that is just to show you, it's not easy to be unaffected by the avian's wind.
You have to be really a great cultivator.
And you really have to go into deep meditation for you to be fully in line with your true self nature.
But you keep meditating, meditating.
One day you will realize that you are really the true self nature that's perfect and pure and complete.
Without being affected by any outside circumstances.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.