Today we are going to talk about the Fundamentals.
In this class, we will use the Shrogamma Sutra to understand the Fundamentals.
There are basically two Fundamentals.
One is the Root of Beginningless Birth and Death.
The Root of Reincarnation is our Deluded Mind.
The second Fundamental is the Root of Beginningless Bodhi Nirvana.
The Root of Nirvana and Enlightenment is our Pure Mind.
So we need to understand the difference between the two.
Now let's look at the verses.
The Root of Beginningless Birth and Death is the Mind that ceases upon conditions
and that you and all living beings now make use of,
taking it to be the Self-Nature.
This Deluded Mind ceases upon conditions.
We are all very much clinging on and attached to external conditions.
For example, if someone praises me, I'm very happy.
If someone criticizes me, I'm very upset.
So that means I'm totally attached to the external conditions.
Every day my emotion is following what's going on externally.
So if I'm attached to external conditions,
then no matter how much good deeds I do,
it is still creating reincarnation for myself.
Buddha asked Ananda,
Why did you become a monk?
Ananda replied very honestly,
Because I saw your 32 characteristics of greatness,
which was supremely wonderful.
The entire body had a shimmering transparency just like that of the crystals.
So is that a good reason to become a monk?
No, because you're basing your spiritual cultivation on someone's appearance,
which is going to change all the time.
It's not reliable.
That's why Buddha said that you and all living beings now make use of.
This you is Ananda.
Buddha is speaking to him.
And we are all like Ananda.
We are using the Deluded Mind as our Self-Nature.
And we actually lost our Self-Nature because of that.
The reason that Buddha expanded the Shakyamuni Sutra
is because Ananda,
he has been learning with Buddha for 12 years,
but he was still being controlled by the spell of the daughter of Mataji.
He almost broke the sexual misconduct precept because of her.
Ananda was the most learned disciple.
Why did this happen?
Because
he didn't find the fundamental of cultivation.
As if he is trying to cook rice with sand.
You will only get hot sand.
You will not get rice.
In order to have rice,
we must have rice as the ingredient.
So if we cultivate very hard,
but we are using our Deluded Mind,
then how can we reach Nirvana?
Now let's look at our Pure Mind.
It is the primal pure substance of beginningless bodhi nirvana.
It is the primal bright essence of consciousness
that can bring forth all conditions.
Because of conditions,
you consider it to be lost.
This Pure Mind is called primal because it is originally there.
It is the mind before we start perceiving the external conditions,
before we start thinking, judging, and discriminating.
That is our Pure Mind.
This Pure Mind actually creates all the external conditions,
but we don't know that.
We are attached to external conditions
and we lost our Pure Mind.
So we unjustly lost our Pure Mind.
It's like we are attached to a little bubble of the ocean
and lost the entire ocean out of ignorance.
So how do we know if we are using our Deluded Mind
or not?
Well, our Pure Mind,
in the Sutra it says,
the Deluded Mind has no substance
apart from the objects,
from the external conditions.
If this thought or this emotion
is coming from stimulants from outside,
that's your Deluded Mind.
If this thought actually has substance
apart from the objects,
apart from all external conditions,
it still exists,
that means it's your Pure Mind.
For example, someone asked
Yin Guang Master,
Have you seen anyone that went to the Pure Land?
How do you know you can go to the Pure Land?
Yin Guang Master answered very firmly,
I don't need to see anyone that went to the Pure Land.
Even if no one in the world chants Amitabha,
I will still chant Amitabha
and go to the Pure Land.
Why is his faith so strong?
Because he knows that chanting Amitabha
is aligning himself
with his Pure Mind.
That's what he's supposed to do.
That's who he is originally.
He is residing in his Pure Mind.
In conclusion,
living beings lost sight
of the original brightness.
Therefore, though they use it
to the end of their days,
they are unaware of it
and without intending to,
they enter the various destinies.
All of us lost sight of our Pure Mind.
Even though we use it
and we have it
to the end of our day,
we are unaware of it.
That's why without intending to,
we enter the six grounds of reincarnation.
We actually don't deserve reincarnation.
We are unjustly wronged
into reincarnation.
This arising,
that arises.
Because of our ignorance
and deluded mind,
we create the twelve links
of dependent origination.
That's why we are reincarnating.
So Buddha tried to explain this
to Ananda with a very simple example.
Buddha raised his golden arm
and bent his five fingers
into a fist.
Then he asked Ananda,
Do you see?
Ananda replied,
Yes, I see.
Buddha asked,
What do you see?
Ananda replied,
I see your golden arm
and the shimmering fist.
Buddha then asked,
What do you see it with?
Ananda replied,
I see it with my mind.
Then Buddha very harshly berated him.
No, that is not your mind.
Ananda was startled
and scared.
He said,
If this is not my mind,
then what is it?
Buddha then firmly replied,
It is your perception of false appearances
based on external objects
that has deluded your true nature
and has caused you
from the beginningless time
to recognize the thief
as your son,
to lose the eternal source
and to undergo the wheels turning.
This deluded mind
is called the perception
of false appearances
based on external objects.
First we have the
external objects.
We call it the five dusts
form, sound,
odor, taste,
and touch.
Because of the external conditions
we create a false appearance,
a shadow image
in our own mind.
We keep thinking about it.
It becomes our perception.
It creates our story.
It creates our life.
That's our life consciousness.
That is not us,
but we think that's us
so we recognize the thief
as our son.
The deluded mind is a thief
that's been stealing from us
but we see it as our true nature,
our son.
That's why we are going through
the wheels turning,
the samsara.
18 years ago,
I started learning Buddhism.
I tried to do a lot of Buddhist work
and to do a lot of ceremony
and learn the Dharma
but deep down inside
I always felt a sense of emptiness
as if something is still missing
in my life
and a sense of insecurity
and I realized why.
Because I've been trying to cook rice
with sand.
I will only get hot sand
because I've been attaching
to the external conditions
to the temple, to the masters,
to all the students
and because everybody is changing
based on everyone's karma
I felt insecure.
Everything is changing.
When I realized that,
I finally felt complete.
I felt like I'm at home.
I'm now safe
and guarded and secure.
So the shragama mantra
is the big
white umbrella.
When we recite the mantra
we are covered by the big
white umbrella because
we are residing in our home
we are safe and we are sheltered.
That's why the shragama
sutra is called
everything ultimately
indestructible.
The samadhi of suchness.
Then you will realize
the deluded mind is actually
the same as the pure mind.
The mind that is dreaming
and sleeping is the mind that's
awakened. We only have
one mind. All you have to do
is to recognize that
you are dreaming. Wake up.
That's all you have to do.
You're naturally dwelling in your
pure mind. It doesn't mean
you won't have external conditions
of obstacles or
afflictions. It just means
whenever things happen
you will not be attached to them.
You will still be safe.
You will be the owner of your
own life. You will not be
affected by the outside world.
Lastly, I would like to share
a story. There was a village
of 500 monkeys.
All 499 monkeys
only have one eye.
Only one has
two eyes. So everybody
laughed and poked fun at him.
So he grew up very depressed
and had very low self-esteem.
Until one day he
had the courage to go outside
the village. Once outside
he saw other monkeys and
much to his surprise all the other
monkeys have two eyes.
Then he realized I'm actually
normal. After that
he lived happily ever after.
So we are all
supposed to have two eyes
which means we are all supposed to be
dwelling in our pure
mind. That's who we
supposed to be. When we recite
the name Amitabha
we need to have the right
fundamental, our pure
mind. So before we start any
cultivation, find
our home, find our
pure mind. If we chant
Amitabha's name or cultivate
for the rest of our life
but using the deluded mind
then that will still be creating
reincarnation for
ourselves. So ponder
upon this deeply.
That's the class for today. Thank
you for listening. Amitabha.