Today we are going to talk about 16 characteristics of the Four Noble Truths.
How do we meditate on the Four Noble Truths?
There are actually 4 characteristics under each Noble Truth for a total of 16.
As we meditate on these 16 characteristics, we can become enlightened.
The first two Noble Truths are suffering and the causes of suffering.
That's describing the difficult lives of mundane people in samsara.
Then we have cessation of suffering and the path to end suffering.
That's describing the happy lives of saints in nirvana.
We can all reach the cessation of suffering and be free from suffering.
Now let's look at suffering, the first Noble Truth.
The first characteristic of suffering is impermanence.
Everything arises due to causes and conditions that are forever changing.
Nothing remains the same even for a single moment.
But we expect permanence.
That's why impermanence is such a suffering.
For the past week, so many people got COVID.
It's unprecedented.
We really feel that impermanence is about life.
In the Sutra of 42 Chapters, Buddha asked the Buddha,
How do you measure the length of a man's life?
The monk replied, Five days.
Buddha said, You do not understand the way.
Then Buddha asked another monk,
How do you measure the length of a man's life?
The monk answered, By the time that passes during a meal.
Buddha said, You do not understand the way.
Buddha asked a third time.
This time, a monk replied, By the breath.
Buddha said, Very well, you know the way.
So our life is impermanent.
It's in between breath.
One breath that doesn't come, it's dead.
And it's next lifetime.
So understanding impermanence will allow us to accept it.
Every moment that we're living,
we will be diligent and mindful all the time,
and not live in vain.
Now let's look at the second characteristic, which is suffering.
There are three kinds of suffering.
The first suffering is called suffering of suffering.
This is the blatant suffering,
such as sickness.
The second suffering is suffering of changes.
When the happiness decay, we lose the happiness.
It becomes a big suffering.
The third suffering is all-pervasive suffering.
That's the moment-to-moment impermanence of our mind.
Our mind has non-stop chattering,
and it has anxiety and insecurity in the background of our mind.
That is called all-pervasive suffering.
We might be able to recognize the first suffering,
or even the second suffering,
but the all-pervasive suffering is really hard to recognize.
When we really recognize our suffering,
that's the door to enlightenment.
So suffering is really our teacher.
Number three, emptiness.
Our biggest delusion is not understanding impermanence,
thinking there is a permanent, independent, controlling self.
And all our suffering comes from the attachment to the self,
the five aggregates.
But the truth is that the five aggregates are just a combination
of physical and mental phenomena that's forever changing.
Because all phenomena are just creations of our own alaya consciousness.
So it's like a dream, a mirage, a bubble, and a flash of lightning.
That's why we call emptiness, emptiness of the self.
If we understand this,
we will remove the ego-centered life experience
and be liberated from the presence of selfishness,
our true suffering.
Number four is non-self.
The five aggregates is condition arising,
therefore there is not intrinsic essence.
For example, if I have really low self-esteem
because growing up the condition is I have always been criticized,
or I have really high self-esteem
because growing up the condition is I have always been praised,
both the high self-esteem and the low self-esteem,
that's because of our ego.
We think there is a self that's independent from others.
We erect walls and we build turfs and territories for ourselves.
When we understand non-self,
it's realizing that the self and the others are not two.
When the line that divides up the self and the other is erased,
then there's no longer any conflict.
There's no longer anything to fear or gain for the self.
So that is non-self.
When we have profound insight into these four characteristics,
that's when we understand our suffering.
Number two, causes of suffering.
The first characteristic is causes.
The fundamental causes of our suffering
is our attachment to the self,
which gives rise to mental afflictions, karmic deeds,
and produces suffering.
For example, our mental afflictions of greed, anger, and ignorance
can produce karmic deeds such as killing, stealing, and sexual misconduct,
which produce the hell realm, the hungry ghost realm, and the animal realm.
This is all because of causation.
And it also causes strong production,
our mental afflictions,
and karmic deeds
can immediately produce intense pain,
just like if we touch an open wound on the body,
it really hurts.
So there's no god punishing us,
or bad luck,
or the wrongdoing of others.
It's all the karmic seeds in our laya consciousness
that's manifesting the sufferings.
That's why it's also called the origin,
like crops growing from a field.
All suffering originates
from our mental afflictions and karmic deeds.
The only way to reduce our suffering
is to abandon our evil deeds
and mental afflictions
and cultivate goodness.
According to Buddha,
anytime we suffer misfortune,
it's like being struck by an arrow.
Oftentimes, we create the second arrow
by reacting negatively to the bad event.
Then we react again to that negative emotion.
The third, fourth, fifth arrow
starts raining down on us.
So instead of pulling out the first arrow,
we actually create more arrows for ourselves.
By understanding the origins of our suffering,
we can stop shooting arrows at ourselves.
Number four is conditioned.
Our mental afflictions and karmic deeds
are both the main causes
and the supporting conditions for our suffering.
Just like crops,
it needs supporting conditions
such as water and fertilizer
in order for it to continue to grow.
If we do not want the crop of suffering,
we need to change our conditions
from mental afflictions
to wisdom of emptiness.
So that's the causes.
The third noble truth,
cessation of suffering.
The first characteristic
is cessation.
We want to stop all our mental afflictions.
That's when we have true happiness
we call nirvana.
There was a boy
who renounced the luxuries of life
went up to the snow-covered mountain
and indulged into deep meditation.
While meditating one day,
he heard a voice
in which a man was reciting the verse,
All is changeable.
Nothing is constant.
This is the law of birth and death.
Hearing the voice,
the boy opened his eyes
and saw a ferocious-looking demon.
The boy asked him
to complete the verse
that was only partially recited.
But the demon said,
I'm too hungry to recite.
The boy then readily offered himself
to be sacrificed as his food
if the demon agreed
to recite the remaining verse.
Then the demon recited,
Escaping the maelstrom of birth and death.
One attains the joy of nirvana.
Hearing the complete verse,
the boy was overjoyed
as he had accomplished
the true meaning of his life.
He then recited and memorized the verse,
engraved it on stones,
cliffs, and trees.
Then to keep his promise,
he climbed a tall tree,
took a plunge into the demon's mouth.
Then the demon turned into Lord Chakra,
the guardian of heaven,
and stopped the boy from falling.
Because he was only testing him
of his devotion and dedication to the Dharma.
Of course, this boy is Shakyamuni Buddha.
He was willing to sacrifice his life
for the Dharma, for enlightenment.
This verse is talking about
what's going on here,
the Four Noble Truths.
Everything is changeable.
That's talking about impermanence and emptiness.
We can escape the maelstrom of life and death.
That's when we have cessation of suffering.
When you have the non-self,
like the boy who was willing
to sacrifice himself for the Dharma,
you will reach enlightenment
and become a true bodhisattva.
The second characteristic is
pacification.
We have true peace
when we have no more mental afflictions.
When we are greedy for worldly happiness,
we are not at peace.
When we are angry at worldly issues,
at worldly events,
we are also not at peace.
So anytime we have mental afflictions,
we are burning with restlessness.
So to have true peace
is when we have no more afflictive emotions.
Number three is being superb.
We are being superb
when we are non-self.
And that's when we have real compassion
and balanced wisdom.
We are perfectly pure and complete.
This is actually
our natural state,
our Buddha nature,
according to the Mahayana teaching.
So our natural state
is not to have any afflictions.
We are supposed to be in nirvana.
We are supposed to be superb.
Number four is definite emergence.
That's the true stopping of samsara.
This is at least at the stage
of the first level of our headship.
When the delusion of the view of self
is completely eradicated,
that's when we guarantee to be liberated
from the bondage of samsara.
Now let's look at the path to end suffering.
Number one is path.
Path is the means which we progress,
leading us to cessation,
like a road that takes us
to the desired destination.
The Buddha's path will not be apart
from precept, concentration, and wisdom.
For example,
when we recite the name Amitabha,
it is a true precept.
When we refrain ourselves
from speaking bad words,
having bad thoughts,
doing bad deeds,
it is also training us for concentration.
When we keep repeating the Buddha's name,
we are training our deep concentration.
And it's also wisdom.
The name itself means non-self.
That's why Amitabha is called
infinite light and infinite wisdom.
Chanting Amitabha
is a perfect path to nirvana.
Number two is awareness.
We should be mindful
of the depth of our problem,
which is suffering,
and the means to escape,
which is the path to end suffering.
When you are really aware,
you will not look at the world
from the perspective of the small self again.
You will see everything
as cause and condition
and as emptiness.
Number three is achievement.
We want to have this resultant state,
achieve what Buddha achieved.
Buddha cultivated wisdom and merits.
That's why he achieved liberation.
Number four is deliverance.
To be liberated from the bondage
of conditioned existence.
As you can see,
all 16 of these,
they work together hand in hand
and are interrelated.
For example,
if you want to be aware,
you need to contemplate
on impermanence and emptiness.
If you want to have pacification,
you need to know the causes and the origins,
which is our own mental afflictions.
This is all aligning ourselves
with the Pure Land Buddhism.
Renounce the Saha world of suffering
and to joyously seeking the Pure Land
that is nirvana.
So have unwavered understanding
of the Four Noble Truths.
Take refuge in it.
This is not a religious faith
or a text for us to study.
This is really our life right now.
Shakyamuni Buddha,
he wanted to find a way
to end the suffering of birth,
aging, sickness and death.
This is what he realized.
This is the perfect time
for all of us to understand
our suffering and the Four Noble Truths
and have a breakthrough
in our cultivation.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.