The
English
Language
of
the
world
is
also
the
language
of
the
world.
In
this
language
of
the
world
is
the
language
of
the
world.
So
we are going to talk about the Four Noble Truths. What do we mean by noble? Noble means
we can actually get back to our Buddha nature. Buddha, when he was a prince, he left the
kingdom. He wants to know why there is death. How come we have to suffer? Even as a prince,
he has to go through life and death and illness. He's like, I don't want to go through this.
Is there any way to end suffering? So he really wants to find out how do we end suffering.
So he left the kingdom and sat in the woods and tried to figure it out. At the time, there
were a lot of different religions helping him go into meditation. But he found out that's
not the answer. Nobody told him why there is suffering. Then for six years, he tried
to starve himself. Every day, he ate one grain of sesame, a little sesame.
So every day, he ate one grain. He did that for six years. And then every day, he just
sat and meditated, trying to figure out what is the truth about life. One day, when he
was 30 years old, he sat under the Bodhi tree. He came to full realization. Oh, this is the
truth about life. After he realized, oh, this is the truth about life, he started teaching.
He passed away when he was 80. So he taught for 49 to 50 years. Then he taught, how do
we get back to our true Buddha nature? When he first started teaching, this is what he
taught. For 49 years, that's what he taught. Mainly, that's what he taught. So that's the
most important Dharma wheel in Buddhism. The Four Noble Truths, the truth about our lives.
This is what you need to contemplate in order for you to reach your enlightenment. The first
one and the second one.
The first one is a group. The third and the fourth is a different group. We're trying
to go from here to here. That's the purpose. We're going from here to here. And Buddha
is very smart. He gives us the result first, then the cause. The result first, then the
cause. He doesn't give us the cause and then the result. To let us know how we are right
now, what's the cause of it, just like someone is sick.
What's the cause of the sickness? How does he cure himself? What kind of medicine does
he take? So that's the Four Noble Truths.
The first one is what is our sickness right now? It's called suffering. You have to realize
that we live in the world of suffering. There are three kinds of suffering. The first one
is ordinary suffering.
means the suffering that we can all feel. For example, someone hit you, it hurts. That's
ordinary. You know that it's pain, that it's suffering. Or you get sick, that's ordinary
suffering. A dog would know, a cat would know, everybody would know. So that's not really
a truth or a wisdom, right? But the second kind of suffering is harder to realize. It's
called the suffering of changes. Good things will become suffering. If you ate a dumpling,
you really like dumpling. You ate one, it tastes very good. If you ate a hundred, will
you still be happy? No. Because why? Ate too much. Happiness became suffering. That's
called suffering of changes.
So you have to realize every happiness eventually will become suffering. So that's the second
truth about suffering. Every enjoyment you're having right now, one day it will become bad
because it will not last. Everything is impermanent. Impermanence is a top teaching of Buddhism.
So we'll talk about that later. So that's the suffering of changes. The third kind is
called pervasive happiness.
Pervasive means contamination of our body and mind. Do you guys remember the very first
class? We talked about the five skandhas. The first one is our form, which is our body.
The second one is our feelings. We're made of our feelings. We feel hot or cold or happy
or sad, pleasure, displeasure. So that's the second one. The third one is our perception,
how we perceive things. That makes up what we think we are. And the fourth one is our
mental formation. Perception going into a deeper level, it becomes a very attached thought.
It's called mental formation. The last one is your consciousness. That makes up your
body and your mind. Do you realize your five skandhas, they're pervasive. They're always
moving.
Always changing. Is there a moment that you stop your mind? No. It's really hard to stop
our mind. So that's a kind of suffering. If you don't meditate, you don't understand how
sad it is that we're always having wandering thoughts. It's really a suffering. Like to
me, it's a big suffering. So that's called pervasive suffering. Not a lot of people get
the second or the third suffering.
Everybody only knows the ordinary suffering. So now you need to know all three. What I
mean, know, you need to be fully aware of it, fully conscious of it, fully accept it
and deal with it. It takes a very strong person to know your own suffering and you can see
everybody when everybody is suffering. That's the first truth. You have to know it wholeheartedly
what suffering is.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
If you don't know it, you don't know how to end it. You have to know it in order to end
it.
The second noble truth is cause of suffering. Do you know why we keep having sufferings?
Why? The main cause is actually because of our own ego, our selfishness. If there's not
a concept of self, when someone hit me, would I be okay?
Would I be upset? No. If I don't exist, then it doesn't hurt, right? It doesn't really
affect me.
So the main problem is the idea of the ego, of the self, that we take on this identity.
When we're born, people taught us, you know, your name is this and that, and this is who
you are and everything about you. Okay, we take on this identity and then when anybody
hurts us, we get upset. This is the cause of why all the suffering comes in. This is
our ego.
So mainly there are three roots or causes of our ego. The first one is greed. We always
want more because there's the idea of self. Because of me, I want more money, I want more
fame, I want more food, I want more sleep, or I want more relationships because we're
always wanting more.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . .
The fact that you want more is why there's suffering. Okay. If you don't want more , there's
no suffering. My favorite thing is to stay in the ego
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
So that's the first cause.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
you're greedy if you don't get what you want it becomes anger okay anything that you want
you don't get you become angry okay so this two is uh one after another okay and the third one
is ignorance not understanding that there's no self that's our main ignorance we think
we should be selfish because there's real me my car my mom my house my everything
but that's not me i am the universal power i'm the buddha nature you are actually the big ocean
but you take on this little bubble as yourself that's our main ignorance we don't understand
the truth about our lives that's why we have this kind of result because of the cause we have this
result we're trying to get out of it we're trying to get out of these two and go here what's the
result that we want to get to cessation of suffering or the ending of suffering suffering
can end
once and for all nirvana or you can call it enlightenment
or you can call it the let go of the ego right there's no ego there's no suffering
so nirvana is what it's not a place it's not a place you go to it's when you let go of your own
ego then you reach there you don't really really have to meditate to reach there and you don't have
all these supernatural powers for you to reach nirvana
it's just for you to get this wisdom to let go of this ego that's all okay that's what buddha
realized we're trying to get to this place where there's no greed anger ignorance that's our
purpose that's our goal then you would be ultimately happy absolute happiness
you will be ultimately happy
it's not really duality of happiness
like a happy or good or both.
that's just three innumerable reasons because we see one of sun.
bad it's just an absolute happiness how do we get here how do we get here we have to cultivate the
fourth one the path to end suffering there is a way the path means a method what kind of method
do we use to reach nirvana there are three methods that we use in buddhism the first one is precepts
the second one is concentration the third one is wisdom that's the only three things we try to
cultivate in buddhism first we follow precepts precepts are rules that buddha said for his
disciples you follow these rules and you will have less suffering what are the rules okay there are
five basic rules the first one is
nirvana
the second one is no killing
if you don't kill other beings you won't have people killing you you won't have sickness
sickness comes from your karma from killing others that's why we try to be vegetarian
okay so first precept is no killing the second precept is no stealing
that includes taxes or anything okay so that is anything it's not just oh i go steal someone's stuff
you know no that includes lying on the taxes there's a sale in the mall every family gets one
three things and you have all your five families go there and get five that's
That's the form of stealing. It can be very, very small. It can be very, very big. But it has karma.
And it all comes back to you in the form of suffering, sooner or later.
So Buddha said you have to follow this precept for you to be in happiness without any suffering.
It's to protect us. It's not to limit us from doing things. It's to protect us.
The third one is no sexual misconduct.
When you're married, you don't go outside and have other relationships.
It's not proper, but it can be very, very small, too.
For example, you look at someone you like and you start flirting. Does that count? It does.
Even if you didn't do anything, you start to just have more.
Talks. That is also a form of sexual misconduct.
So the fourth one is no lying.
When you say things that are exaggeration.
You know, like people that sell cars.
They say everything is a great car or whatever.
So that is still kind of lying.
The fifth is no alcohol.
Because when you drink, when you drink, it's not alcohol itself that is a sin.
Because when you're intoxicated, you're more likely to kill, to steal, to have sexual misconduct and to lie.
That's why he made this rule to prevent from doing the first four.
So first, hold precepts.
Then you're more likely to go into deep concentration.
If I have a lot of defilements and I have a lot of these bad karmas,
when I sit there, I cannot go into deep concentration.
Because you have a lot of wandering thoughts.
And not just wandering thoughts, you have a lot of bad thoughts.
Okay, so you guys are all very good people, you know, already.
For you to be able to sit here.
To go into deep concentration, first you gotta withhold precepts.
Then you can go into samadhi or deep concentration.
That's what we're doing right now.
When we're trying to meditate for hours or hours, you know, and persistent at it.
This is from persistency.
You keep doing it, you'll be good at it.
Practice makes perfect.
You know, that's what concentration is, okay?
So the last one is wisdom.
What kind of wisdom?
The true wisdom is to understand that there's no self.
That's real wisdom.
When you can go past yourself,
when someone is rude to you,
you can actually tell yourself,
there's not a self that I'm being offended to.
If there's not self.
Who is being offended?
Nobody.
Okay, so it takes a great person with great wisdom
to be able to let go of the self.
When you reach this wisdom, or we call enlightenment,
you will reach nirvana.
This is what we call nirvana.
And this is what Buddha did.
That's what he did.
That's what he accomplished in his life.
And that's what he tried to teach us for 49 years.
He was in India.
He was a real person, a real prince,
2,600 years ago.
And his dharma is still with us today
because he's our teacher.
We can all go back to our true Buddha nature
if we can just start cultivating,
let go of the self,
and soon enough we will reach nirvana.
Everybody can get here,
but you have to cultivate.
Soon enough we will be away from all kinds of suffering
and all kinds of greed, anger, ignorance,
and all the defilements.
That's what we're trying to do.
Thank you very much for listening.
That's it for today.
Goodbye.