Today we are going to talk about Path to Enlightenment.
Shakyamuni Buddha became enlightened by understanding the Four Noble Truths.
Today we are going to delve deep into Four Noble Truths to understand what is enlightenment.
The first one is suffering.
Right now we are suffering because we are in samsara, which means reincarnation.
As long as we are reincarnating, we are under tremendous suffering.
What is the cause of our suffering?
That's the second Noble Truth.
The cause of our suffering is our afflictions.
Because we have afflictions, that's why we are reincarnating.
If we don't have afflictions, then we will be out of samsara.
So the key is to get rid of our afflictions.
How do we do that?
We need to practice the path to end suffering.
We call it Bodhi.
Bodhi means way to enlightenment.
Usually it's the three aspects of learning.
Precepts, concentration and wisdom.
We practice these three things that are Bodhi so we can reach cessation of suffering.
That's what we call Nirvana.
Nirvana is not death.
It means when we have no more afflictions.
When we have no more self, no more afflictions, that is the ultimate happiness.
I further summarize these four.
Samsara means our five aggregates.
Our body and mind.
We are suffering right now because we have the five aggregates.
Our form, which is our body.
Our feelings, perception, mental formation and consciousness.
The first one is our body.
The next four is our mind.
So body and mind.
We are attached to our body and mind.
We think that is me.
We have a perception of the self.
That is why we are in Samsara.
Buddha wants us to contemplate on the four mindfulness about the five aggregates.
Our body, our form is impure.
Every day trying to decorate this body and make it healthy and perfect or have sexual desires about other people's body.
If we can see how impure everyone's body is, you will love your body so much and we will get rid of the self.
Then our feelings.
We have to contemplate that it is only suffering.
We think we can gain happiness when our worldly desires are fulfilled.
For example, we have great food.
We go traveling, have great fun.
We think this feeling is happiness.
But any happiness we feel right now eventually is suffering.
Because when the happiness subsides, it always becomes suffering.
There is no way you can be out of suffering as long as you have a self.
So we have to contemplate.
Feelings will always end up as suffering as long as we are in Samsara.
Our perception and our mental formation, that is our mind.
We have to know our mind is impermanent.
Right now, we believe this mind of ours is permanent.
My opinion, my thoughts, my views, this is the real me.
But there is no me.
Your thoughts are constantly changing.
Your emotions from day and night are completely different all the time.
How can you believe there is a permanent self?
It's not stable.
It's always changing due to cause and conditions and effects.
So the mind is impermanent.
Lastly, the consciousness.
The whole world, we call it Dharma, which means everything.
It is non-self.
We think everything has eternal, independent, controlling self,
which is a false view.
When we believe our body is clean, our feeling is happy,
our mind is permanent, our consciousness is self,
that is what we call upside-down view, false views.
So we need to contemplate on the fact that it's impure, suffering,
impermanent, and non-self.
So how do we do that?
First, we need to understand what is our afflictions.
Let's look at the second noble truth.
What is our afflictions?
Basically, it's our wrong views and wrong thoughts.
If you can get rid of our wrong views and wrong thoughts,
you have no more afflictions.
Then it's Nirvana.
There are five basic wrong views.
The first one is the view of the self.
We believe the body is me.
That is the biggest wrong view
because we think this is me and we are separate from others.
That's why we dislike others.
We are selfish.
We protect our body, protect this image
because we have a strong sense of self.
So we have to see that we have the wrong view of the self.
The second one is the one-sided view.
One-sided means either we believe in emptiness
or we believe in existence.
Some people believe in emptiness,
which means when we die, it's like a candle that's blown out.
That's all.
That is people that dwell on emptiness.
Some people dwell on existence.
They believe human will be human next lifetime
and human next lifetime.
Forever you'll be human.
That is people that believe in existence.
But both of these views are incorrect.
They are only one-sided.
It's not the middle way.
The middle way is not emptiness or existence.
It's this balance of emptiness and existence.
Number three, some people hold unbeneficial precepts.
For example, there are people that hold dog precepts or cow precepts.
They will behave like a cow or a dog
because they saw in their meditation
a cow or a dog went to heaven.
They don't know what's the right cause.
They believe it's because they act like a dog or a cow.
So they will start eating grass
or they will bark like a dog their whole life.
That's the precept they hold.
But that is totally the wrong cause to enlightenment.
They don't know what's the real precept.
They think that's the way to enlightenment.
The fourth wrong view is our attachment to views.
This is the wrong precepts.
Not knowing the right cause.
Wrong attachment to views is not knowing the correct effect or retribution.
Some people they have not reached enlightenment.
But they believe because they have deep meditation
they are arhat, which is their attachment to the wrong views.
Thinking their meditation is already enlightenment.
It's already arhatship.
The fifth one is deviant views.
Evil views.
Doing bad deeds.
Is good.
So you have the wrong views.
Because we have the view of the self,
that's why we have the next four.
Because of this wrong view,
we also have wrong thoughts.
The five primary afflictions.
We are greedy because we are selfish.
We always want to gain for ourselves.
It can be money.
It can be relationship.
It can be fame.
Food or sleep.
Greedy for these five desires.
We are very angry when we don't get our desires met.
We resent the obstacles from getting what we want.
When things don't go our way, we are upset.
That's our anger.
We are also very ignorant.
The fact that we think we have a self that's separate from others.
That's our biggest ignorance.
We don't understand there is no self.
Then we have arrogance.
We think we are superior than others.
It can be our appearance, wealth, or education.
You think you are so much higher than others
because we have a strong self.
Lastly, we have doubt.
We doubt ourselves.
We don't think enlightenment is possible.
We doubt the Dharma.
We don't believe practicing the Dharma will help us get into enlightenment.
And we doubt our teacher.
We think the teacher, they are not cultivating well.
I don't need to listen to the teacher.
We doubt these three things.
That's why we cannot succeed in our cultivation.
Because we have wrong views and we have wrong thoughts.
That's why we are in samsara.
And our five aggregates are suffering.
So what do we do now as a Buddhist?
What can we do to leave the suffering?
To get rid of our reincarnation?
Buddha says we need to practice.
Both Mahayana and Dravata,
we practice the Eightfold Path.
The only right path.
You can get rid of your afflictions.
First is right view.
Instead of wrong views,
you must build up right views.
How do we build up right views?
You need to understand the Four Noble Truths.
That is the right view.
If you don't understand why you are suffering,
how you can get out of suffering,
how are you supposed to solve any problem
or become enlightened?
So first, you have to understand the Four Noble Truths.
And you gotta get rid of the idea of the self.
So first, we must have right view.
Then, we must have right intentions.
Your thoughts.
You must get rid of your wrong thoughts.
Right intentions is without greed.
No greed, no anger, no ignorance.
That's our right thoughts, right intentions.
We have to get rid of our wrong speech.
For example, no lying,
no foul language, no gossiping,
and no slandering of others.
We must speak right speech.
We also have right action.
No killing, no stealing,
no sexual misconduct.
So with our mind, our mouth, our body,
we have to act accordingly.
If your body, mind, and speech are not proper,
how are you going to become enlightened?
Five, right livelihood.
You need to have a right job,
right career.
You cannot be selling drugs,
selling your body.
You cannot be doing unlawful things.
We do not want to hurt any living being.
Because we know we are all reincarnating together.
How can you hurt other beings?
So have the right way of living.
So you are not accumulating negative karma by your job.
Six, we must have right effort.
You need to be diligent in your practice,
in getting rid of afflictions.
Our only job is to awaken to our true nature
and to get rid of our wrong views and wrong thoughts.
Because that's the only way to get rid of the cause of suffering.
So put our mind and all our power into our practice.
Get rid of our evil and cultivate goodness.
Seven, right mindfulness.
Basically, these four.
Be mindful.
The body is impure.
Feelings is suffering.
Mind is impermanent.
All dharmas are non-self.
Lastly, right concentration.
Concentration is when you are mindful all the time.
You go into a deep meditation in terms of your wisdom
in your four mindfulness.
You can hold with the four mindfulness all the time.
Then you are totally focused in the dharma.
So we need to practice the Eightfold Path
in order to reach the cessation of suffering.
Nobody wants suffering.
Everyone wants to be happy.
Wants to reach nirvana.
Wants to see our true nature.
The suchness, the Buddha nature.
We need to practice these in order to get here.
We should know from all the Mahayana Buddhism
is telling us one important truth
which is the suchness, the nirvana
is already here.
Right here and right now.
In your one mind.
Because you are originally enlightened.
You don't need to practice so hard.
It's already within you.
You have the Buddha nature already.
So you will realize the four virtues of nirvana
which are permanence, bliss, self and purity.
They are the opposite of the four mindfulness.
Why is that?
Because before we have the upside down views.
Right now these are the truth.
They are aligned with their suchness.
You have the Buddha nature that is permanent.
Your Buddha nature is the same.
No matter which realm you are in.
And we have full blissfulness.
Bliss is our true nature.
We are always happy.
It's not coming from greed for worldly things.
It's from our internal happiness.
Our innate nature.
We are supposed to be happy all the time.
We have the self.
It's not the self we perceive as the five aggregates.
It's already the true suchness.
Our Buddha self.
That's our higher self.
The true self.
Lastly,
Self is always pure.
It's perfectly pure which means no afflictions.
All our afflictions are only illusion.
They don't really exist.
You can completely be awakened out of your afflictions
in one minute, in one instant.
Because you realize who you really are.
The true suchness.
In Mahayana Buddhism,
we know samsara is nirvana.
Affliction is bodhi.
There's no difference between samsara or nirvana.
There's no difference between affliction or bodhi.
Why?
Because we already have the Buddha nature.
As long as you let go of your attachment to all the worldly forms,
understand everything is only illusion,
happening in a dream,
let go of the self,
you are already your true Buddha nature.
Tragama Sutra.
It says,
When madness ceases, bodhi appears.
What is the madness?
The madness is our deluded mind having these illusions.
It sees this illusional self.
And go back to our true nature.
Then the bodhi naturally appears.
You are just who you are already.
The path to enlightenment
is to understand the truth of the world,
which is the Four Noble Truths.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.