Today we are going to talk about Tien Tai and Pure Land.
The Knight Patriarch of Pure Land Buddhism, Master Ou Yi, wrote a commentary on the Amitabha
Sutra using Tien Tai Buddhism to explain Pure Land Buddhism.
We will discuss the relationship between Tien Tai and Pure Land.
The Tien Tai Buddhism was founded by Master Zhi Yi based on this verse from Bodhisattva
Nagarjuna.
It says, For dharmas arising from conditions, I affirm that they are empty.
They are conventional.
But yet indicate the meaning of the middle way.
All dharmas arise from conditions arising, cause and effect, thus the basis for everything
in this universe, including our body, including our family, including everything that we see
in this world.
They are all conditioned, means they are forever changing.
It's impermanent.
Therefore, I affirm that they are empty.
Because they are changing, there is not an intrinsic nature in any of the conditioned
dharma.
We should not be attached to anything, including the idea of the self, or anything that appears
in our lives in this world.
They are all illusory appearance based on the cause and conditions.
Everything cannot stand alone by itself.
Everything can only exist by itself.
Everything is interdependent and everything is forever changing.
Everything is impermanent.
We call it empty.
We often say to surpass passion and depart from discrimination.
That's how we actually let go of the attachment to the self and attachment to all dharmas.
So emptiness is the basis of enlightenment.
They are conventional.
It means even though everything is empty, they do have a temporary provincial existence.
We still live on this earth.
We must use this life to be a true bodhisattva, give everybody the best we got, and be full
of love, compassion, kindness, and joy.
Spread our love to all sentient beings.
That is a true bodhisattva.
Focus on what's in the conventional world without any attachment to the world, but yet
indicate the meaning of the middle way.
Middle means we are balanced between the ultimate truth and the conventional truth.
That's our true Buddha nature, the basis of all our cultivation.
And that is the basis of Tantide Buddhism.
From these four lines,
Master Zhi Yi categorized all Buddha's teachings into four doctrines of conversion.
The first teaching is called the Tripitaka teaching.
This is the Theravada Buddhism.
Their concept is focused on all conditioned arisings, such as the Four Noble Truths and
the Twelve Links of Dependent Origination.
They believe everything is really arising.
Really ceasing, this life and death, this samsara, this nirvana, it's really happening.
That's why they try very hard to sever from the cycle of life and birth.
This is called the Rising and Ceasing Four Noble Truths.
The Four Noble Truths are suffering, cause of suffering, cessation of suffering, way
to end suffering.
These are the Four Noble Truths.
The Four Noble Truths are suffering, cause of suffering, cessation of suffering, way
to end suffering.
The Four Noble Truths are suffering, cause of suffering, cessation of suffering, way to
end suffering.
These are the Four Noble Truths taught by Buddha.
For the Theravada Buddha, all things are conditioned rising and conditioned ceasing.
To them, it's really happening.
In reality, there is samsara, there is nirvana.
So that's what they base their meditation on, to end the suffering of samsara.
The second teaching is called Common Teaching.
Common Teaching is the teaching of the Three Wisdoms.
They are very common to Theravada and Common to Mahayana Bodhisattvas.
So there's higher level of emptiness.
We understand everything, conditioned arising.
They are not really rising or ceasing.
Therefore Four Noble Truths are called Non-Arising Four Noble Truths.
This is a higher level of emptiness.
There is nothing really rising.
or ceasing. Everything does not exist by itself, nor by other causes, nor jointly with other
causes, nor without causes. Thus, it is known to be non-existent. There are four deductive
reasonings here. We should think everything is not really arising or ceasing at all. For
example, if we have anger, we should use this deductive reasoning. First, where does anger
come from? Is this anger arising by itself? If it is, then we should be angry all the
time. So that can be right. Number two, is it because of his words or other people's
words that make you angry? If that is the case, then everything is not really arising
at all. So that can be right. Number two, is it because of his words or other people's
at all. So that can be right. Number three, is it causes joined together that make you
angry right now? No, because two things cannot be combined to create. Therefore, it can be
right either. Number four, is it without a cause? You just become angry for no reason.
That can be it either. Conclusion, thus, it is not a cause, it is a result. So that can
it is known to be non-existent. This anger never arise, never cease. You should just
let it go. It never happened and it doesn't affect your Buddha nature at all. This is
how we should contemplate all the time in order to have this Prajna of emptiness.
The third teaching is called the Distinctive Teaching. This is tailored for Bodhisattvas.
Not only do they know emptiness and let go of their attachment, they also focus on what's
going on in the world. They understand the immeasurable Four Noble Truths. The Ten Dharma
Realms have different sufferings. Everyone is an incarnation, their immeasurable number
is one. Everyone is an incarnation, their immeasurable number is one. Everyone is an
immeasurable number is one. Everyone is an incarnation, their immeasurable number is
one. Everyone is an incarnation, their immeasurable number is one. Who cares about what happens
to any one others chew and drink. They don't care about anyата, that is immeasurable.
Bodhisattvas know that minimal consumer Auto-Saltra also understands toma all sufferings,
is the
ultimate convinced progress.
Rub трав
Buddhism is all about the complete round teaching. It's all inclusive teaching.
Nothing really matters anymore. Everything that's going on in the world
is already your Buddha nature. Samsara is your Buddha nature. Nirvana is your Buddha
nature. Nothing is of any difference. Sentient beings and Buddha are the same.
It's called the non-doing for noble truth. There's nothing for you to do.
There's no suffering to depart from. There's no Nirvana to gain. It's already
your Buddha nature. It's just right here and right now in your one true mind. This
is our true suchness. This is all that matters. So we call it one color, one
smell. Everything is the middle.
Any smell, any color, all dharmas in the world is already the Buddha.
Because your mind is the Buddha. You don't have to try so hard to be out of
suffering. You are already out of suffering because you are the Buddha. So
that's the ten type teaching based on the Lotus Sutra. Because of these four
types of teaching, we have the four Pure Lands of
Buddha.
the Amitabha's Western Pure Land. We are studying Pure Land Buddhism where we chant
Amitabha Buddha's name, hoping to go to his world of ultimate bliss. Every Buddha's
land has four different types of lands based on the four teachings. The first land is Together
Dwelling Pure Land, where the ordinary beings and saints live together because we have not
ended our afflictions yet. That's why we dwell in this land. So this is about rising and
seizing Four Noble Truth. When we are still in the samsara, so by chanting the name Amitabha,
even if we haven't ended our afflictions, we can still go to this land.
where the saints and the ordinary beings live together because of our Buddha nature.
We will end reincarnation forever and we will never retrogress just by chanting the name Amitabha.
The second land is the land of expedient liberation.
That's the art hats, they already severed the idea of the self
and they are learning the common teaching to gain higher wisdom of emptiness.
They can go further to the third land, the land of real reward.
All the enlightened Bodhisattvas they live in this land of real reward.
It's beautiful land full of all the goodness, merit.
They are in this conventional world, trying to save sentient beings.
The last land is the land of meditation.
The second land is called what we call Sun ребята.
Sun.
land of eternal still light. This land is where Amitabha resides. In this land, there's
actually no form, nothing at all. It's just the Buddha nature. We call it eternal because
the Buddha nature never ends, never dies, never moves, and it's still without any wandering
thoughts, without any chaos, and it's full of light, bright, illuminating, and shiny.
That's what our Buddha nature is like. So this is where all Buddhas reside. So if you
can understand these four types of teaching based on the Tantide Buddhism, you will know
which land you will be going to. What is so special about Amitabha's Pure Land? That's
different from Amitabha's Pure Land. That's different from Amitabha's Pure Land. That's
different from Amitabha's Pure Land. That's really misshapen for me. What I don't like
about other Buddhas' land is that this together dwelling Pure Land in Amitabha's Pure Land.
They are horizontal with the upper lands. We all dwell together in Amitabha's Western
Pure Land. Us mundane people can be with the合伯 米 , the Bodisattvas 谷身佛 ,
and the Buddha in the same space. That's why it's the easiest, the fastest way to
for us to become enlightened and reach Buddhahood because you are with these
people who are enlightened in conclusion complete principle accomplishing
practice complete practice demonstrating the principle the principle is the
ultimate truth the emptiness the practice is the conventional truth where
we have real physical practice this can be chanting Amitabha this can be our six
pyramidas it can be any of our practice the complete principle of the one true
mind when we dwell in our perfect nature we will accomplish all our practice just
one chanting of Amitabha you are already the Buddha because we have the principle
we have the Buddha nature
to begin with any practice is a way to reach Buddhahood because we have it
originally vice versa all our practice is to show that we have the Buddha
nature the Buddha nature is our practice the practice is our Buddha nature
everything that you do even if you're sweeping the floor even if you're
washing dishes that can all be your practice
because one color one smell it's already the middle way so any of your
practice is for you to go to the Western pure land there's noведmondo
obstruction between the principle and the practice or we say thevic retour
numina and the phenomena or between our heart and
what is going on in the world that way you know how to live the slide by being a
empty, not attached to anyone or anything but love or sentient beings and give the best
that you have in this lifetime. At the end of our life, we will go to Amitabha's Western
Pure Land. There is a woman, she hated her husband. Her hatred was so strong, she grew
a lesion on her back. One day, she came to realization, I cannot live like this anymore.
So she made a clear-cut decision. I will only have love toward my husband. We will live
in harmony, peace, and kindness. From that day on, she never complained. She only exalted
his greatness. Three weeks later, she went back to the doctor. Her lesion was all gone.
There was no more. Why is that? Because the principle. We have the Buddha nature. It's
you just have a kind heart, then anything can happen in the physical world, in the world
of the phenomenon, because everything is based on our heart.
So detached from the idea of the self, detached from all our opinions and judgment of others,
only have love and kindness in this conventional world, then you are likely to align with all
Buddhas.
And go to Amitabha's Western Pure Land. So that's the class for today. Thank you for
listening. Amitabha.