Today we are going to discuss Aspirations for Enlightenment.
This is from The Awakening of Faith in the Mahayana by Aswagosha Bodhisattva.
There are three parts to this.
One is Aspiration for Enlightenment through the Perfection of Faith.
Two is Aspiration for Enlightenment through Understanding and Deeds.
Three is Aspiration for Enlightenment through Insight.
All Bodhisattva, they aspire to the Enlightenment realized by all Buddhas, disciplining themselves
to this end and advancing toward it.
Now let's look at Aspiration for Enlightenment through the Perfection of Faith.
We must have faith in our true nature.
We call it Suchness.
We need to cultivate three kinds of mind.
One is the mind of straightforwardness.
To correctly meditate on the principle of Suchness, Suchness is also called Emptiness.
It is the essential nature of reality.
It is only through delusion that all things come to be differentiated.
If one is to be free from delusion, then there will be no appearances of objects regarded
as absolutely independent.
Then we know what's Emptiness, that's Suchness, so correctly contemplate on it.
Two is the mind of Profoundness.
There is no limit to the joyful accumulation of all kinds of goodness.
In our nature, we are perfectly endowed with all the excellent qualities.
Number three is the mind of Great Compassion.
We naturally have great compassion.
We wish to uproot the suffering of all sentient beings.
So this is the mind of Great Compassion.
We naturally have great compassion.
We wish to uproot the suffering of all sentient beings.
So this is the mind of Great Compassion.
We naturally have great compassion.
So this is our Bodhi mind, who we really are.
Like a precious gem that is pure and bright, but is now marked in impurities.
Now we need to polish them with expedient means.
Therefore expedient means, to have the mind of straightforwardness, we have the fundamental
means.
This is the basis.
We need to meditate on the fact that the essential nature of all things is unborn, is emptiness.
So we can divorce it.
ourselves from deluded view and we do not abide in the samsara. On the other hand, we
do not abide in the nirvana. We know everything is cause and effect and it doesn't get lost
so we need to cultivate our great compassion, practice meritorious deeds and to transform
all sentient beings equally. Bodhisattva do not abide in samsara and do not abide in nirvana.
They actually abide in the suchness which is emptiness. To have the mind of profoundness,
we have two means. Means of stopping evil and means of increasing goodness. Means of
stopping evil means develop the sense of shame and repentance. That's how we stop our evil
and prevent them from growing. One is to conform to the faultlessness of the essential nature
of reality. Then we have the means of increasing the
capacity of our goodness by diligently honor and pay homage to the triple jewels of Buddha,
Dharma, Sangha and praise, rejoice and beseech the Buddha. That's how we increase our goodness.
Then to have the mind of great compassion, we have the means of the great vow of universal
salvation. To liberate all sentient beings down to the last one, no matter how long it
might take to help them to attain perfect nirvana.
We really have this bodhi mind. We just need to really believe in it and know our true
nature. There's an old man with Alzheimer's disease. Every day at the same time, he would
go sit in the front porch. All the kids would get off the school bus. Kids would come meet
him and he would think he's meeting them for the first time. All the kids, they patiently
talk to the old man as if they're meeting him for the first time. So all these amazing
kids, they are like Buddha. They are like Buddha. They are like Buddha. They are like Buddha.
They are like Buddha. They are like Buddha. They are like Buddha. They are like Buddha.
We all have the Buddha nature. So believe in our humanity, in who we really are. Now
we have strong faith, then we can take action by understanding and these by practicing the
six parameters. In the essential nature of reality, we are free from covetousness. Therefore,
we devote ourselves to giving. The first parameter, we want to give to the needy in terms of our
money, in terms of the dharma.
of the Dharma and in terms of fearlessness. Anyone who's in hardship or fearful, we want
to help them. No matter what you do, even when you're cooking, have the heart of giving.
People who eat your food will feel your love and kindness. So always have the heart of
giving because we naturally don't have any greed or stinginess in our nature. Number
two is to know that in our true nature, we are free from defilement. Therefore, we devote
ourselves to precepts, holding precepts, stopping evil and increasing goodness. That's who
we're supposed to be. So getting rid of our jealousy, deceit, flattery, and hatred is
totally possible because we don't have them in the first place. Number three is to know
that in the essential nature of reality, we are free from anger.
Therefore, we devote ourselves to endurance. We naturally have endurance in all kinds of
situations. When there is gain or loss, honor or dishonor, praise or blame, suffering or
joy, we naturally will stay calm and peaceful and patient. Number four, we are free from
indolence. Therefore, we devote ourselves to diligence. Do not be sluggish in doing
goodness. Purge ourselves of cowardice. Be courageous and selfless.
Do not be overjoyed, counselors. We want to pay homage to the Buddha. Have a sincere heart
of repentance and we see the Buddha for guidance and rejoice for other people's happiness.
That way we will avoid various hindrances and our capacity for goodness increases.
Number five is to know that in the commission we are free from scattered minds. Therefore,
we devote ourselves to concentration. Concentration means meditation, or we call it cessation.
We want to stop all wandering thoughts.
It's not that we first meditate on the object of senses in the external world
and then negate them in our mind.
It is only when our mind wanders off, then we bring it back to the correct thought.
What is the correct thought?
It's to know everything is mind only.
It's emptiness.
There is no external world of object as conceived.
Even this mind is devoid of any real mark of its own,
which would indicate its substantiality.
Therefore, it is not substantially conceivable as such at any moment.
That is the reality.
That's how we transcend all thoughts.
Number five is to know that in the essential nature of reality,
we are free from ignorance.
Therefore, we devote ourselves to wisdom.
This wisdom is also called clear observation.
We want to observe that
all
conditioned phenomena are stationary and are subject to instantaneous transformation
and destruction.
All activities of the mind arise and extinguish from moment to moment.
So there's no fixed substance.
There's only creation of condition.
So the past is like hazy as a dream,
and the present is like a flash of lightning,
and the future is like the cloud that
rises up suddenly.
So everything is impermanent and empty.
And when we understand this,
we feel great pity for all sentient beings that's going through suffering.
We are suffering all kinds of misery of the body and mind.
And at the present moment,
we are going through incalculable pressures and constraints that's difficult to forsake,
difficult to shake off.
That's why we want to make great vows to be free from all discrimination.
And we want to be able to practice all meritorious deeds and to apply limitless expedient means
so to help all suffering sentient beings to attain the perfect nirvana.
This is how we have real wisdom.
By having faith and understanding in the suchness,
then performing the six paramitas is easy.
Three is the result.
Aspiration for enlightenment through insight.
Through insight, we have three kinds of subtle modes of mind.
One is the true mind,
when we are free from all intellectual discriminations.
Again, the true mind is free from discrimination,
free from thoughts.
That's when we are self-enlightened.
Then we have the mind capable of applying expedient means to enlighten others.
Now we can spontaneously help all sentient beings
because now we are capable.
Number three is the mind subject to the influence of karma operating in subconsciousness.
We are still subject to karma when we still have any little bit of thinking
in terms of helping sentient beings.
So there's still movement in the subconsciousness.
Until we reach perfect enlightenment,
we will still have this subconsciousness.
So this is how we become enlightened through our aspiration.
Abbas Gosha, Bodhisattva, said the main reason I wrote this treatise
is to cause all men to free themselves from all sufferings
and to gain final bliss of enlightenment.
He just wants to help all of us to awaken so we don't have to suffer anymore.
Lastly, I want to share with you his prayer in the beginning of the treatise.
He said,
May all sentient beings be made to discard,
their doubts,
to cast aside all their evil attachments,
and to give rise to the correct faith in the Mahayana
that the lineage of the Buddha may not be broken off.
He just wants us to have no more doubts,
have real faith in the suchness in the Mahayana.
That's how the lineage of Buddhahood can be carried on.
So we all have the mission
to carry
on this lineage of Buddhahood,
just by knowing that we have the Buddha nature,
the suchness,
that is emptiness,
that's who we really are.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.