Today we are going to talk about unwholesome mental factors.
This is from the One Hundred Dharma Structure by Bodhisattva Vasavandhu.
It talks about everything in terms of One Hundred Dharma.
Out of the One Hundred Dharma, fifty-one are mental factors.
Out of the fifty-one, there are twenty-six that are considered unwholesome mental factors.
So these are our afflictions.
In this class, we will talk about these twenty-six unwholesome mental factors.
Hopefully it will help us eradicate our afflictions.
The twenty-six consists of six primary unwholesome mental factors and twenty secondary unwholesome mental factors.
Out of the twenty, it's divided up into ten minor, two medium, and eight major.
Let's first look at the six primary unwholesome mental factors.
Number one is greed.
Because we have a strong self, we are selfish.
That's why we are often greedy.
And that is the reason why we are in this reincarnation.
In the Sutra of Eight Realizations of Great Beings, it says,
Excessive desire is suffering.
Birth, death, and weariness in life originate from greed and desire.
All our life and death and reincarnation comes from our greed.
We should let go of our greed and our selfishness.
Two people were riding on the ship.
A gave B all his luggages, trusting his friend who would take care of his luggages.
B thought, oh, I should put all my friend's luggage on the bottom, and I put my luggage on top of his.
That way, if the ship gets wet, mine will not get wet.
But there was a big storm.
So the captain ordered the crew member to throw excessive luggages into the ocean.
Four-way reduction.
All B's luggages were thrown out of the ship.
A's luggages were still okay.
So do not be selfish.
When you do things that are unwholesome for your own benefit, the karma will just come right back to you.
Number two is anger.
We are often angry for many different unpleasant situations.
We can be mad at our body because of birth, aging, sickness, death.
We can be mad at ourselves when we have greed, anger, ignorance.
And we can be mad about the environment when it's hot, it's cold.
We think it's unpleasant, and we become upset.
And we can be angry about people that hurt us, our competitors, even friends and families.
And we can be angry about death at the end because we don't want it to happen.
Moreover, we are angry about ourselves.
About others, about the past, present, and future.
We can be upset about everything.
That's why we have to really look at how much anger we have inside of us.
There were two people on a boat arguing.
Why did you say that to me yesterday?
You tell me exactly why.
Little did they know, the time they spent arguing, the boat is already sinking.
The sinking boat is symbolizing reincarnation.
We are...
We are in the sinking boat.
But we are still quibbling, arguing, and mad at each other.
That's really being silly.
So do not be angry about anything or anyone.
Number three is ignorance.
Because we think there's a real me, we do everything dependent on the self.
That's the biggest ignorance.
And we do not believe in karma.
Doing wholesome deeds will bring good retribution.
And
unwholesome deeds will give you unwholesome retribution.
When we do not believe in karma, we will likely be worried and fearful about everything.
Because we don't understand karma.
That's all ignorance.
Number four is arrogance.
Everybody is arrogant in some ways.
Some are arrogant because of their education, their wealth, or their looks.
You might look down upon others.
That's all.
Because of our arrogance.
Number five is doubt.
We have a lot of doubt about our self.
Doubting our ability to become a Buddha.
We're doubting the teacher.
We don't think the teacher has the right cultivation.
So we don't believe in the teaching.
And we doubt the Dharma.
We don't think the Dharma can really be applied in real life.
If we have doubt, we are constantly unsure about what to do.
And always confused.
Number six is our wrong views.
Biggest wrong view is believing this body is the real me and separate from everyone else.
That's why we have a lot of opposition with everyone else in this world.
Following the primary unwholesome thoughts comes 20 unwholesome mental factors.
Let's first look at the 10 minor ones.
Number one is hatred.
When unpleasant event happens, hatred can arise because of someone's words.
Because of the situation, we can explode.
That's at the moment.
Number two is vengeance.
After the things happen, we hold grudges.
We might not show our hatred right there.
We repress it and we keep it inside of our heart.
Number three is vexation.
Because we have vengeance, we are likely to develop vexation.
That's when you get angry.
That's when you really want to get back to others.
We want to sue others.
Take revenge or talk back.
That's all because we have strong vexation.
All these are because of anger.
Number four is concealment.
When we do something wrong, we are likely to cover it up.
Because we want to have a good image of ourselves.
That's why we conceal our mistakes or our bad habits and bad behavior.
But when we conceal our bad deeds, negative karma will grow bigger.
Number five is deceiving.
We might be falsely kind.
We're lying, we're pretending, trying to deceive others to get some benefit.
That's all because we are not being sincere.
Number six is flattering.
We might flatter our boss, our superior, our parents because we want to gain some benefits.
That's all being insincere.
That is not a cultivator.
Number seven is pride.
Pride is being proud of ourselves.
It's kind of like arrogance, but you have to compare with others to be arrogant.
Pride, even without comparison, you're just naturally proud of yourself, thinking you're better.
Even when you're poor, you can still be proud.
Even if you have no education, you can still think I'm very smart.
That's all because of our natural pride.
Number eight is harmfulness.
When we have a vaccination, we might want to cause harm to others.
We want to kill, we want to do all these things that are very violent.
Number nine is jealousy.
Jealousy is also anger.
We do not want to see others being successful because we think we should be the only one that should be successful.
That's because of our selfishness.
Number ten is parsimony.
When we are stingy, we don't want to share our wealth or the dharma because we don't want others to have it.
All these are very strong vaccinations and afflictions.
Hatred, vengeance, vexation, harmfulness, and jealousy, they are based off of anger.
Concealment, deceiving, flattering are based on ignorance.
Pride and parsimony.
They are based on our greed.
Now let's look at the two median unwholesome mental factors.
One is shamelessness.
Two is guiltlessness.
Shamelessness is when we do not want to hear about wholesome virtues and cultivation of good people.
We actually dislike it.
Guiltlessness is when we like all the wrongdoings, all the violence, or people suing each other.
We're actually happy.
That's because we don't like it.
That's because we are guiltless.
When we are shameless and guiltless, we will do any kind of bad deeds.
So all bad deeds come from these two mental factors.
Now let's look at the eight unwholesome mental factors.
These are all things that are hindering our meditation.
Number one is drowsiness.
When we meditate, we become sleepy and drowsy.
When you cannot focus, the meditation will have no result.
Number two is restlessness.
It's the opposite of drowsiness.
When we have a lot of things going on in our mind, we're actually excited.
It's having a lot of wandering thoughts.
It cannot keep still.
It's agitated.
Number three is faithlessness.
When we do not believe in cultivating, in changing our afflictions, and becoming wholesome,
we do not believe we can reach Buddhahood.
And we do not believe we can achieve Buddhahood.
And change our bad habits.
When you do not believe, you cannot succeed in any of your cultivation.
Number four is slothfulness.
Being lazy in our cultivation.
We do not want to meditate.
We do not want to prostrate to Buddha.
We do not want to chant because we are simply lazy.
Number five is heedlessness.
It's kind of like laziness, but it's more not following the rule.
We're not watching our mind, our thoughts, our words.
We are just letting ourselves go wild.
Six is forgetfulness.
We forget to be mindful.
To be mindful of our Buddha nature.
We let our thoughts go wild and just follow whatever the situation is going on right now.
Seven is distraction.
Distracted by a lot of wandering thoughts.
Our mind is chaotic and agitated.
It's kind of like the restlessness, but it's more distracting.
Eight is unmindfulness.
Kind of like wrong view.
We are unmindful because we don't have the right view.
We might think our own opinion is right.
We do not follow the good teachings and we believe in our own opinions.
All these are mental factors that are hindering our meditation.
As you can see, the kinds of afflictions are different in the primary, secondary, the minor,
median, and major.
Now,
let's look at them in terms of the eight consciousnesses.
The eight consciousnesses, they all have a different number of unwholesome mental factors.
The eighth one is our laya consciousness, the big storehouse that stores all our karmic seeds.
The seventh consciousness is our manas, which is attached to the eight consciousnesses,
thinking there is a real me and a real self.
It's called the manas.
Then the seventh consciousness,
tells the sixth consciousness,
our mind,
what to think,
how to think about situations that we experience in our life.
Then we have the first five consciousnesses,
eyes,
ears,
nose,
tongue,
body consciousness.
So these five,
they work outside and the sixth consciousness is their manager.
These are the eight consciousnesses of how our mind functions.
So the eight consciousnesses,
all have different kinds of unwholesome mental factors.
The first five consciousnesses,
they only have greed,
anger,
and ignorance.
I have a five here.
Out of the six primary,
they are only capable of greed,
anger,
and ignorance.
They don't have any of the minor unwholesome mental factors.
They have the two medium ones,
and they have the eight major ones.
So three plus two plus eight,
together,
it has 13 out of the 26.
The sixth consciousness,
because the mind is very powerful,
it can think a lot,
it's capable of all 26 unwholesome mental factors.
So the one that really creates karma is really our mind consciousness.
The seventh consciousness,
it has four out of the six primary unwholesome,
mental factors.
It has greed,
greedy about the self.
It has no anger,
because it's never angry about the self.
It has ignorance,
thinking there's a self,
and it's arrogant about the self.
It has no doubt.
It has wrong view,
wrong view about the self.
Because it's only caring about the self,
it only has four out of the six.
It has no minor unwholesome mental factors,
and it has no medium ones.
It only has the major ones,
four plus eight together for a total of 12.
The eighth,
the liar consciousness,
it doesn't create karma,
so it's not wholesome or unwholesome.
It's a big storehouse,
stores everything as karmic seeds.
As you can see,
the minor,
medium,
major,
secondary unwholesome mental factors,
these are not based on the severity,
of the affliction.
They are based on the range of function
in the eight consciousnesses.
The minor one is called minor,
because it's only working in the sixth consciousness.
The medium one is called medium,
because it's in the first five consciousnesses,
and the sixth consciousnesses.
And the major one is called major,
because it's in the first five,
and the sixth consciousnesses,
and the seventh consciousnesses.
Therefore,
the range is bigger,
that's why it's called major.
If we can understand these 26 unwholesome mental factors,
always be mindful of our thoughts,
and be able to catch them early,
we are able to purify our consciousnesses,
and transform the deluded consciousnesses into wisdom.
That's how we change from a mundane
to
a Buddha.
Everyone can do this.
Why?
Because the eighth consciousness is actually our Buddha nature.
Just wake up and purify it.
All the unwholesome mental factors,
they do not really exist.
It's not in us to have these unwholesome mental factors.
You really have to believe that you are wholesome,
you are good,
you have the Buddha nature.
So by understanding how these
unwholesome mental factors work,
we can truly make a change in our lives right now,
and be out of reincarnation,
and reach Buddhahood.
It's all from being able to eradicate our unwholesome mental factors.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.