Today we are going to talk about the greatest offerings.
As a Buddhist, we show our reverence by giving material offerings to Buddha.
But what is the true offering? It is actually the offering of the Dharma.
In the Practices and Vows of Universal Worthy Bodhisattva, it talks about seven offerings of the Dharma.
And that's what we'll be talking about for today.
Number one, the offering of cultivation in accordance with Buddha's teaching.
It is one thing to listen to the sutra and another thing to really practice the Dharma in our daily lives.
As Confucius said, if a man is proper in his conduct, others will perform without orders.
If a man is improper in his conduct, though giving orders, no one will obey.
So how come our kids and family will not listen to us?
It's because we're not good role models.
In ancient China, there was a grandfather who lived with his son and grandson.
They lived together for many years.
But the grandfather got old and sick, and the son wanted to get rid of the grandfather.
So one day he made a large bamboo basket,
and he carried the grandfather up the mountain with the bamboo basket and wanted to leave him there.
The grandson saw the whole situation, so he cleverly said to his dad,
Hey dad, that saved the bamboo basket, so I can carry you up the mountain when you become old.
The father was very embarrassed of his behavior, immediately took the grandfather home and took very good care of him.
We want to be a good role model who really practice Buddha's Dharma,
and be all that is good, that is really honoring Buddha.
Number two is the offering of benefiting all sentient beings.
All sentient beings are Buddha's only beloved son.
So by benefiting all sentient beings, we're making Buddha very happy.
And also all sentient beings, they have the same Buddha nature as us.
We are all together as one.
So love and really care for all sentient beings.
In America,
there was a ten-year-old boy.
He was struggling in school because he had a compulsive behavior of tapping with his hands.
So all the teachers got very upset and sent him to the principal's office.
And the principal said to him,
Clinton, why don't you try to sit on your hands whenever you felt like tapping?
But usually that will only work for five seconds.
And he started tapping again.
So one day in class, he started tapping again.
And his teacher, Mr. Jensen said to him,
Clinton, you stay after class.
Clinton thought this time I'm in big trouble.
So he was really afraid.
After class, Mr. Jensen sat him down and gently said to him,
Clinton, you're not in trouble.
I just want to ask you one thing.
Have you ever thought about playing the drums?
And Mr. Jensen took out a pair of drumsticks out of his drawer.
From that day on, Clinton started playing the drums and he became a world famous drummer.
It only takes one person who truly cares to transform a person's life.
So be that person.
Number three, the offering of embracing all sentient beings.
Buddha gave us four methods so we can gain trust and build good relationships with all sentient beings.
Number one is giving.
We want to always be giving.
For example, in the household, we always want to save the food that other people like to eat for them.
And we eat something else.
That way they will know that you really care for them.
Or we can give the gift of smiling.
We always smile in the house so everybody feel your loving kindness.
And number two is loving words.
We always want to give positive feedbacks.
Oh, you're such a great husband.
You're so good at cooking.
Oh, you're such a good cleaner.
We always want to be positive so the atmosphere in the house will be very good.
Number three is support.
Everybody goes through difficult times.
And needs support.
We want to be the person that's always there to love and encourage them.
Number four is teamwork.
Always do things together.
We can set a time every week so we can chant Buddha's name together.
We can listen to Dharma together.
Or we can eat vegetarian food together.
That's all good teamwork that will build up a great family and a great relationship.
So use these four methods to embrace all sentient beings.
Number four is the offering of enduring suffering on behalf of others.
Karma is personal.
We cannot replace other people's karma and suffering.
But what we can do is try to endure as much suffering as we can so other people will suffer less.
There was a Buddhist story about a giant turtle.
A group of virgins, they were sailing when a big storm hit.
The giant turtle saw the shipwreck and saved the merchants by letting them climb on his back.
He brought them safely to land.
Tired from the long swim and the heavy load, he fell asleep on the sand.
Meanwhile, the merchants, they were hungry and thirsty.
And after the ordeal, they were still not sure of their lives.
So they were discussing amongst themselves how to find food.
One of them said, we should kill and eat the turtle.
The turtle heard this and out of great compassion for the merchants, he decided to stay put and be eaten.
That turtle was Shakyamuni Buddha.
Buddha said, there is not an inch of land where I did not lay my life for all sentient beings.
So sacrifice and enduring pain for others is the Bodhisattva way.
Number five, the offering of diligently fostering good roots.
Good roots are firm foundations we accumulate by cultivation.
Usually, we say there are three good roots, no greed, no anger, and no ignorance.
Number one is no greed.
We don't want to be coveted about the things that other people are greedy for.
In fact, we want to be yielding, let other people have the good things.
Number two is no anger.
We have to know this life, we are just travelers passing by.
So don't be contentious about anything with anyone.
It's not worth fighting because we are going to go to the pure land.
We're going to become Buddha.
So don't fight over the little thing this lifetime.
It's really not worth it.
We're just here to cultivate and contribute.
Number three is no ignorance.
We believe in karma.
Know that we really don't possess anything this lifetime.
Everything is cause and effect.
So work on the cause and don't worry about the effect.
As long as we're filled with the heart of loving kindness, then everything is already perfect.
So that's the three good roots when we don't have the three poisons.
Number four is one good root of all bodhisattva and that is called diligence.
All bodhisattva are very diligent.
They are vigorous day and night trying to save all sentient beings.
No matter how tough the situation gets, they will not turn back or give up.
Just like universal worthy bodhisattva.
My vows are endless.
Thought succeeding thought without interruption.
In bodily, vocal and mental deeds without weariness.
We want to be universal worthy bodhisattva.
So cultivate, foster good roots.
Number six is the offering of not forsaking the conduct of a bodhisattva.
A bodhisattva is an enlightened being who enlightens others.
A bodhisattva would think Buddha's heart is my heart.
Buddha's vows are my vows.
I use my vows to guide my conduct.
So every day he's thinking of how to save all sentient beings.
He's a rescuer.
He felt responsible for everybody's well-being and happiness and enlightenment.
He has no time to lament over his own problems.
He only think about others.
And a bodhisattva, he has a special trait.
No matter how badly other people treat him, he will not hold it against them.
He will never be irritated or lose his temper.
That's a true bodhisattva.
Also a bodhisattva would be humble.
He will not brag about himself.
Because he really understands non-self.
So be a bodhisattva.
That's honoring Buddha.
Number seven is the offering of not abandoning the bodhi mind.
Bodhi mind is our treasure.
It's our awakened mind.
It consists of three parts.
Number one, straightforwardness.
Always contemplate on the principle of suchness.
We have the perfect Buddha nature within us.
We are the pure consciousness.
So in this world, what we do is adapt to conditions but never change.
Remain steadfast while according with all conditions.
So we are in this world but not of this world.
We are actually with our Buddha nature.
That way you will have a really peaceful and happy life.
Number two is profoundness.
Profoundness is deep belief in accumulating all kinds of goodness.
So deep that it's to our bones.
No matter what happens, we only remember to be good.
Number three is great compassion.
Every Buddha, they take the heart of great compassion.
They want to uproot the suffering of all sentient beings.
Because of great compassion, we develop the bodhi mind.
Because of the bodhi mind, we become enlightened.
Every Buddha follows the same path.
Therefore, the greatest offering is the offering of the Dharma.
We actually don't need any money.
We just need to have the sincere heart of cultivation.
That's the best offering to Buddha.
That way we are accumulating infinite merits and virtues.
And we officially become the same family as Buddha.
So thank you for listening.
A-bi-to-fo.