Today we are going to talk about the Unbreakable Wisdom.
This is from the Diamond Sutra.
Diamond is a metaphor for unbreakable wisdom.
So we are going to talk about this perfect wisdom.
We are going to go straight into the last chapter of the Sutra.
It says all things are conditioned existence.
Everything has many different components, many different factors and parts.
For example, in Buddhism we talk about karma.
So from my prior life, good deeds and bad deeds caused me to have this body that I'm having here today.
And based on all the different factors, it's going to change.
I'm going to go through old age.
I'm going to go through sickness.
I'm going to go through death.
Everything is changing.
Anything that's conditioned existence, it will change.
It's not permanent.
All the components are going to change.
So definitely everything will change.
Second of all, it's unreal.
When we say unreal, we mean three things.
First, it's not permanent.
It's not forever the same.
Second, it does not exist by itself.
No, I cannot exist by myself.
There are many different parts, different components for me to exist here today.
So it's not real.
Lastly, it cannot be controlled.
I cannot control how my body is going to age or when it's going to die.
So it's not real.
With everything that is conditioned existence, we can know for sure that it will definitely change.
And it's unreal.
Now it talks about six things.
Six metaphors to describe this conditioned existence.
It's like a dream, a mirage, a bubble, or a shadow, or a door drop, and a flash of lightning.
There was a story about a poor student named Mr. Lu.
He was going into the city to take the Imperial exam.
He was tired, so he checked into a hotel.
The hotel owner said, oh, you must be tired.
Let me go cook you dinner.
So Mr. Lu went into his room and took a nap.
He had a dream.
He dreamt that he took first place in the Imperial exam.
He married the daughter of the most wealthy person in the city.
And he became a very prominent government official.
One day, his nemesis falsely accused him of a crime.
So the emperor sent him out of exile for years.
Later, the emperor realized he
was falsely accused, brought him back, gave back his position, and later promoted him again.
So he enjoyed everything.
And he had many children and many grandkids.
And he was getting old.
Then he heard a sound knocking on the door.
Mr. Lu, your porridge is cooked.
So he woke up.
The time it took to cook the porridge, his whole life went by.
That is to show you our life is like a dream.
It's like a mirage.
Mirage is an optical illusion.
We think it's real.
For example, the success, fame, or position that you hold, it's all gonna change.
Can change for the better or change for the worse.
One day you might lose it.
One day you can get it back.
But it's forever changing.
Your success, it's like a mirage.
It's like a bubble.
We all dream of the perfect love.
The perfect marriage.
But do you know your partner is a conditioned existence?
Everything that he or she likes every day will change.
So how can you expect the relationship to be the same forever?
That is not possible.
Marriage, love, it's also like a bubble.
It's like a shadow.
Like a black image.
You cannot touch the image.
It's not real.
For example,
we all want to have
the perfect image of being a great person,
a mom,
a great doctor,
whatever we are.
But that is still just an image like a shadow.
Or like a dewdrop.
Just a little drop of water.
When the sun comes out, it evaporates.
That's just like our life.
It's a very short life that we are here on this earth today.
We should treasure every moment and be the best that we can be.
It's like a flash of lightning.
We all want to keep our youth.
We want to look 18 all the time.
Some people have plastic surgeries,
go on diets just to keep their youth.
But it's not possible.
Your youth is like a flash of lightning.
These are six metaphors that describe all things in life.
So one should contemplate upon all things in this wisdom.
Not to force yourself to look at things this way or be pessimistic.
Or hate your life.
No.
To see things in a clear way is to understand the truth.
See the reality of things.
That way you will be so much more.
You can reach your potential.
And bring out your true Buddha nature.
Your true self.
Now we go to the body of the sutra.
Talking about four forms.
Four concepts that we are attached to.
Preventing us from seeing.
The truth.
And having the unbreakable wisdom.
First is the form of the self.
We all have a strong idea about me.
Me as a person.
About what's mine.
My family.
Or I'm a successful doctor.
I'm afraid people's gonna come steal my things because I'm so rich.
Or even for Buddhists.
I'm a Buddhist.
I have high moral value.
Or I'm a great meditator.
You have an image.
Of a strong self.
But that's against the real teaching of Buddha.
So we all have the strong idea of me and the self.
There was a master.
One day he brought all his students up in the mountain.
And when they reached the top of the mountain.
There was a big tree.
The master went and hugged the tree really really tightly.
And he asked the student.
Please help pull me away from this tree.
I am stuck.
So all the students tried really hard.
To pull their master.
But the master has supernatural power.
All the students cannot move him at all.
After a long time.
They stopped trying.
And the master just let go.
And he was free.
He said to all his disciples.
We are all hugging the tree.
Hugging the ego.
Hugging the me.
And we're saying.
Why am I suffering so much with my life?
Because we are hugging the self.
That's why you have so much pain.
And so much sorrow.
And so much suffering.
So the image of the self is actually why we are suffering.
The second image is the image or the form of others.
Because there is a self.
We have the opposite.
Which are people that are different from my existence.
You have conflicts.
You have comparison.
You have envy.
Just look at brothers and sisters.
Who's prettier.
Who's doing better in school.
Or who does the parents love.
More.
Because we have the idea of others separating from us.
That's why we have jealousy.
That's why we have pride.
That's why we have so much suffering.
The idea of the self makes us have the idea of others.
So that we have a lot of conflicts.
The third is the form of a physical being.
This is talking about the physical existence.
The space that we're living in.
We always describe ourselves.
I am from what country and this is my house at this address.
We are very caught up in how we identify ourselves.
Our existence is not defined by our physical existence.
The space is not real.
It's an illusion.
Buddha talked about the six realms of reincarnation.
There are actually lots of ghosts.
There are actually heavenly beings.
There are 28 levels of heaven.
And there are actually Buddhas who are out of the six realms of reincarnation.
If we see beyond the physical existence, we can see so much more.
There are actually a lot more out there that we don't even know.
If you can just break away from the concept of the physical being.
We have the concept about lifespan.
This is space.
This is time.
We're very caught up in the idea of time.
Everybody wants to have a long life.
When you're old, you talk about when you were young.
How great you were.
If you're a child, then you all dream about the future.
I'm going to be the president.
I'm going to be someone great.
You know, we're thinking about the past, thinking about the future.
The concept of time itself is an illusion.
If you can go into deep meditation, you will see your past lifetimes.
You might be able to see your future.
You can see a lot of things.
If you just let go the idea, the concept of time and lifespan.
We are all caught up.
In these four forms.
That's why we cannot see the truth.
Now to see these four forms as the six metaphors we just talked about.
For example, you should see the idea of the self as a dream, as a mirage, as a bubble,
as a shadow, as a door drop, as a flash of lightning.
Same as the image of others, image of physical beings.
The image of lifespan, the time.
It's all like a dream, a mirage, a bubble, a shadow, a door drop, and lightning.
If you can see everything in this matter, you have the unbreakable wisdom.
And you see what Buddha sees.
You can do a lot more for mankind.
Your life on this earth would be completely different.
Because you will be able to reach enlightenment and help everyone else reach enlightenment.
In conclusion, we should free ourselves from all attachments while mastering the mind.
The two big questions throughout the whole sutra is where should my heart reside?
And how do I master this wandering mind full of delusions?
The answer is simple.
Let go of all attachments to form an image.
See beyond the illusion.
Then you'll be able to master your mind naturally.
Because your true Buddha nature will come alive if you just let go of the concepts you're holding onto.
Let go of the big tree.
You are free.
Like an eagle up in the air.
Up in the sky.
You see the world much more clearly.
You can have this grand vision and see what other people cannot see.
Your happiness should not be depending on marriage or my success or my image of the self or in this space and time.
If you let it all go, your happiness is unbreakable.
The unbreakable wisdom is unbreakable happiness.
Happiness is inside within you.
Not the outside conditioned existence.
So this is the perfect wisdom.
This is how we get out of reincarnation.
For Pure Land Buddhist practitioners, it's very important.
You have to let go of this lifetime, this samsara life full of the self and the me.
You have the same unbreakable wisdom as Amitabha Buddha.
So sure enough, you'll definitely go to the Pure Land.
Pure Land and reach Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.