Today we are going to talk about repentance.
Why is it so hard for us to change our bad habits and defilements such as quitting smoking,
stop arguing with our spouses, stop being bitter, jealous, and angry?
It's because we haven't learned how to truly repent.
So today we are going to discuss how to repent and reform and effectively change our lives
for the better.
So there are two kinds of repentance.
One is called formal repentance and the second one is called formless repentance.
Formal repentance.
Of all bad karma which I have done based on beginningless grief, anger, and ignorance
committed by body, speech, and mind, I now repent and reform.
We need to admit that we have a lot of bad karma, which means we have a lot of bad causes
which will have negative retributions in the future.
So recognize and admit that we have a lot of mistakes.
We have done a lot of bad things.
The mistakes are based on beginningless grief, anger, and ignorance.
They're all from our three poisons of the mind.
It's beginningless because we have lifetimes and lifetimes deeply ingrained poisons inside
of us.
We commit a lot of bad deeds from our body, speech, and mind.
These are the three gateways of our actions.
We have ten unwholesome deeds.
If we don't do these ten things, then it's ten wholesome deeds.
That's how we judge good and evil.
Three are from the body, four are from our speech, and three are from our mind.
First we have killing, which means harming others' lives.
And the second is stealing, taking other people's belongings when it doesn't belong to you.
Third is sexual misconduct.
Adultery.
Fourth is lying, deceiving others.
All the bad deeds are not benefiting others.
The fifth is divisive speech, breaking up people's relationships by slandering another
person.
The sixth is harsh speech, which means all kinds of harsh language.
Idle gossip is unwholesome jokes or have sexual connotations.
And from our mind, there's greed, selfish.
We only think of others.
We only think of ourselves.
We only think about ourselves.
Anger, ill feeling, animosity toward others, and we have ignorance, not understanding cause
and effect.
Don't understand karma, that's why we're worried, angry, we have a lot of anxiety and
stress about life.
That's all from our ignorance.
That's why our bad karmas are committed by body, speech, and mind.
I now repent and reform.
From today on.
I vow to repent, turn around completely, never do it again.
So the key of repentance is never do the offenses again.
Because we are human, we're not born a saint, we all make mistakes, we're not perfect.
So a lot of times, a cultivator will repent, make the offenses, and then repent again and
make the offenses.
According to the Bodhisattva precepts, we're not perfect.
We're not perfect.
As long as you keep trying, you have the heart of confession, but it's just that the offenses
are just too deeply ingrained that you cannot change it right away, you don't break the
precept.
It actually has merit just for trying.
So precepts are very, very sympathetic and very, very flexible.
As long as we hold the precept and we remember to change and to confess, we are already on
our way to Buddhahood.
And we're accumulating infinite merit.
And we're accumulating infinite merit just by struggling to do good.
The key is never give up.
I might not be perfect right now, but I will keep trying every day until I have no more
offenses.
So that's the spirit of a Bodhisattva.
At Buddha's time, there was a Angulimala.
He was the son of a Brahmin.
He was sent to study with his teacher at a young age.
Because he's very smart, he was the teacher's favorite student.
And all the other students were very good students.
And all the other students were jealous of him.
So they told the teacher that Angulimala is having a relationship with the teacher's wife.
The teacher was very upset and wanted to revenge.
So he told Angulimala, you need to kill a thousand people and give me their fingers
as a payment for me teaching you.
Angulimala was confused.
But he started killing people all over the villages.
And he put a lot of money into it.
He put the fingers on the necklace and wrapped it around his neck.
So by this time, he already had 999 fingers.
He just needed one more.
He said to himself, I'm going to kill the first person that I see and then I will be
done.
The first person that came was his mother.
And he said, okay, I'm going to kill my mother.
This other side, there was a monk, which is Buddha.
And he said, okay, I will kill this monk.
He started running toward the monk, trying to catch him.
But no matter how hard he tried, he could not catch up to this monk, who was walking
very slowly.
He was exhausted.
He cried out, you stop now.
Buddha turned back and said, I have stopped.
It is you that have not stopped.
Angulimala was confused.
He's like, what do you mean, monk?
I have stopped and you are still walking, but you said the opposite.
Buddha said, I have stopped all my anger.
Anger and violence, long time ago, but you are still killing and hurting people.
You need to stop now.
Just these few words touched the heart of Angulimala.
He kneeled down, confessed that he was wrong.
He asked to be ordained as a monk.
From that day on, he cultivated extremely hard.
No matter how other people treated him, throwing rocks at him.
Because he's a mass murderer, he has no ill feeling toward anyone anymore.
His heart is always at peace and always cultivating.
One day he saw a pregnant lady having a hard time giving birth.
He went back to the temple and asked Buddha, how can I help this lady?
Buddha told him what to do.
So he came back and very sincerely said, sister, from the day that I have been a monk till
now.
I have never had any ill feeling toward any living being.
By this truth, may you be well.
May your unborn baby be well.
Immediately the mother gave birth and both the mother and the child are safe and healthy.
So from a mass murderer that killed 999 people to the most compassionate person and became
our head and enlightened.
How is that possible?
If he can do it, we can do it.
We haven't done anything that bad.
We can be a noble and virtuous person if we just keep trying, holding precepts and keep
repenting every day.
It's like washing ourselves clean.
Repentance is a gift for us to renew and becoming better and better each day.
So love to repent.
It's a great dharma door for us to improve.
The second one is called formless repentance.
So formal repentance is changing actual offenses through the behavior.
Formless repentance is changing from the mind, from the source.
Offenses arise from the mind, use the mind to repent.
When the mind is forgotten, offenses are no more.
Mind forgotten, offenses eradicated.
Both are empty.
This is called true repentance and reform.
This is a deeper wisdom.
Offenses arise from the mind.
The root of all our offenses comes from the mind.
It's like we have a poisonous tree.
We don't want to just pull the leaves one by one.
We want to uproot the whole tree.
So we want to know our mind and use the mind to repent.
Then we will have no more offenses.
When the mind is forgotten, offenses are no more.
The key here is when the mind is forgotten.
It doesn't mean we become forgetful.
It means we get to the deep depth of our mind.
The depth of our mind is without thinking of the duality of good and evil, wholesome and unwholesome.
There's no offenses.
There's no merits.
It's all the same.
Because in essence, it's all empty.
The self is empty and all the offenses are empty.
When you understand this truth, your mind is pure.
You will have no more offenses to start with.
So offenses are no more.
The mind forgotten, offenses eradicated, both are empty.
The mind is empty of its essence and offenses are empty in its essence.
Both are empty so they don't really exist.
If I ask you, show me the heart when you were angry at someone, it's already gone.
So which one is the real you?
Where is the offenses?
Where is the bad deed?
Where is the mind that committed the offenses?
It's all a conditioned existence.
They're impermanent and it's not real.
So know that for a fact, you will be free to change anything because anything is possible.
With emptiness, you can change anything.
There's not a set personality or I'm just this, I'm just an alcoholic.
There's nothing that's permanent.
Everything is empty of its essence so everything can be changed easily.
This is called true repentance.
Repentance and reform.
This is the wisdom of emptiness.
So by understanding this, you will be pure in your mind and you will feel joyous in your heart.
No more feeling ashamed or dwelling on your past mistakes, the people that you have hurt or whoever that has hurt you.
Let go of all the trauma and all the things that happened to you.
Because they're empty in its essence.
That's why we meditate.
When we meditate, we try to get to the root of the subconscious mind, completely overhaul and change your entire life.
So we need to use both the formal and formless repentance together.
Every day we want to repent because repenting means we're getting better.
We're aware of our body, speech and mind.
So we need to do the formal repentance and try to change each offenses.
Notice your speech.
Notice your action.
Notice your thoughts.
Change them one by one.
Do not give up.
Know that just by trying, you're already earning incredible merits for yourself.
You're on the way to Buddhahood.
We also need to keep the formless repentance in mind.
Know that there's no offenses to begin with.
Start with zero.
Every day you're starting anew.
Every day you're starting pure.
Have faith in yourself.
And manifest greatness and happiness.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.