Today we will talk about Twelve Dependent Origination.
This is the truth about reincarnation.
We will incorporate the Twelve Dependent Origination with the Four Noble Truths and Three Dharma Seals
and understand their importance to Pure Land Buddhism.
Let's first look at the Twelve Links of Dependent Origination.
Number one is ignorance.
Ignorance is our delusion about our own existence.
We think there is a real self.
Being selfish is normal and we have a lot of greed, anger and ignorance.
Because of our ignorance, we have formation, which is our volitional activities.
We started creating karma with our body, speech and mind.
This can be wholesome or unwholesome.
Then because of the formation, we have consciousness, our alaya consciousness.
Now find the right parents and when the parents are having copulation,
this consciousness attached to the egg and the sperm and now the mother is officially pregnant.
Then we have name and form.
When the mind is not fully developed, it's called the name.
And when the body is not fully developed, it's called the form.
Then we develop the six senses.
Our eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body and mind.
We come into contact with the world when the mother gives birth.
And then we will start to have feelings, experiencing sensations such as pleasure, displeasure and neutral feeling.
We will have a lot of craving.
This includes all the love and hate, likes, dislikes and greed and anger.
We have a lot of clinging.
There's a lot of grasping and attachment to all the world.
There's a lot of attachment to all the worldly things.
Then we will have becoming, creating new karma, new karmic formation.
Then we have birth, emergence of new born being.
Then we have aging and death all over again.
This is two layers of cause and effect through three periods.
Ignorance and formation, these are past causes.
Consciousness, name and form.
Six senses, contact and feeling.
These five are our present.
Effects.
Craving, clinging, becoming, that's our present.
Causes.
Birth and aging, that's our future effect.
It's two layers of cause and effect.
So dependent, ordination, it means cause, condition and effect.
One relies on the other.
This arising, that arises.
This ceasing, that ceases.
This is a cycle.
If we follow the cycle, this would be called samsara.
But if we reverse the cycle, it's called nirvana.
When ignorance is the condition, formation arises.
When formation is the condition, consciousness arises, so on and so forth.
So that's going forward with this reincarnation.
But if we learn Buddhism, we try to reverse the cycle.
So we want to go against the current.
If we don't want aging, death, don't have birth.
If we don't want to have birth, don't have becoming.
If we don't want to have becoming, don't have clinging.
If we don't want formation, don't have ignorance.
With the cessation of ignorance, formation ceases.
With the cessation of formation, consciousness ceases.
So on and so forth.
So we want to end this reincarnation.
The point of Buddhism is to reverse the samsara and reach nirvana,
which means ultimate peace and liberation.
From afflictions.
This 12 dependent origination is the same as the Four Noble Truths.
Four Noble Truths is suffering, cause of suffering, cessation of suffering,
path to end suffering.
Our suffering is 3 to 7.
That's our current suffering.
Birth and aging, 11 and 12.
That's our future suffering.
What is the cause of our suffering?
It is our ignorance and formation.
That's our past causes.
Then our present causes is our craving, clinging, and becoming.
Therefore, you can see that the key is to get out of samsara,
to work on the craving, clinging, and becoming.
We need to stop this rope that is tying us down.
In every situation, we have the right to choose.
Either we follow the samsara and go with our craving,
or we follow the Dharma and reach nirvana.
There was a businessman who loved gold.
So he worked day and night to accumulate a lot of money and a lot of gold.
He was afraid that people were going to steal his gold.
So he hid the gold in a big bottle and buried the bottle under the ground.
In his lifetime, he accumulated 7 bottles of gold.
But because he worked too hard, he died young.
After death, because of his craving for gold,
he reincarnated into a poisonous snake.
The snake that guarded the 7 bottles of gold.
And this happened lifetime after lifetime for thousands of years.
Until one day, he felt extremely tired of this life.
So he left the 7 bottles and went on the road and found a passerby.
He asked,
Can you please help me to bring a bottle of gold to the temple and donate to the temple?
The compassionate monk at the temple accepted the offering
and expanded the Dharma to the temple.
The snake was refreshed with Dharma joy
and decided to donate the other 6 bottles of gold.
With this act of giving and renunciation of craving,
he then reincarnated as a heavenly being
and later became a human.
He was Sharaputra, Shakyamuni Buddha's disciple
who attained Arhatship.
So his craving was his love for gold.
What is our craving?
Understand what we're going through.
What are we craving for?
We need to cut off the rope of Samsara
because it's a whole big massive suffering
and it's actually a big lie.
We don't want to keep going through the cycle of reincarnation.
In order to end the Samsara and reach Nirvana,
we need to understand the 3 Dharma seals.
Seals are like stamps that prove the authenticity
that this is Buddha's teaching.
There are 3 stamps.
Number 1 is impermanence.
As you can see in this 12 links of dependent origination,
everything is condition arising.
Therefore, they're constantly changing.
Nothing is stable or fixed.
So impermanence is the truth.
Impermanence is not a bad thing.
It is only suffering because we believe
that things should be permanent.
We think this body should be permanent.
We think relationship or our money or our wealth
should be permanent.
So when it changes, it becomes suffering.
So accept the impermanence
and use all the impermanence situation to cultivate.
So when the problem arises,
calmly discern what is the cause and condition
that is causing today's problem.
What can I do to change the conditions
and make things better and benefit everyone?
And I would be wrong if any cause of suffering arises in me,
such as grief, anger, and ignorance.
And I need to work diligently on my causes
through my thoughts, speech, and action.
With every impermanence situation,
I should enhance my wisdom and compassion.
So use this impermanence wisely.
Then we have non-self.
In this 12 links of dependent origination,
you don't see an I.
There's not an I.
Everything is just cause and effect.
This is condition arising.
So in the condition arising,
there's not a me.
But we think there is an independent me
that is independent from all the dependent origination,
which is not true.
The me that we think is independent, existing,
that is a pseudo-self.
For example, someone yelled at me
and I'm upset.
That's because I think there is a real Tracy.
That's being yelled at.
But if we know it's non-self,
then we'll be liberated from anger.
So break the bond of self-love.
It is the root source of all our delusions.
See things as they are.
As condition arising,
there is not a me in this condition arising.
When you really see the truth,
you will see true equality.
No one person is better than other.
And I'm no better than anyone else.
Everybody is equal in this condition arising.
When you see this,
you will have true equality
and true compassion toward all beings.
And then you realize everybody is together as one.
Because everybody is empty in essence
and everyone is non-self.
When we understand impermanence and non-self,
we will reach Nirvana.
Nirvana is not death
or a place.
Nirvana is the cessation of afflictions,
delusions.
We're liberated from Samsara.
This is our normal state.
We are originally Nirvana.
It's not something we're trying to get.
We just need to see clearly
the truth about Samsara.
Let go of our craving and clinging.
Pure Land Buddhism is the same thing.
Why do we need to go to the Pure Land?
Pure Land is our Nirvana.
We want to go to Pure Land
because of our strong vow.
We want to be detached from this mundane world
that we keep being trapped in this cycle
of reincarnation,
which is a massive lie
and massive suffering.
We want to get out of it.
This is all a self-created jail.
It's like we're planting a poisonous tree.
We keep giving it water,
keep giving it fertilizer,
but this is a poisonous tree.
But we keep letting it grow bigger and bigger.
So chanting the name Amitabha
is to wake us up from this delusion,
from this upside-down false thinking.
Therefore, Buddhism is not just about
chanting the name Amitabha.
It's about our profound insight
and understanding about
impermanence, non-self, and Nirvana.
And then our chanting
will have real substance
has real meaning.
Subsequently,
every recitation of Amitabha
is now worth more than
10,000 recitations of Amitabha
because we have true insight.
Just like if I sincerely say,
I'm sorry.
It's better than I say,
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry,
but I don't mean it.
And I say it 10,000 times.
It's useless, right?
The real chanting
is to have real understanding
of the Dharma
and want to transform
and be out of the suffering.
Don't just rely on Amitabha
to bless us.
We need to go inside
and work on ourselves
to look deeply into our craving,
cleaning, and becoming,
and cut off this rope
that we created for ourselves
that's entangling us.
Once you're a true Pure Land practitioner,
then you'll be confident,
you will be going to the place
of ultimate bliss,
which is our Nirvana.
Finally, when you let go
of all attachments,
even to the Dharma,
even to Twelve Dependent Origination,
Four Noble Truths,
and Three Dharma Seals,
you will see that
Samsara is the same as Nirvana
because Samsara is emptiness
and Nirvana is emptiness.
That is the ultimate truth,
and ultimate enlightenment.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.