Today we are going to talk about the Ten Great Vows of Universal Worthy Bodhisattva.
What's a Bodhisattva?
It's someone trying to become a Buddha, doing the work like a Buddha to help everybody be out of the reincarnation and become Buddha.
So they're full of love and compassion.
Universal Worthy Bodhisattva, he is the symbol of all Bodhisattva.
His mind is broad, full of compassion, love, and is never-ending.
So we're going to learn his Ten Big Vows.
This is what he lives by every day.
Today we're just going to cover four, and we're going to have two more classes to cover the other six.
The first vow is to pay respect to all Buddhas.
So respect and really treasure everybody.
So who is Buddha?
Sometimes we bow to Buddha.
Who are we bowing to?
We're not bowing to a statue.
We're bowing to our own Buddha nature.
Bowing is to show our respect to our own Buddha nature.
We want to respect everyone.
Everyone is a Buddha.
That includes your husband, your wife, your children, everybody around you.
Everybody is a Buddha.
Respect everybody, regardless of who they are.
In the Lotus Sutra, there is a never-despising Bodhisattva.
He doesn't stay in the temple and chant.
He goes everywhere.
And everybody he sees, he says to them,
I deeply respect you.
I dare not belittle you because I know you are going to be a Buddha.
So he goes around and tells it to everybody without discrimination.
All the monks and a lot of people, they started disliking him, thinking he's very annoying.
They started throwing rocks and sticks at him because he goes around every day to tell people that.
And people started hating him.
But he never gets upset.
He just still says the same thing.
You know, I dare not belittle you.
I respect you.
You are going to be a Buddha.
He does that all his life.
Till his dying days, he heard this voice in the air.
You are going to reach Buddhahood because of what you did this lifetime.
And he became enlightened.
All the people that hated him before started learning from him.
He helped everybody reach Buddhahood and become enlightened.
This is a great story of someone who,
truly respects everybody equally without any discrimination.
So this is what we want to learn, the Bodhisattva's way.
And the second is to praise the Tathagata.
We love and respect everybody and we also use our mouth to praise people.
Buddha's other name is called Tathagata.
Why do we put this word here?
Because you want to praise the virtues and goodness of Buddha.
Everybody is a Buddha.
But not everybody is virtuous.
We only praise the good virtues.
If someone is killing people, we do not go praise them.
You want to praise everybody that's doing good,
that's being virtuous, that's doing kind deeds.
We don't want to be stingy with our praises.
Every day you should praise someone.
Praise your husband.
Praise your wife.
Praise your mom.
Praise your kids.
Praise everybody.
When you praise them, they have more confidence.
They will be encouraged.
They do things better.
So there is a story.
There is a cow.
In the olden days, the cows, they can talk.
So one day he told his farmer, his owner,
Owner, you are so poor.
I have an idea.
You go tell the rich farmer I'm going to have a race with his cow.
And whoever wins the race will get a thousand dollars and you'll be rich.
So he said, oh, sure.
So all the villagers, they come to see this race.
The poor farmer said to everybody, oh, this is my cow.
He's great.
He runs very fast and he works really hard.
But he only has one horn.
Then they start having a race.
But the cow lost.
The owner asked him, you told me to go have a race and you lost.
What's going on?
He said, I was going to win.
But you said I only have one horn.
And made me lose my confidence.
That's why I lost.
Okay, you go tell him I'm going to have another race.
This time you only say my good quality.
Don't say my shortcomings.
And I will win.
So all the villagers come and they have another race.
And he said, oh, my cow is wonderful.
So fast and so hardworking.
He's such a great cow.
And then they have a race.
And short enough, he won.
So everybody needs praise.
Their confidence will boost up and they will do great in their life.
So don't be stingy with your praises.
You know, that's a very good deed when you praise others.
The third great vow is to make abundant offerings.
Offerings.
That means we give other people gifts.
Do everything that you can to give to others.
As Buddhas, we do a lot of offerings to the Buddha.
Every morning, we will give Buddha a little cup of water.
Why do we do that?
Buddhas don't need your offerings.
These offerings is to help us remember to cultivate.
Today, I'm going to have a pure heart.
My heart is going to be as pure as this water.
So I offer it to Buddha to remind myself I'm going to be pure.
We offer Buddha flowers.
Why do we offer him flowers?
Because flowers are causes.
Virtuous causes will give you good results.
So flower is the cause and we offer fruits.
Fruits is the result.
Do good deeds, you will have good results.
You have prosperous life.
You will have very good life if you are a good person.
So all the flowers, all the fruits, that is just to remind yourself to be good.
And we offer Buddha lights.
It means wisdom.
Today, I'm going to be wise.
I'm not going to fight with anyone.
I'm going to love everybody because I know I'm one with the universe, with everybody.
All the offerings is to help yourself learn, improve and be a Bodhisattva.
All the offerings is just to bring out our loving heart.
2600 years ago in India, Shakyamuni Buddha, he's the only Buddha we know of on this earth.
There was a very, very poor lady.
She really, really wants to offer a light to Buddha.
She goes to beg and finally got one penny.
And she went to get the oil lamp.
She's so happy.
She went up to Buddha and said,
Buddha, I want to offer this lamp to you.
With this, I vow that I want to be wise.
I want to reach Buddhahood.
And I want to help all sentient beings to get out of delusions, darkness and reach enlightenment and Buddhahood.
And she bowed and that was her offering.
So the next day,
everybody offered a lot of lights to Buddha.
But all the lights were out, except hers.
Buddha's servant tried to blow out the oil lamp.
But for the life of her, he could not blow it out.
It would just keep going, keep going, keep going.
And Buddha says, because her heart was so sincere,
her light will be strong forever, forever.
And she will reach Buddhahood.
If your heart is strong and you really want to become a Bodhisattva,
and help everybody become enlightened,
that is a strong vow.
A strong vow will have great power.
And that is the power that gives you life force.
So to make abundant offerings,
that's a Bodhisattva's way.
Lastly is to repent and confess.
You might say, I haven't done anything bad in my lifetime.
I've been pretty good.
In Buddhism, we say every thought creates a karma, a result.
So you thought.
This person is ugly.
That has karma.
Someone in your life will come to you and say you're ugly.
Because you created this thought.
Every thought is a karma.
So how much bad thoughts we have, it's countless.
So every day we must confess.
Confess our sins and repent.
What do we mean by repent?
Not just to bow to Buddha.
Repenting means I will never do it again.
I will be good.
I will not be mad at anyone.
I will never yell at anyone.
I will be kind.
I will be loving.
Confess.
You will become better.
Through confession, you will be clean and you start over.
You keep learning.
You keep starting over.
You do bad things.
You keep confessing.
And you keep getting better.
So always confess our sins.
There was a boy.
Ever since he was little,
he just remembered he was brought into the orphanage by his mom.
That was the last thing he remembered of his mom.
And he never seen his mom again.
So he grew up.
So he grew up in the orphanage hating his mom.
So his whole life, he's full of hate.
He grew up.
And he's in his 30s.
One day he finally found the courage.
He said, I'm going to go try to look for my mom.
So one day he finally found where she stayed and went to the place.
She was already dead.
And she had this table and this desk.
And he looked in her drawer.
And what did he find?
He found all the train ticket stops from her.
From her house to the orphanage.
It's full of it.
The whole drawer is full of the ticket stops.
What does that mean?
His mom visited him every day.
She was there every day to see him.
She just didn't let him know.
He cried.
He knew I was wrong my whole life.
My mom loves me.
So from that day on, he changed.
And his life is full of love.
He never hates anyone anymore.
All the bad things that happen to us is not caused by others.
It's caused by our own thinking.
So change your thought to be one that's loving and full of appreciation and kindness.
Then you change your life.
Repent.
That's when we grow and become a better person.
These are all great vows.
If we do this every day, we become the universal, worthy Bodhisattva.
His vow never ends.
And it's from thought to thought.
Not even a single thought, he forgets about his vows.
His body, mind, and speech all take the action to do this vow.
And he never ceases.
And he never feels tired.
Every waking moment, he is trying to be a Bodhisattva.
And that's why we try to learn.
To become a great person with great vision inside of our heart.
To love to help everybody become enlightened.
Okay, so that's the class for today.
And we will continue with the vows.
Next time.
Thank you for listening.