Today we are going to talk about Guarding the Original True Mind from the 5th Patriarch of Zen Buddhism, Hong Ren.
He says the only thing we need to do is constantly guard our true nature.
It is talked about in terms of 4 questions and 4 answers.
1. How do we know Guarding the Original True Mind is the foundation of Nirvana?
The essence of Nirvana is silence and stillness, inaction and peace and bliss.
What is the essence of Nirvana?
It is silence when the mind is completely quiet and silent without wandering thoughts.
It is still, inaction, unmoved by any phenomenon or circumstances of life.
It is always in a state of peace, happiness, harmony and bliss.
This is the state of Nirvana, the cessation of suffering, the elimination of afflictions, enlightenment.
How do we reach this level of Nirvana?
It is through Guarding the Original True Mind.
As one's mind is the True Mind,
the illusion will be cut off.
Because the illusion is cut off,
one will have right thoughts.
Because one has right thoughts,
the wisdom of silence and illumination will be generated.
Because the wisdom of silence and illumination is generated,
one can completely realize the Dharma nature.
Because the complete realization of the Dharma nature,
Nirvana is attained.
So there are five steps here.
As we guard and stay with our true nature,
our delusions are cut off.
We will have no deluded thoughts.
And because of that,
we will have right thoughts,
right mindfulness.
For example,
if a mother,
her teenage son hasn't come home late at night,
she might be having a lot of wandering thoughts,
thinking he got into an accident or being robbed.
But all these
are not the right thoughts.
Someone is enlightened,
will stay calm and peaceful
without having suspicions and wandering thoughts.
And because we have right thoughts,
then we have this wisdom
of silence and illumination.
We can see everything clearly
without having emotional turmoil.
Because of the wisdom
and because we realize our true nature,
that is Nirvana.
So all these
is because
we are guarding the original true mind.
In the Shravagama Sutra,
Guanyin Bodhisattva says,
I entered the flow through hearing
and forgot all objective states.
He entered the flow of Nirvana,
or enlightenment,
by hearing.
When he hears,
he does not hear the sounds,
not the object of hearing
and what is being heard.
He only stays with his true nature.
That is how we reach Nirvana.
It's all through guarding our mind
and we can do it through
guarding our six senses.
Number two,
how do we know
guarding the original true mind
is the key to entering the way?
How do we enter the way to Buddhahood?
Again,
it's through guarding the original true mind.
If one paints the image
of a Buddha with all their power
and create lots of merits
like the sands of Ganges River,
these are only ways for Buddha
to teach our wise sentient beings
so they will create good karmas
for the future
and to plant crosses
to see Buddha in the future.
But these are not the right way.
The only way is to guard
our original true mind.
If one wants to reach Buddhahood earlier,
one would guard the original true mind.
If a person does not guard
the original true mind
and becomes a Buddha,
there is no such thing.
In conclusion,
take the mind in one place
and nothing can be accomplished.
Discipline the mind
so it listens to our order
like a servant.
We should be the owner,
the master of our mind.
So it does whatever we want it to do.
We think thoughts
that are positive,
that are good,
that are not deluded.
We are in control of our mind.
So train this mind
so it stays in one place.
Where is this place?
That is the original true mind.
That's the only place to be
in this peace and blissfulness state
that is silent and still.
If our mind can always stay constant
in this one place,
nothing can not be accomplished.
We can accomplish anything
when we have this meditative absorption.
We have focus,
we have concentration,
we have wisdom.
There is nothing you cannot do.
For example,
if you want to pray for a sick person
by chanting the Buddha's name
or the great compassion mantra
or sutra,
you give the merit to them,
you believe they will get the merit
and heal this person completely.
Number three,
how do we know guarding the original true mind
is the core of the 12 sutras?
The 12 sutras have different types of sutras.
Some are verses,
some are narratives,
some are past life accounts.
Different kinds of sutras
Buddha is trying to teach us
about sense and blessings,
about all the karmic causalities
and retributions
through boundless metaphors
to let us know our different desires,
create different things
of the world.
Buddha is trying to teach us
about one vehicle,
the single vehicle,
that our mind is the Buddha.
Our Buddha nature
is like the sun behind the clouds.
So if one clearly understands this
and always guards the original true mind,
the delusion cloud is eliminated
and the wisdom sun appears.
When you really guard the mind
and it's not really about
the sutra anymore.
When we have this wisdom,
why do we need more knowledge
about life and death
and all the principles of the sutra?
It's like a mirror.
When the dust is completely removed,
brightness will shine naturally.
We don't need to do anything else anymore.
If we carry an elusive mind
to learn a lot of sutra,
then that is still useless.
Always have the right thoughts
and be in a state of inactive mind.
That is true learning.
There's actually nothing else to learn
because both the I and Nirvana
are empty in nature
and it's already the original true mind.
Number four,
how do we know guarding
the original true mind
is the father of all the Buddhas
of the three times?
All Buddhas are born from mind nature,
original true mind.
If we can guard the original true mind first,
then we will not generate any delusive thoughts.
If delusive thoughts are not generated,
the duality of the mind is eliminated.
Then you can become a Buddha.
When we guard our true mind,
we will not have any delusive thoughts.
We will have no dualism in our mind.
The subject of the thinker
and the object we are thinking about
disappear.
Then we are really with our true nature.
That's when we become a Buddha.
Buddha is not elsewhere.
It's just when you are guarding
who you really are.
How do we know if we are staying
with our original true mind?
You can test yourself.
If you hear a great news about a person
who has harmed you,
undermined you,
insulted you,
and you feel a sense of sting
in your heart or sizzling,
that means you are still not there.
Our mind needs to be completely pure,
completely perfect,
full of love and joy.
If we are contaminated in our mind,
we are not guarding it.
Nobody can annoy you or hurt you
or come into your mind.
Do not give your power away to anybody
or anything.
Nothing can come into your life
except when you are giving them power.
So always guard and protect your mind.
Guard the original true mind.
Then you will reach nirvana.
You will enter the way.
You will understand all sutras.
And you will really reach Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.