Today we are going to talk about One Mind.
This is from The Awakening of Faith in Mahayana by Bodhisattva Asvangosha.
This is a masterpiece that combines 100 Mahayana sutras into one concise structure.
It talks about our pure mind.
In the beginning, he said, may all sentient beings be made to discard all their doubts
and to cast aside their evil attachment and to give rise to the correct faith in Mahayana.
So the lineage of Buddha may not be broken off.
He wrote this sutra for this reason.
He wants us to get rid of all our doubts about our true nature and to cast away our attachment
to this deluded mind so we can have true correct faith in our own Buddha nature.
We call it the Mahayana.
We will have a brief overview about this sutra in this class.
First, let's talk about this sutra as a whole.
The One True Mind.
It has two aspects.
One is the aspect of absolute.
Two is the aspect of the phenomena.
This is the suchness, the true mind.
This is the life of our mundane that is in samsara.
We want to get out of this life and to live in our enlightened mind, the true Buddha nature.
The suchness.
So let's first look at this absolute mind.
It has two aspects.
One is the non-verbal suchness.
Two is verbal suchness.
This suchness, you cannot describe it.
That's why it's non-verbal.
But if you really have to describe it, we can describe it in this way.
Let's first talk about how it's non-verbal.
It transcends all verbalization.
Description and conceptualization.
It is what it is, that's why it's called suchness.
You can say one world of reality and the essence of all phases of existence in their totality.
Our one mind is the only world.
But we think the physical world we live in is the real world.
But only the world of the mind is the reality.
we call it the one world of reality. It's the essence of all different kinds of existence.
The ten dharma rounds, there's only one round, the mind of the Buddha, which is our own mind.
So all existence in their totality, the whole universe is this mind that cannot be described
in words. If we predicate on words, we would call it the verbal suchness. In terms of two
aspects, it's truly empty, yet it's truly not empty. It's truly empty because this suchness
is empty of all existence. Human beings cannot be enlightened because we have two problems.
First, we think there is a real self. Two, we think everything in the world is real.
That's our attachment to the self and attachment to all dharmas, which means all things. The
true dharma is the one that is not empty. The true dharma is the one that is not empty.
The true dharma is the one that is not empty. The true dharma is the one that is not empty.
Truly emptiness is describing suchness is really empty of self and empty of all things.
If we can detach from the self and detach from all worldly things, thinking is real,
we can be empty of all dharmas. That is the true nature of the absolute mind.
If you want to talk about it in its conventional existence, you would say it is truly
non-empty as well. It has conventional existence. It's provincial. We still live in this world.
So we still need to see how this mind is endowed with numerous excellent qualities. It is eternal,
permanent, immutable, pure, and self-sufficient. You can say it is eternal. It doesn't have
rising or ceasing. It lasts forever. It doesn't matter which realm you are in. It doesn't matter
how many reincarnations you go through. It is permanent because it is not impermanent
like all the conditions arising. Immutable, it is not moved by any life situation. A
true mind is not affected like our emotion by all the life circumstances. It is also
pure. Never been soiled by any of your human experiences which means it has no se with
to begin with is self-sufficient it's always satisfied because innately we are
always perfect we're always pure in our goodness so know your goodness you
really have this truly non-empty suchness but how come we are not right
here all the time right now we still live a mundane life because we living in
the phenomenon world which is the samsara we will talk about what is
non-enlightenment and what is enlightenment we have original
enlightenment basically is the suchness but our mind become agitated it start
moving it becomes non-enlightened we start discriminating with the sense of
the self we become deluded then we start learning Buddhism we think
that we are not right we are not right we are not right we are not right we are not right
there's a way out of this non-enlightened mind so we start
cultivating this is called the process of actualization of enlightenment
finally at the end we will reach the final enlightenment there are four kinds
of enlightenment what is original enlightenment two is non-enlightenment
three is process of actualization of enlightenment
lastly is final enlightenment
we're using the deluded mind we call it the Alaya consciousness this is the
non enlightened mind but we actually have an original enlightened mind and
this original enlightened mind it has two aspects one is in relation to defiled
state two is pure essence in relation to its defiled state which means we have
the ability to overcome all our afflictions and all our defilements
because we have purity of wisdom and we actually have super rational functions
purity of wisdom that's when we actually have non-conceptual knowledge of all
things we can live without discriminating learning Buddhism is to
practice insight meditation so we don't discriminate as much
we're awakened we're aware of what's going on without conceptualization that
is our purity of wisdom we call it fundamental non-conceptual knowledge
that's what we want to reach you live in the state without a lot of
conceptualization as when the self would be empty then we have suprarational
functions if we are empty of the self then we will be empty of the
damage and then there is no healthy self so if we have a transgenerational
Dharma will have the ability to help all other sentient beings to become enlightened. Because
we are naturally endowed with excellent qualities. Every day it will be miraculous. You can help
a lot of people in your life. Just be there at the right moment, at the right time, tell
people the right Dharma and they will be enlightened. Because we have this supernatural power. Only
if we have this non-conceptual knowledge. So do not use this thinking mind, but use
our true nature to live this life. So the purity of wisdom is called fundamental non-conceptual
knowledge. The suprarational function is called the subsequent non-conceptual knowledge. One
is fundamental, one is subsequent. We have both of these innate in us.
But we need to deal with our afflictions in relation to our defiled states. Then this
original enlightenment has its pure essence. It is actually described as a perfect round
mirror. We turn the whole alaya consciousness, the deluded mind into the great perfect round
mirror wisdom. Here it has four kinds of mirrors. One is the mirror empty of images. The mirror
is empty. It is free in essence. The mirror is empty of all the images. First we need
to understand all the images in the mirror is empty in essence. Everything is truly empty.
The mirror is empty of all marks of appearances. Everything appears in your life. There are
only images in the mirror. A mirror knows not to be attached to whatever that's happening
reflected in the mirror. It stays perfect. Unmoved by the pains and sores of life, it
is always an unmoving mirror. It is everywhere. It is always open. It is always healthy, it's
happiness and sadness of your life that is the perfect mirror then it's the
mirror influencing toward enlightenment now it's talking about how it's truly
not empty all the images in front of mirror is for us to use it's not empty
because it influences advancing toward enlightenment you use your life
situation to be a bodhisattva and to help others to reach enlightenment this
is truly empty this is truly not empty then we have the third mirror mirror
free from defiled objects we use the Dharma and this purity of wisdom that's
why we are free from hindrance both in our afflictions and in our intellect we
should be free from all of this
our defilements of the self and free from our discriminating intellect this
is the mirror that is not tainted in any way we use the Dharma to renunciate from
samsara by changing our non-enlightened state lastly the mirror influencing one
to cultivate goodness so the mirror free from defiled objects that's our purity
of wisdom
the mirror influencing one to cultivate goodness that's our suprarational
functions now whatever appears in our mirror is helping us and helping
everyone to become enlightened to bring out our capacity for goodness we are now
happily living in this world cultivating all the goodness and to help all sentient
beings there's actually no hindrances in your
mind there's actually no hindrances in your mind there's actually no hindrances in your mind
all the deluded mind has no validity be substantiated the deluded mind never existed
in the first place there's a fourth patriarch of Zen Buddhism his name is
Dao-Sing when he was 14 years old he visited the third Patriarch Seng Chan when he
arrived he asked master please teach me a way to Liberation the master said who is
tying you down?" He thought about it for a while. Nobody, nothing is tying me down.
Then the master said, why do you need a method of liberation? What do you need to
liberate from? At that moment he became fully enlightened at the age of 14. So
who is tying you down? Why are you living a suffering life not enlightened? Because
we are caught up in our deluded mind, but we don't have to live this way. Now
let's look at non-enlightenment – our non-enlightened state. The deluded mind
we're using, it has nine aspects – three subtle aspects and six cruel aspects.
The three subtle aspects, that's from our enlightened consciousness. The six claro
aspects is from our sixth consciousness.
thinking mind. This is the storage. This is the thinking mind. The storage house, the
alaya, we will naturally become agitated. It has three aspects. First is the
activity of ignorance. The mind is agitated. It becomes ignorant. That's why
it's called activity of ignorance. Then it will develop the second aspect,
perceiving subject. Then we will have the third aspect, the world of object. Because
our mind is agitated, it starts moving. We create a perceiving mind and we create
the world of the object. Both the subject and the object are created by your
alaya consciousness. That's why we said everything is an illusion. It's only
created by the mind.
By your deluded mind. The world you see and the mind that is interpreting the
world, they're all from your own alaya consciousness. Then we will have the
three cruel aspects. When we face life situations, we naturally will be defiled.
First, we will have a discriminating intellect. For example, someone is
yelling at you, insulting you. So your like and dislike will discriminate.
Against the situation. In this case, you dislike someone insulting you.
Number two is the aspect of continuity. You will keep thinking about it because this event
is giving you pain or pleasure. In this case, it's pain. And you keep thinking about it,
you cannot fall asleep. It's really disrupting to your life. The third aspect is the aspect
of attachment.
Now you're super attached to this dislike.
You are very upset.
You really dislike the situation.
Number four, you will give it aspect of speculation of names and letters.
You will assign a label, this person is evil, he's mean, he's my enemy, I hate him.
Now he's attached to this name and label.
Number five is the aspect of giving rise to karma.
You will talk back or you will hit this person.
You will give rise to bodily actions.
Then that becomes karma.
Lastly, it's the aspect of suffering.
Because you produce karma, you will have related suffering based on your anger, malicious words,
or your actions.
You will have the negative karma.
Now you have to suffer the consequences of your mind.
So every situation, you will have negative karma.
Any situation, we think like this.
We go through the three subtle aspects and we go through the six cruel aspects.
That's why we are always non-enlightened.
So what do we do now?
It's to catch yourself at the earlier stage of the cruel aspects or even at the subtle
aspects.
Catch yourself early, when you are attaching name, when you're upset and eat comprar.
upset when you are having negative thoughts the sooner you catch it the sooner you will be out
of samsara every day you become a little more enlightened this is everyday practice everyday
cultivation you want to reduce our non-enlightened deluded mind and have our purity of wisdom and
suprarational function come out you have to let go of your deluded thoughts your false thinking
so the trick is have faith in the mahayana how should i live this life should i keep living this
life in the six crew aspect and the three subtle aspects repeat the same pattern of thinking or do
i want to get out of samsara i need to change my thinking pattern i need to have non-conceptual
knowledge
stop discriminating and start living in the true suchness bodhisattva asangosha
explained the absolute aspect and the phenomena aspect
they are mutually inclusive they are one of the same you cannot be away from the phenomenon
to see the absolute and you cannot live in the absolute without the phenomenon so they are
mutually the same
same. We only have one mind that is without any differentiation and it's
without any alteration. It is only the existence of the one mind. There was a
monk who has been holding precepts for all his life, pure precepts. So one day he
was walking on the street at night. All of a sudden he stepped on something, feels
like a live frog. He went home and he could not sleep that night because he
thought he broke the precept of no killing. In the morning he woke up, he
went to the same spot and looked for the frog. Little did he know, wow it was
only a very right eggplant. He realized the world of the object is only created
by the mind. Nothing really existed except what is experienced in your own
mind.
He realized I have a strong self because I think I am the one holding pure
precept and he has strong attachment to the Dharma because he thinks holding
precept is the most important thing. So he did not understand the empty of the
self and empty of all Dharma. We need to really awaken our faith in our true
suchness.
When Gosha wrote this shastra, it's so that all sentient beings would be free from
suffering of their deluded mind and to reach ultimate bliss. We can all get out of
samsara and reach enlightenment and be aligned with our suchness. So samsara or
nirvana, you get to choose.
So that's the class for today. Thank you.
Thank you for listening. Amitabha.