Today we are going to talk about mind over matter.
Our mind creates the physical world, we call it matter.
If we can change our mind, then we can change the physical world.
According to the consciousness-only school of Buddhism, it says we have eight consciousnesses.
We have the eyes consciousness, ears, nose, tongue, and body.
These five come into direct contact with the outside world.
These five have minimal ability to perceive the outside world.
They have to work with the sixth consciousness, the mind consciousness,
in order to have cognitive function.
Unfortunately, this mind consciousness is controlled by the seventh consciousness,
the manas consciousness, which is full of the self, the ego.
The manas consciousness is infatuated with the alaya consciousness, thinking that is the self.
This is how we experience the world.
Unfortunately, this is a deluded mind.
If we can transform our consciousness into wisdom,
then it's the true Buddha nature, our true suchness.
But little do we know that this alaya consciousness is the same as our true Buddha nature.
It's one of the same thing.
It's just one is deluded, one is enlightened.
It's just in different states, but it's the same mind.
Therefore, we need to understand how to transform the deluded state right now.
First, we have to realize that the mind is the same as the alaya consciousness.
Second, we have to realize that all the consciousnesses are ignorant.
They're deluded.
The alaya consciousness is called the basic ignorance.
It's the big warehouse that carries us through all our lives of reincarnation.
You can call it the soul.
That's our big root, ignorance.
It's the opposite of the secondary ignorance, the sixth consciousness.
This thinking mind is only secondary
because it's easier to see, easier to change the mind consciousness.
But it's harder to realize the existence of the profound and subtle alaya consciousness.
That's why this is basic and this is secondary.
This is like brooding the tree from its root.
This is like breaking up the branches of the tree.
What we need to do is completely wake up from the dream, the whole life that
we're having is a big illusion. To know illusion is to depart from it. To depart from it is
to be enlightened. If we just wake up and know that this is all a dream, then it's the
original enlightenment. The modest consciousness is called the unmixed ignorance. This ignorance
doesn't have to mix with any other consciousness. It's very distinct and particular. It doesn't
need to have other afflictions. It's naturally ignorant. That's why it's called unmixed
ignorance. So all of them are ignorant in nature. This alaya consciousness has three
names. The first name is store consciousness. It's a big storehouse. Whatever we have done
in all our lives is stored in here. What we think every day gets stored in this storehouse
as karmic.
You call it seeds or you call it karmic energies. All your wholesome, unwholesome and neutral
deeds are all stored in here. When the condition ripens, the seeds develop into a real world.
All the matter is created by the alaya consciousness. The seeds, they will manifest into our reality.
We do not know that all realities are only images created by our alaya consciousness.
Therefore, we think it's real and our mind attached to them. And we're suffering delusions
and afflictions because of the outside environment. The second name is called appropriating consciousness.
This consciousness appropriates all our sense organs. So our body will not perish as long
as we are living. Even when you're sleeping, this consciousness is carrying our body through
so we stay alive. At the moment of our death, it appropriates us into our next life. When
parents are consummating, it attaches itself to the egg and the sperm. That's how you develop
into a new life. It's all because of this appropriating consciousness.
Lastly, it's called the mind. This mind accumulates. You have many, many habits accumulated from
your prior lifetimes.
You don't even know. But if you like to meditate this lifetime, it's because you meditated in
your prior lifetimes. If you see an insect, you like to kill it, that's because you've
done it many, many lifetimes. So you're used to it. We carry many, many habits from our
prior lifetimes. That's why it's called the accumulating mind. So the existence of this
alaya consciousness is the basis of Buddhism.
That's what reincarnation is. And that is what cause and condition is. If we can understand
the existence of alaya, then we know how to change our lives and get out of reincarnation.
The alaya is neutral. Whatever you put in it, it carries with it. But the manas, it's
naturally defiled because it's full of the self. It naturally has four afflictions all
the time.
Number one is self-view.
Number two is self-divine. Number three is self-divine. Number four is self-divine. Number
five is self-divine. Number six is self-divine. Number seven is self-divine.
When you're doing wholesome deeds, unwholesome deeds or neutral deeds, it doesn't matter
what you're doing, you always have this idea of the self. When you're doing good deeds,
you want people to praise you. You want people to affirm this ego. We always carry this idea
of the self. It's always present. We also have the self pride. We think we are special.
We're better than others. Even a dog, even an ant, we think we're better than others.
the ant, even pigs, they are proud of their appearance. Then we have self-love. We're always
protecting ourselves, protecting this body, protecting our reputation, our family. We love
the self. That's the only thing we really love. And we also have self-ignorance. We're ignorant
about the self because we think we have a self. That's the biggest ignorance. These four afflictions
are with our manas all the time. That's why it's always defiled. The mind consciousness is the
only one that goes outside and experience the world. Because we're attached to the external
world, the conditions, we start having afflictions. I listed the six basic afflictions. In favorable
conditions, we become greedy. We want it to happen again and again. In unfavorable conditions,
we become angry, bitter. We have resentment, irritation. That's all anger. We also have
ignorance. This ignorance is the same as the self-ignorance except the affliction in the
seventh manas is inborn. But the mind consciousness ignorance is acquired. It's acquired from
your education, your society, your belief system. So the sixth consciousness is more
acquired affliction. And we have arrogance. That's the same as self-pride. Except this
is inborn, this is acquired. And we have doubts. Deep down inside, we never believe our mind
is the Buddha nature. No matter how much we learn about the sutra, we never believe we
are the Buddha. If you really believe in it, then you will be enlightened already because
your mind is already the Buddha. But we have doubts.
So that is also a strong affliction. We also have false views. The biggest false view is
the view of the self. So it's the same as the self-view. Except this is inborn, this
is acquired. So we have all these afflictions in our mind consciousness. When we have these
afflictions, these afflictions, it becomes unwholesome deeds and it permeates into seeds
in the laya consciousness.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
And then ripens into resolve. And so it's a big reincarnation. So if you want to talk
about reincarnation, it all happens in our consciousness. It's a big vicious cycle.
The key of learning Buddhism is to change this consciousness. Because that's the only
thing we can really change. Our thinking. If we change this, then everything will change.
We got to be careful of every one of our thoughts. Because every one of our thoughts
is stored in here. We will have karma. Be careful what you think about. It all have
consequences. We need to change greed into generosity. Anger into compassion. Ignorance
into wisdom. Arrogance into humility. Doubt into faith. False view into right view. Watch
every one of our thoughts and change our afflictions. That's how you purify.
Your laya consciousness. Every moment you're thinking, you are changing your laya consciousness.
Destiny is in your hand. Right now we have a big earthquake in Turkey. That is our collective
deeds, our collective karma in our laya consciousness. We are all responsible for this disaster.
Of course, everyone has different level of karmic sea with this event. But we are all
responsible.
What we need to do is to repent. Earthquake comes from our pride, our uneven mind. We
got to watch our thoughts. That's the only way to improve the world. If we purify our
laya consciousness, we will realize the laya consciousness is our true Buddha nature. The
suchness. All the ignorance now is the original enlightenment. It's no longer ignorant. We
have the pure mind. This mind is actually eternal. It never changes, no matter how many
reincarnation we've been through. It's always the same. And it's always permanent. No matter
what happens in the outside world, your Buddha nature is permanent. It's the same. And it's
immutable, it's not affected by any of your afflictions. None of your afflictions affect
your true nature. And it's natural. Only true Buddha nature. So stay with me and watch next.
and it's always pure, it doesn't have the idea of the self, it has no afflictions, and it's self-sufficient.
We have perfect wisdom, perfect compassion, and we can be omniscient like Buddha,
if we really go back to our true perfect nature.
Ching Yuen Master, he has established more than 300 temples throughout the world.
He helped save millions of people to learn Buddhism through his words, through his action.
He was very sick in his old age, but he said,
I am not sick, I just have little inconvenience. He worked all his life and never felt tired.
That is a Bodhisattva. He has no delusion and no limitation in his mind.
So believe in ourselves and change our destiny for the better. It's really mind over matter.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.