Today we are going to talk about
Liao Fan's fourth lesson, the second lesson.
Last time we talked about how Liao Fan changed his life.
And now we're going to talk about the second lesson.
Exactly what do you do to change your life?
There's actually ways to change your life for the better.
So the second lesson is ways to reform.
How do we reform?
You want prosperity, happiness, good thing to happen to you.
You got to have the cause to have the effect.
So this tells us exactly what to do.
First, you have to reform.
That means change your balls and mistakes.
First, we have to admit it.
All the bad things that happened to us today
is because of bad things that we did.
Either this life or prior lifetime
or anything that we did before.
That's why we are having this life we're experiencing right now.
If we're poor, because we did not give in our prior lifetimes.
If we don't have good relationship,
that is because we did something bad to people in their prior lifetime.
So if we don't want the bad things
to continue, we got to change our way to be virtuous.
Fate and destiny is in your hands.
You can do everything to change your life.
There are four parts to today's reform.
First is three ways of reform.
And there are three methods of reforming.
If your reform has been successful,
there are signs you're doing right.
And there are signs you're still having a lot of offenses and bad deeds.
In order to change our life and change our mistakes,
the first is feeling ashamed.
Reflect on my fault.
A lot of people don't even think they're doing anything wrong.
At first you have to realize,
oh, I'm kind of lazy, you know, that's why I'm not doing well.
I want to lose weight, but I didn't eat a lot of chocolate.
You don't know what you're doing wrong.
You have to reflect, how come Buddha can be a Buddha?
He started like a normal person, just like us, with many faults.
But he changed his way.
How come he's able to do that?
And we're still mundane.
Person.
First, feel shameful.
When you feel shameful, you can change.
I don't know if you guys heard of this guy, his name is Nick.
He was born with no arms and no legs.
But he can do everything that we're doing.
And he even can swim, he can do all the sports.
And now he's 30, 40, and he's making speeches everywhere.
Giving motivational speeches to all the young people.
Telling them how to live a good life and never give up.
He said, I have no arms and no legs and no worries.
We should be shameful.
He can be happy.
How come we can't?
We're still having so much trouble and so much difficulty in our life.
So we should first feel ashamed of ourselves.
Second, we want to feel fear.
What do we mean by fear?
Fear means feeling respect.
When you're by yourself or you think nobody knows,
or the Buddha and all the spirits are watching us.
Don't think of evil thoughts.
Or pick a nose.
Or the things that you will not do in front of people.
Because the gods are watching us.
So everything that you're doing is recorded.
And all the good things will have good fortune.
All the bad things will have bad results.
So don't think nobody knows.
Live every day as if all the gods are watching you all the time.
So be good all the time.
So there's a story.
Two people, they think they're talking by themselves, nobody knows.
And first they were talking about all the good things.
They're talking about Dharma.
So all the heavenly beings, they came by and watching them.
You know, talking about all the good things.
After a while, because of their bad habits, they start gossiping.
And all the heavenly beings left.
After a while, they start saying even worse things.
All the evil gods, they come by and they actually spit on them.
All the gods and all the deities and all the spirits,
they know exactly what we're doing.
So be good all the time.
Even when you're alone.
That is a way to cultivate and become good.
So that's the second way of reform.
The third way is determination.
You want to be successful, you have to be determined.
I want to change my way from today on.
How come we want to go on a diet, quit smoking, not be angry, and we can't do it?
What's the reason?
Because we're always giving ourselves a lot of excuses.
Uh-oh, I'll do this later.
Because of this and that, because of other people.
We have a lot of excuses.
That's why we can't reform.
So you got to do it right away.
I hear about this book today, from today on.
I'm going to reform, I'm going to change my way.
There is a man, he was only 20.
He learned how to be virtuous.
He said, oh, I got to change my way.
He tried really hard every day to change his way,
but he still felt like he's not doing enough.
He kept changing, kept changing, kept changing,
till he was 50.
And he still thinks he's not doing enough.
He still has a lot of faults and mistakes, you know, offenses.
And so he keeps changing, keeps changing.
All the saints and all the sages said this is a great man
who knows how to change himself
because he's constantly aware of his thoughts and changing.
So we got to be determined for you to really have any kind of reform in your life.
Okay, so that's the third way to reform.
There are three methods of reform.
First is changing.
Change through behavior.
If I don't want to smoke, then I just cut down how many cigarettes every day.
You know, I cut it down.
So I change by the actual behavior.
I force myself.
I can't smoke every day.
You know, I cut it down.
So I change by the actual behavior.
I force myself.
I can't smoke.
No more chocolate.
No more cake.
No more sweet.
I force myself.
I don't get angry.
I won't be mad at anyone.
I force myself.
But that is only temporary.
So the second way is changing through reasoning.
If you know the reason, then you will be able to change.
For example, smoking is really bad for your health.
Or getting angry is not necessary because when someone is slandering about you.
If he's right, I should change my ways.
If he's wrong, why should I be angry?
I shouldn't even listen, right?
If you know the reasoning,
there's no point being upset.
And there's no point smoking.
No point eating a lot of junk food, right?
So if you know the logic behind it, then you are likely to reform forever.
The third is the ultimate way.
It's changing from the heart.
We have numerous mistakes, right?
If you change one at a time, it takes a long time.
But if you just change from the heart because everything stems from your heart.
If you just change your heart
to be pure and virtuous,
you will have no more offenses,
you have no more mistakes,
you have no more faults
because your heart is constantly still and peaceful
and you're not having a lot of thoughts, okay?
So this is like meditation.
Your heart is very calm and your mind is clear.
You're not likely to do a lot of bad things or have faults.
So that's changing from the heart.
If you really want to reform,
you need to do all these three ways.
If you combine them,
then you can change yourself for the better.
There are signs of you actually being successful.
You will feel these things.
These things will happen to you.
First, you will naturally feel light and generous.
You have a good mood.
Nothing is happening, but you feel very joyful.
You have a good mood all the time, okay?
And the second one is because of all the good things and virtues,
you become wise all the time.
You kind of know everything.
You kind of know what I should do with everything.
And without any confusion.
And the third is relaxed in turmoil.
When a lot of bad things happening,
it's very hectic,
you're still very relaxed, calm.
Even when there's a lot of trouble around you,
you still feel peaceful and you're not moved.
The fourth is you're happy seeing an enemy.
Usually we see an enemy,
we are very angry or we try to hide
or we pretend we're nice, but we're not.
But when you really reform,
even when seeing someone you don't like,
you are genuinely sincere and happy
and treat him like a loved one.
That means you have really changed yourself
to be able to see an enemy and be happy.
The fifth is dream of spitting black things, okay?
A lot of these are dreams.
You will notice in your dreams
you spit out black things.
Black things means offenses, bad things.
In your dream, you're actually spitting out black stuff.
That means all your bad things are gone.
You're starting anew.
So seeing yourself spitting out bad things,
that's good.
The sixth is dream of past sages.
Sometimes in your dreams,
you might see Jesus or you can see Buddha
or you can see someone very virtuous
and encourage you.
That is a very good sign.
That means you have become a virtuous person.
So that's the sixth one.
The seventh one is when you dream of flying.
Flying is good.
That means you're free of offenses and evil darkness.
And the eighth is dream of pennies and canopies.
All the decorated pretty stuff like we have here,
that means you are having an auspicious life.
That's a good sign.
All the pretty and beautiful things
that's decorative in your life
that you dream of them, okay?
So these are the good signs of that you have reformed.
But there are also bad signs.
Pretty much they're the opposite.
When you're not doing well
or you're actually not really reforming
and you're still going out with your old ways,
this is what will happen to you.
First, feeling confused and oppressed.
You have no energy.
You're like, oh, every day I'm sluggish
and I don't know what I'm doing.
That means you have a lot of offenses.
Secondly, you can be very forgetful.
You forget your keys.
You forget all your work.
You don't know where you left it
because you're very confused.
The third is worrying about nothing.
Nothing is going on.
You're just sitting at home.
But you're very worried about everything.
Nothing is happening, but you're worried.
That is also a sign of offense.
The fourth is embarrassing virtuous people.
When someone is virtuous,
you don't want to see the person
because, you know, you feel shameful.
You don't want the other person to see you.
And the fifth is displeased with proper teaching.
When you hear good teaching, you're not interested.
You don't want to listen
because you don't want to reform.
And the sixth,
when kind, receive hostility.
When you have a lot of offenses,
you're kind to others.
Other people treat you badly.
Even if you give people presents,
they're mad at you.
That means you're not doing too well nowadays
because people naturally don't like you.
And then the seventh,
you have a lot of nightmares.
Having a lot of nightmares,
upside down and all kinds of dark stuff
or you're not flying, you're falling.
That means you're doing a lot of bad things.
And the last one,
talk incoherently.
You don't know what you're saying.
You're saying like random things.
Your speech and your behavior is not normal.
A lot of these interesting signs
that you can tell if you're doing good
or you're doing bad.
From now on,
after you hear of this Lao Fanzhou lesson,
what we do is we are positive
and we are very active
in changing our life for the better.
Do all that is good
and get rid of all our bad habits
and our mistakes and our offenses.
So the next class,
we're going to talk about
how to cultivate good deeds.
So this is to reform
and the next chapter,
we're going to really do all the good deeds.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.