Today we are going to talk about one thought three thousand rounds, which means one instant
of thought has three thousand rounds imminent within it.
In this class we will talk about how our mind is the three thousand rounds.
First let's look at the ten dharma rounds, there are ten places that we can be in.
From the bottom there is hell, which is full of suffering and torment.
Number two, hungry ghosts, they are cursed with insatiable hunger.
Number three, the animal round, they are full of ignorance, just eat and sleep all day long
and they are content with it.
These are the three lower rounds.
Then we have number four, asura round, they do good deeds but they are jealous and belligerent
in nature.
Number five, humans, we are the only round that can be enlightened but we are burdened
with desires and doubts.
Number six is heavenly beings, they are always wealthy, happy and have very long lives.
These are the three higher rounds, these consist of the six rounds of reincarnation.
But if we cultivate, we can go up to the four rounds of the sages.
Number seven is shravaka and number eight, pratyata buddha, these two, they are self-enlightened
beings.
They have strong renunciation to get out of the reincarnation so they let go of all afflictions,
so they are self-enlightened.
Then we have number nine, bodhisattva, not only do they want self-enlightenment, they
want to enlighten others, so they are full of compassion and want to deliver all other
sentient beings.
Lastly, we have buddha, who has perfect supreme enlightenment.
These are the ten places that we can be in, they are mutually eminent and mutually inclusive.
One round consists of the other rounds.
For example, if I am an animal, I can be full of love for others and always let others eat
first, then I am a bodhisattva in the animal round.
So these are all inclusive.
Each ten rounds has ten features related to them.
We call it ten features of thusness or suchness.
We will use hell and buddha as contrasting examples.
Number one, exorcism.
Number two, the third round.
Every round has their own forms, their outer appearances.
Hell beings, their forms are full of suffering and torment.
They are always in punishment, in presence of boiling water, ice, fire, and their body
can be torn into pieces, so they are always in pain and suffering.
In contrast, buddha, their form is a conditioned cause of buddha nature.
They are full of goodness and merit.
Number three.
Deer, they carry their own virgins and their own spirits.
Number two is their inner essence.
Everybody has their personality.
The hell beings, their essence is full of anger.
They are always upset, complaining, full of bitterness.
In contrast, buddha, their essence is called the enlightened cause of buddha nature.
It's their perfect wisdom.
So wisdom is buddha's essence.
Number three, substance.
Substance is basically a combination of form and essence.
Or you can call it, wisdom or wisdom.
So wisdom is buddha's essence.
Number three.
we call body and mind the helping their substance is deteriorating body and mind because they're
always in degradation on the other hand buddha's substance is their direct cause of buddha nature
the body of buddha is their suchness we call it the buddha body so they have totally different
form essence and substance then we have number four forces every round have their own energy
for example how beings they have the energy of repetitive suffering they go through a punishment
they die a small breeze blows by they wake up and start experiencing the punishment again they never
die so that's their life force buddha's life force is their bodhisattva vow they want to save
their life force buddha's life force is their bodhisattva vow they want to save
all sentient beings that's their energy just like the earth treasure bodhisattva
his vow is i want to save all sentient beings out of hell or i will not become a buddha
he wants to save the most painful sentient beings so bodhisattva's vow is their energy number five
is action every round has its action or functions hell beings their action is a wholesome
action that's why they're in the lower realm buddha set precepts for us the precepts are not
for him it's to protect us so we don't go to the unfavorable rounds buddha's actions is their six
parameters they like to be giving and hold precepts and be patient especially bodhisattvas
are always giving there is a lady in taiwan she sells vegetables for a living and she accumulates
a lot of money and donated millions of dollars to the needy just by selling vegetables so bodhisattvas
loves to give that's their action number six main causes for the hell beings their main causes
is their unwholesome deeds such as killing stealing and sexual misconduct buddha's causes
are the adornment of their perfect wisdom of the middle way which is their buddha nature
understanding everything that is conditioned existence is empty in essence number seven is
their supporting conditions if the hell things their conditions are their unwholesome craving
and clinging their delusions are their supporting conditions and the causes are their actual
karmic deeds the conditions the delusions are what's supporting the causes for buddhas
conditions are the adornment of their virtues and merits they have the ability to save all sentient
beings because of their merits number eight is effect effect is the habitual effect for
the hell beings they habitually have a lot of anger and resentment so that's the carryover
effect habitual effect from prior lifetimes for buddhas their effect is called anathara samyak
sambodhi that means supreme perfect enlightenment that's buddha's effect which is becoming
perfectly enlightened for retribution is where you really end up in which realm for the hell
beings their retribution is being in hell experiencing the punishment buddha's retribution
is called the mahaparin nirvana which means mahayana nirvana is another shravaka one-sided
nirvana that's a nirvana when you really attain buddhahood number 10 the ultimate state from
number one form essence all the way to number nine all these are conditioned existence and
their essence is emptiness that's the ultimate state the true state of all phenomena and that
is our buddha nature in essence that's why we call the ultimate state so this is telling us
no matter hell or buddha it's all in this one instant of thought which is your absolute mind
this is called the single vehicle so it's not three separate vehicles these are just expedient
ways that's the only thing buddha wanted to get across his only perspective is to let us know
that we all have the buddha nature just like him this is the entire universe and the entire universe
is in our one thought lastly we have the three worlds number one the world of living beings
every round has the people that they live with the hell beings they live with people in suffering
together and buddha they live with bhakti safa they are just full of compassion number two is
the world that beings live in that's the physical place for example the hell is full of steel and
middle. For Buddha, they live in the place of eternal, quenching light. That's the place of
formlessness. It only has the Buddha nature. Number three is the world of five skantas.
The hell beings, they have unwholesome five skantas. For Buddha, their skanta is emptiness,
but it's perfect in its emptiness. So the 3,000th round consists of 10 dharma rounds,
and in every dharma round, they include the other dharma round. So it's 10 times 10,
times the 10 features, times the three worlds. That's how we get to 3,000 rounds, or 3,000
worlds. These 3,000 worlds is all within our one thought, because our mind is the absolute
Buddha mind. This is the only thing that Buddha wanted to
let us know, that we are the Buddha to begin with. We're originally imminent with the
3,000 worlds. So that's the Tiantai Buddhism conveyed in the Lotus Sutra. So how do we
live this life right now? We just have to align ourselves with our absolute mind. If
we have a thought of anger, complaint, then we are in hell. If we have the thought of
loving kindness and compassion, then we are a Buddha. So it's all up to us. If we really
want to end the virus right now, all we have to do is align ourselves with our Buddha thoughts,
replace hatred and unwholesome thoughts with loving kindness and compassion. That's the
only way to solve any problem. So change the world one thought at a time. Lastly, I want
to share with you one of my favorite Dharma thoughts. The 3,000th round consists of 10
one of my favorite stories in buddha's time there was a very very poor lady she sustains her living
by begging for food and spare change one very cold night she was begging for food finally she
got one small coin at this moment she heard the townspeople say that they're giving light offering
to buddha she thought how much i wish i can make a light offering to buddha so she decided to use
this one small coin to buy the smallest amount of lamb oil to make light offering to buddha
when night time comes the whole city was illuminated with light offering to buddha amidst
the crowd is this poor lady she sincerely lit up her candle at that moment she felt this incredible
sense of richness and happiness she made a very sincere and compassionate vow made this light
guide all sentient beings out of the suffering of life and death and lead them to the path
of ultimate peace and happiness when morning came everybody's life were extinguished
except hers buddha's disciples they were all in art and buddha said to them this
life was led by a strong and sincere vow that's why it can never be extinguished
the poor lady
came into the temple and bowed to buddha buddha said to her in 20 kalpas you will become a buddha
and you will save immeasurable number of sentient beings your name will be called the lamb light
buddha so even though she was in hell she was very very poor but her mind was a buddha she had
a sincere bodhi resolve to save all sentient beings so at that moment she is a buddha and
she will become a buddha no matter how much suffering we are in don't be hopeless we are all
buddha at every moment in time if we just come back and align ourselves with our true nature
so that's the class for today thank you for listening amitabha