Today we are going to talk about Samadhi.
Samadhi means proper concentration or proper reception.
That means our mind is in total control.
We are the owner of our mind.
It is a state of absorption where our mind is brought into focus
and our mind is true, righteous and proper without any deviance or bias
and it is without any false thinking.
We are going to study the Sixth Patriarch Hui Nang Master's Platform Sutra
that talks about Samadhi.
He says in order to have complete wisdom
you must understand the two kinds of Samadhi
the Samadhi of one form and Samadhi of one conduct.
Let's first look at the Samadhi of one form.
If you do not dwell in forms anywhere
and do not give rise to hate or love
do not grasp or reject
and do not calculate advantage or disadvantage
protection and destruction while in the midst of forms
but instead remain tranquil, calm and yielding
then you will have achieved the Samadhi of one form.
Samadhi of one form is a wisdom
which means our mind do not dwell in any form.
That means the living situation
all the phenomena
when you are not attached to form
you are back to your essence
which is formless without any attachment.
Anytime, anywhere
we are in complete control
in charge of our emotion.
When situation comes
we do not give rise to love or hate
and we do not grasp or reject
any kind of situation
things or people.
It's not that we try to ignore anyone
but our mind should always be at peace
without these strong emotions
and strong discriminations
and we do not calculate advantages or disadvantages
do not be selfish
or have a strong form of the self
the Diamond Sutra
it says the Bodhisattva
should not dwell in any form when giving
when we give or help others
we do not think what is there for us
we do not remember the person that's giving
and the person that's receiving
and how much the offering is
so let go of all the attachment to form
that's when we would be at peace.
In the midst of any form
any living situation
we should remain tranquil, calm
and ill-being
so that's our natural state of mind
when we are in control
when we have the Samadhi
we will no longer be attached
to living situation
to your family, to your co-worker
to your friends, relatives
you still perform your duty
and do the best that you can
but you have no attachment
that's our proper state of mind
when it's at peace.
You probably heard this story
there are two men arguing
about a flag flapping in the wind
one says it is the wind that is moving
the other says no
it is the flag that is moving
a Zen monk came and said
neither the flag or wind is moving
it is the mind that moves
so when our mind moves
or is agitated
and it's not calm
it is giving its power away
to the situation
we are no longer in control
we are no longer the owner
of our mind
so Samadhi means
we are always in charge of our mind
we can think the thought
that we want to think
we can have the emotion
the feeling that we want to have
we are always in charge of our mind
so Samadhi in one form is wisdom
Samadhi of one conduct
is concentration
this is more understanding
the teaching of the Dharma
this is more about
the effectiveness
of your practice
now let's look at
the Samadhi of one conduct
in all places
whether walking, standing, sitting
or lying down
maintain a simple and straight mind
and attain the unmoving
bodhimata
and the true realization
of the pure land
this is called
the Samadhi of one conduct
in all life actions
walking, standing, sitting
or lying down
we should maintain
aware and mindful of our thought
our mind should be simple
and straightforward
the mind that is conniving
or pretending
or lying
that is not being straightforward
we should always have a pure mind
that is very sincere
our words, our appearance
and our heart should be the same
without any pretending
or putting on a mask
we should always be respectful
that is in alignment
with our true nature
and we want to attain
the unmoving bodhimata
that means our holy temple
the holy temple is not
in the other places
it is in our own mind
when our mind is at peace
that is the bodhimata
and it is the true realization
of the pure land
we all want to go to
Amitabha's pure land
but the pure land
means our pure mind
when our mind is pure
we create the pure land
when our mind is evil
we create the corrupt world
so it is all because of our mind
this is called cassation
our mind is the cause of all things
so we need to have the correct thought
the correct mind
which is the pure mind
that is our original
pure true mind
that is the samadhi
samadhi of one context
when we are walking
standing
sitting
and lying down
we know who is the person
that is walking
that is standing
that is sitting
or lying down
they are the function of our mind
through the function
we need to reflect back
to our essence
the essence of our mind
we chant the name Amitabha
all day long
when we are walking
standing
sitting or lying down
is to remind us
we are one with Amitabha
because we all have the same Buddha nature
so by chanting and reciting his name
we are bringing out our true nature
in the Sragama Sutra
it says to be in control of the six senses
and purify our thoughts
chanting is controlling our six senses
our eyes
ears
tongue
body
and mind
we collect it inward
chanting the name Amitabha
that is how our mind is purified
so we often say
when you drop a clear pearl
into the muddy water
the muddy water will turn clear
when we chant the name Amitabha
in a distracted mind
the mind will resonate the Buddha
so every time we chant
is to purify our mind
so it's no longer chaotic
and confused
in every action
we should be mindful of our true nature
by chanting and reciting
Amitabha Buddha's name
that is the samadhi of one conduct
which means in one alignment
with our true nature
this is the same as Buddha remembrance
samadhi
or we call it chanting
of single-mindedness
Patriarch Hui Nan says
one who perfects
the two forms of samadhi
is like the earth
in which the seeds are planted
buried into the ground
and they are being nourished
and is growing
ripening
and bearing fruit
this is the final verse
it says the my ground
contains all seeds
under the universal rain
they all sprout
sudden enlightenment
the flowers have bloomed
the Bodhi fruit itself
is self-fulfilling
our mind is the ground
that contains all seeds
the rain is the dharma
Hui Nan Master's dharma
is like the tiny rain
moisturizing the seed
the seed is like our Buddha nature
that is receiving the moisture
from the rain
when we reach
sudden enlightenment
it's like the flower blooming
so with enough
samadhi of one form
and samadhi of one conduct
we'll definitely reach
sudden enlightenment
it can be one instant
it can be one day
or it can be ten days
or ten years
when the time is right
and you accumulated enough effort
it will definitely bear fruit
the Bodhi fruit
is self-fulfilling
it is natural
because it is all within us
the two types of samadhi
they are innate in all of us
we are supposed to be
we are supposed to have
the right concentration
to be in control of our mind
at all times
there was a monk named
Large Beads Hui Hai Master
he wanted to visit Master Ma Zu
so he traveled a long way
when he arrived
Ma Zu Master asked him
where did you come from
Hui Hai answered
I came from the Da Yun Temple
in Yue Zhou
Ma Zu asked
what do you want here
Hui Hai answered
I'm seeking for the Buddha Dharma
Ma Zu answered
I don't have anything here
what Dharma do you want
what is the point of leaving home
not attending to your own treasure
Hui Hai asked
what treasure
Ma Zu answered
this person asking
is the treasure
everything is sufficient
there's nothing lacking
or shortcoming
it can be used freely
so why seek for it externally
just that one sentence
Hui Hai realized
certain enlightenment
so the person who is
walking
standing
sitting
lying down
is the Buddha
the mind is the Buddha
all we have to do is to
work diligently
work hard in our Samadhi
of one form
in combination with the Samadhi
of one conduct
one is wisdom
one is concentration
one is our understanding
one is our practice
if you combine the two
when the time is right
we will definitely attain
the wonderful Bodhi fruit
we will taste the wonderful fruit
of Bodhi
so that's the class today
thank you for listening
Amitabha