Today we are going to talk about enlightenment.
The way to enlightenment is ineffable.
Surpassing the path of language, all Buddhas are born from it, this dharma is hard to conceive.
Enlightenment is beyond words and language, but all enlightened beings have three things in common.
Number one, they realize the illusion of the self.
Number two, they are permanently released from the cycle of rebirth.
Number three, as a byproduct of their enlightenment, they possess supernatural powers.
In this class, we will use Yongjia Master's Songs of Enlightenment to discuss enlightenment.
Have you not seen people whose study has ended,
who do nothing, who abide in the Way at ease?
Have you not seen people?
Enlightened beings are hard to come by.
When you see them, they actually don't do much.
Their study has ended.
Yongjia Master said,
In my earlier days, I set out to acquire learning.
I studied commentaries, inquired into sutras and shastras,
distinguishing among terms and characteristics.
I did not know how to stop.
Entering the sea to count the sands, I exhausted myself in vain.
So he became a monk when he was only four.
He studied a lot and was the master of the Tantai school of Buddhism.
But he felt like he was attached to all the terms, and he was studying in vain.
That's why he said,
An enlightened being whose study has ended, who do nothing.
Now we are all very busy, busy in our reincarnation.
Every day our mind is full of things,
full of opposition, full of people who like us, dislike us.
Our mind is very occupied.
But enlightened beings, they have no one to be,
nowhere to go, nothing to do,
and they have no deadlines to meet.
They are very much at ease.
We often say,
Walking is Zen, sitting is Zen.
In speech or silence, in movement or stillness,
my substance is at peace.
So enlightened beings, no matter if they're walking or sitting,
they're always aware of what they're doing,
aware of the condition,
and it's always residing in their true nature,
in their suchness.
So actually we do not need to do anything,
because we already are.
We are already there.
We don't need to add anything to ourselves.
We are already who we're supposed to be,
just beings.
They do not banish false thoughts.
They do not seek the truth.
Often we think of cultivation as banishing our false thoughts
and seeking the truth.
But Yongjia Master tells us,
Do not seek the truth.
Do not call off the false.
Comprehend both Dharma are empty.
They do not have characteristics.
False thoughts, the truth,
they are both empty in nature,
and it's not something we should be attached to.
Let's talk about Yongjia Master's enlightenment.
He only met his Dharma teacher,
Hui Nan Master, one time.
He walked around Hui Nan Master three times
and stared at him.
Hui Nan Master commented on his informality.
He then replied,
The question of incessant rebirth is a momentous one
that can come at any moment.
I have no time to waste on ceremony.
I wish you can give me an answer to this question quickly.
Hui Nan suggested he embody birthlessness,
i.e. birthlessness in order to overcome impermanence.
Yongjia immediately displaced understanding of it
and then was ready to leave.
But Hui Nan said,
Do not leave so quickly.
Yongjia replied,
There is no such thing as quickly.
Distinction between quickness and slowness
is an artificial construct.
Hui Nan was very satisfied at the answer,
but Yongjia kept asking,
A mere concept, an artificial construct,
can it really have meaning?
Hui Nan asked in return,
Who is it that distinguishes whether it has meaning or not?
Then Yongjia replied,
Distinctions are meaningless.
Hui Nan said,
Excellent! Excellent!
Now you stay here just one single night.
That's why Yongjia is famous
for being the overnight guest
that certified him of his enlightenment.
So enlightenment is not really about
cutting off our false thoughts
or seeking the truth.
It is about understanding birthlessness
or non-production or we call just emptiness.
Number two,
The true nature of ignorance is the Buddha nature,
the empty body and illusory.
Transformation is the Dharma body.
So there are two things here.
Our ignorance is the Buddha nature.
Our body right now is the Dharma body.
So we do not look for the Buddha nature elsewhere.
It is in our current mind,
which is ignorance.
It is in our current body.
We do not look for something
that's outside of who we are right now.
One of my favorite stories is about wild ducks.
There was a master and a disciple
taking a walk one day.
The master asked,
What is that?
The disciple replied,
Wild ducks.
The master asked,
What happened?
The disciple answered,
Wild ducks flew over.
Then the master said,
The master pinched the disciple's nose really hard
and he became enlightened.
What does the story mean?
It's fine that the wild ducks flew over.
It is the fact that he was not at the present moment.
He has been attached to the external conditions
and his mind was no longer present.
But when his master pinched his nose,
the pain actually brought him to the present
and he became enlightened.
He realized that this whole time
he has been attaching
to the external circumstances.
That's why he is not enlightened.
So in the song it says,
It does not leave where it is.
It is always clear.
If you search for it,
know that you will not see it.
It is always just here.
You don't have to go search somewhere else
to find your Buddha nature
or the Dharmakaya.
It's always right here
at your present ignorance
and your present body.
There's actually nowhere to go.
Number three.
In the Dharma body's enlightenment,
there is not a single thing.
So it's emptiness again.
In our dream, very clearly,
there are six destinies.
After enlightened, completely empty,
there is no universe.
We are in the dream state right now.
That's why we think
there are six realms of reincarnation
and we are in the human realm.
But after you're enlightened,
you realize there actually
there's no universe.
Everything is empty in its essence.
When you really see emptiness,
you will not be attached to anything
of the world,
even when people slander you
or abuse you.
So Yongjia Master said,
Let other people slander us.
We bear their condemnation.
They are like those
who try to burn the sky,
only exhaust themselves.
I hear of it.
It's just like drinking the sweet dew,
thus smelt and refined.
Suddenly,
enters the inconceivable.
So enlightened person,
even if other people slander us
or abuse us,
we will not be affected
because we know they are just
burning the sky.
It's useless.
We hear their comment.
It's like drinking the sweet dew
and we actually go into
our Buddha nature,
the inconceivable,
because we know
there is not a single thing.
At its source,
the inherent nature
is the Buddha of divine innocence.
We are the divine innocence.
That doesn't mean we have a thing.
It just means we are born with it.
It is what it is.
We are naturally what we are,
the Buddha nature.
Yongjia Master used the example
of the lion's cub.
The lion's cub together follow along,
three years old,
and then they too can loudly roar.
So lions are the king of the jungle.
Other animals do not come
and disturb them.
Even the little cubs,
they know they are the king
because they have the Buddha nature.
They are born with it.
So even at three years old,
they can roar like the adult lions.
So know who you are.
We are the divine innocence.
You are the price's jewel.
A price's jewel
is used and accessible
for benefiting beings,
responding to potential always.
So you are a price's jewel.
You can benefit all sentient beings.
Just like Guanyin Bodhisattva,
observe the sound of the world.
Wherever people need him,
he will go save them.
So we can all be like Guanyin Bodhisattva
if we find our true nature.
Number four,
when one is certified
to the characteristics of reality,
there are no people,
no dharmas.
The karma of the avicci
is canceled in the kusna.
When one is certified
to be enlightened,
understand the real mark
is empty of the people,
empty of the dharma,
then even our karma
of the worst hell
is canceled in a split moment
because of our
sudden enlightenment.
Anybody can have
the sudden enlightenment.
Courageous donor was a monk.
One day he went into the city
and a daughter of a wealthy man,
a married woman,
asked the monk to come
and expand the dharma.
The daughter fell in love with him.
Every time he comes,
the daughter would seduce him.
After a while,
he gave in
and started having a relationship with her.
The husband became suspicious
and the monk actually told this woman
to poison the husband to death.
At the end,
the monk knew that he was going
to the avicci hell,
the worst hell,
because of his serious offenses.
But a bodhisattva appeared,
showed him incredible transformations.
He actually realized the real mark,
became enlightened,
and awakened to non-production,
which is emptiness.
This is called
sudden enlightenment.
Just like a room that has been
in darkness for a thousand years,
but we just have one light,
and immediately
the darkness is no more.
This is the same concept
for the Pure Land Buddhism.
Just one recitation
of Amitabha Buddha's name,
it gets rid of all our 81 kappas of sin,
because we all have the Buddha nature within us.
There was a woman that started meditating
in her 20s,
but every time she meditated,
she would remember her stepfather
sexually abused her when she was young.
So every time she meditated,
she would feel this strong sense of fear,
anger, and anxiety,
and she could not meditate anymore.
Meditation teacher told her,
forgive and feel compassion
for your stepfather.
That is the only solution.
And she realized it was truly
her anger and animosity
toward her stepfather
that was causing the pain.
So she let go of all the anger,
soon went into deep meditation,
and became a spiritual teacher,
and started teaching healing meditation.
So anybody can be enlightened,
at any time.
We say,
when madness ceases,
bodhi appears.
We might not be fully enlightened,
like Yongjia Master this lifetime,
but we can definitely have a great enlightenment
that will transform our lives right now,
and we will at least be awakened enough
to align ourselves with Amitabha Buddha,
and go to the Western Pure Land.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community