Today we are going to talk about virtues and relationships.
We are all searching for happiness.
According to the ancient things, the key to happiness is to cultivate virtues and build
harmonious relationships.
So today we are going to talk about five social relationships, five ethics standards and
eight virtues.
Let's start with the five social relationships.
Number one, parent and child.
The parents should be loving and the children should be respectful.
Parents give us lives and raise us up.
This kind of unconditional love and kindness is priceless.
So this is the most valuable relationship.
In the olden days, there was a Mr. Yang.
He was a devoted Buddhist.
One day he decided to leave home and go look for this Zen master far away.
So he walked for days and on the way he met a monk.
The monk asked, where are you going?
He said, I'm trying to find this well-known Zen master.
He said, oh, why don't you go find Buddha instead?
He said, where do I find Buddha?
He says, oh, easy.
You just turn back toward your home.
If you see Buddha, you go find Buddha.
He said, where do I find Buddha?
You see someone wearing a yellow robe and having their slippers on the wrong feet.
That person is Buddha.
So this person walked back and for days he didn't find anyone that meets the description.
Finally he reached home.
He knocked on the door and his mother came out.
And much to the surprise, his mother was wearing a yellow robe and having her slippers on the
wrong feet.
So who is Buddha?
Buddha is your mother.
So if you're a Buddhist.
You should be filial and loving to your parents.
If you can't even love and respect your parents, then no matter how many omitofu you chant,
it's not going to work because you don't have the heart of the Buddha.
Number two is siblings.
The younger siblings should respect the older siblings and the older siblings should be
gentle and caring to the younger siblings.
The siblings are like branches on the same tree.
If we fight with each other.
It's like rotting the root and killing the tree slowly.
We should be loving to our siblings.
A hundred years ago, there was a 15 year old girl named Hazel Miner.
On March 15, 1920, she drove her younger brother and sister to school as usual in a carriage.
By noontime, because of the huge blizzard, their carriage tipped over and they were stranded.
Hazel was soaking wet, but she didn't care for herself.
That's it.
She found two blankets and a robe.
She wrapped them around her brothers and sisters and she also opened her own coat and spread
it around her brother and sister, trying to keep them warm.
She also kept telling them stories and sing songs and prayers, hoping to make them stay
awake.
25 hours later, the villagers finally found them.
By this time, Hazel, she froze to death and saved her brother and sister.
Hazel's monument is still in the Oliver County Courthouse in North Dakota.
Hazel can sacrifice her life for her siblings.
How can we fight with our siblings for little things?
Number three is husband and wife.
This is the most important relationship.
If this one is harmonious, then all other relationships will be harmonious as well.
There were two couples.
They live across the street from each other.
Couple A and B are in a relationship.
They live on the same street.
Couple A fights every other day.
Couple B never fought.
So finally one day, the couple A's wife went to couple B's wife and asked, what is your
secret?
How come we're always fighting and you guys never fight?
Couple B's wife said, oh, it's easy because everybody in your family is good people.
Everybody in my family is bad people.
The couple A's wife said, oh, that doesn't make any sense.
Couple B's wife said, whenever something happens, you have to be careful.
You have to be careful.
Every single one of us can be thick.
There is a single thing that goes wrong in your family because everybody insists on being
right and good people so nobody admits their fault so you guys will be arguing and fighting.
But in my family, when something goes wrong, we will admit our fault and apologize and
change our ways.
That's why in my family, we never fight.
So in order to have a good marriage relationship, we should be apologetic and we should always
be respectful for our spouse.
Thank you.
Number four is rulers and subjects. This applies to employers and employees. According to Mencius, if the ruler treats the subject like brothers, then the subject would treat the ruler like a best friend.
If the ruler treats the subject like dogs and horses, then the subject would treat the ruler like a stranger. If the ruler treats the subject like machines, then the subject would treat the ruler like an enemy. So how you treat others is how others will treat you. The relationship is reciprocal.
Number five is between friends. Friends have five duties to each other.
Number one, we have to give sound.
Virtuous advice so our friend doesn't go down the wrong path.
Number two, we should be caring. When they're going through a difficult time, we should be there to comfort them.
Number three, we should praise them when they are doing good deeds. We should praise them and encourage them to succeed in their endeavors.
Number four, we should keep secrets. When they tell us their family secrets, we cannot disclose it to anyone else.
Number five, we should give fine-grain-water.
financial support. When they're in a sudden financial crisis, we need to help them in
any way we can. So these are the five social relationships that we all have. In order for
these five social relationships to be harmonious, we need to have the five ethics standards.
Number one is loving kindness. Loving kindness is the root to all virtues. In Chinese, it's
the symbol of wisdom. On the left side, it's human. On the right side, it means the number
two. So two people stack up together. That means the relationship is very thick. We're
always thinking for the other person and we're not being selfish. Number two is duties. We
must follow our duties and play our role. If you're a father, be a good father. If
you're a son, be a good son. If you're a wife, be a good wife.
When you perform your duties, then the relationship will be in harmony. That way, you can be a
role model to all people and other people will follow your footsteps. Number three is
respect. Respect is the beauty in all relationships. If you want the relationship to be beautiful,
you need to keep a distance and show respect. Don't be careless because you're too close
and you say things that are rude.
So always have respect, especially between husband and wife. Number four is wisdom. In
order to have wisdom, we must first learn education on virtues. In school, we only learn
about knowledge on how to obtain a career, but we don't learn about morals and ethics.
So now we need to learn about virtues and apply the virtues to all different kinds of
relationships. That is wisdom.
Number five is trustworthiness. We have to be the person that everybody can count on.
They can trust you whenever they're in need to help them. So these five ethics standards,
if you expand them, they become eight virtues. Number one, filial piety. This is specific
to parent and child. This word is also a symbol of wisdom. On the top, it means old. On the
bottom, it means son. So the older generation on top of the younger generation together
as one. So we should not have any generation gap. If we have love and respect in our heart,
there is no problem and no conflict in the family.
Number two, we have to be respectful to elderlies. This is between siblings. We need to respect
our older siblings and respect them like they're our parents.
You can show respect in many ways. For example, when you're eating, drinking, walking, sitting,
you always let the elderlies go first to show your respect.
Number three, we need to have loyalty. Loyalty is between ruler and subject, but it also
apply to many different relationship. For example, you and Buddha. You need to be loyal
to Buddha. That means always follow his teaching.
Don't be an eye servant. Only good when someone's watching you.
Number four is trustworthiness. That applies to friends. You want to be the trustworthy
person that everybody can count on. You cannot make any empty promises. If you said it, you
have to do it. You have to be a credible person and be trustworthy.
Number five, we have to show respect. The best way is to treat each other like VIPs,
especially husband and wife. If you treat each other with respect, then nothing will
go wrong. This is well tested in 5,000 years of history. So show each other respect in
all relationships.
Number six is duties. We need to perform our duties in all five relationships, especially
the first one, parent and child. We have the responsibility to take care of our parents
when they're old and sick. We cannot just send them to senior homes because it is our
duty to take care of them.
Number seven is to have honor. This applies to rulers and subjects. Especially with the
subject, you cannot take any briberies. You have to be loyal and honest. In the Han Dynasty,
there was a Mr. Yang. He was being promoted to a very high government official position.
So on the way to see the emperor, he passed by the emperor. He passed by the emperor.
He passed by the emperor. He passed by the emperor. He passed by the emperor. He passed
by the city. The magistrate of the city, Mr. Wang, tried to bribe Mr. Yang. So in the
middle of the night, he took out 10 kilograms of gold and tried to give to Mr. Yang. And
when he offered it to Mr. Yang, Mr. Yang said, I cannot take this. Mr. Wang said, oh, it's
middle of the night. It's so dark. Nobody will know. Just take it. And Mr. Yang said,
God knows. Earth knows. You know. I know. How can you say nobody knows?
So we need to be a man of honor and never take briberies.
Number eight is shame. We need to feel ashamed when we are not behaving according to our
virtues. We all have the virtues inside of us. Sometimes we cannot do it. We should feel
ashamed. Man-shin says shame is the greatest and the most important word in a person's
lifetime. Because when we feel remorse and ashamed, we will put in our best effort to
change our ways and correct our mistakes.
We should be able to overcome our faults and reach sageshood. So these are the five social
relationships, five ethics standards, and eight virtues. If you follow this, you will
have a harmonious relationship and you will be truly happy. We all say we want to reach
Buddhahood. But in order to be a Buddha, first we need to be a virtuous person. If we're
not virtuous and we learn all the Buddhism and all the philosophy, it's not going to
because it's meaningless when you don't apply it.
Use Buddhism and Confucianism in your own life
and solve all your relationship problems.
And that way, you will gain true happiness.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Om Nito Fo.