Today we are going to talk about how the mind works.
The essence of our mind is called the original enlightenment.
It was free from all thoughts, but because it couldn't stand still, it started moving
and being agitated. It became the deluded mind, so we call it non-enlightenment.
Learning Buddhism is a process of actualization of enlightenment back to the perfect stillness
and finally reach final enlightenment, becoming a Buddha, reaching Buddhahood.
So today we are going to talk about how the mind works from the unenlightened state to
the enlightened state.
Every thought goes through 9 aspects, 3 subtle aspects and 6 cruel aspects.
Let's first talk about the 3 subtle aspects. This happens in our alaya consciousness, which
is our storehouse that stores all the karmic seeds of our past actions ready to be ripened
and produce the external world.
So let's look at the 3 aspects.
First is activity of ignorance.
It was the perfect still-suchness, but it got bored. It started having activities.
That means it started having thoughts. We call it this activity of ignorance.
Why do we call it ignorance? Because we are ignorant and we don't know that we have the
perfect self that is pure, eternal and that is self-sufficient. So we forgot about it
and we started having thoughts.
Number 2, it would produce perceiving subject.
Number 1, it would produce perceiving subject.
consciousness produces the seventh consciousness and the seventh consciousness grabs onto the
eighth consciousness as its permanent self. So we started having the idea of the personhood,
the ego, and we start perceiving the world based on our ego. So that's a perceiving subject.
We usually give the example of forced perceptions of water. Human, we see water as this liquid
that we can drink and use. Animals, such as fish, see the water as their habitat. And heavenly
beings, they see water as crystal. And all the ghosts, they see water as thick blood that's not
drinkable, even though they're very thirsty. So who is right? Who is seeing the right water?
Nobody, because it's all relative. It's based on perceiving subject of alaya consciences or
consciousness.
Number three, we will create the world of objects. So both the subject and the world
of objects is produced by our own alaya consciousness. Everything that you see in the external world
is actually all once imagined in our mind. So be careful what you think about. It will
manifest. For example, you might think of someone and the telephone ring and it will
be that person calling. Or you became a vegetarian.
You're thinking of vegetarian food and you spot a vegetarian restaurant around the corner.
Why is that? Because our thoughts produce reality. So think about things that's positive
and great. If you think about Amitabha Buddha, you will see Amitabha Buddha.
So we create the dreamer. We create the dream world, but we don't know it's a dream.
We have the six crew aspects of our thoughts that's happening in our spirit. So we create
the six consciousness, which is our mind. That does the thinking and analysis.
Number one, it will have discriminating intellect. It will discriminate this external object
as something we like or dislike. For example, we might like a lot of compliments and we
don't like any criticism. Or we like a lot of accomplishments, we don't like any failures.
Or we like prosperity and we don't like declines.
What do we base our likes and dislikes on? We base it on the idea of the self. We do
everything to protect the self and that's how we think and discriminate the world.
Number two is aspect of continuity. This discriminates the likes and dislikes, when after it continues,
it becomes a feeling of pleasure and pain. When we eat a chocolate cake, why do we like
it so much?
not that we like the taste of the chocolate cake it's because we like the
pleasure derived from tasting the chocolate cake that's the same as
alcohol or cigarette or any kind of thing that we're addicted to we're
addicted to the pleasurable feeling so that's because of the aspect of
continuity number three is an aspect of attachment as feeling of pleasure and
pain continued it will become attached will have even more attachment for
example if you really like your son you will attach everything to your son when
something happened to your son you would be depressed or worried a lot that will
affect your whole world or you bought a new car and someone made a scratch on it
and then you're heartbroken why because you've attachment the more attachment
you have the more suffering you have but we don't know that
number four is an aspect of speculation on names and letters we will analyze in
terms of words we will give it names in our mind for example we'll have names
based on what society gives us this is Louis Vuitton bag this is Rolex watch
this is a Porsche because of what the society tells us we have a lot of names
and letters in our mind we attach to our experience based on these brand names
and number five is an aspect of giving rise to karma after the strong
attachment with names will commit to an action for example something we
want we're gonna go search for it or with don't like someone we will have the
action of hitting the person or we might say something rude to revenge so these
are all things that we're going to commit
and it becomes a karma number six aspect of anxiety attached to the
aspect of karma. Because of karma, we will create anxiety. Anxiety here, it means suffering.
If you do a good deed, you will create karma in the three good realms, the heavenly realm,
the asura realm, and the human realm. If you create bad deeds, you will go to the three
bad realms, the animal realm, the ghost realm, and the hell realm. No matter what happens
to you, you are still creating karma in the six realms of reincarnation that never ends.
It's a vicious cycle and that's what we call delusion, karma, and suffering. That's what
we call samsara or life and death. So samsara or reincarnation is not caused by anyone.
It's caused by your own deluded thought, your deluded mind. So learning Buddhism is a process
of learning.
It's a process of liberating ourselves from this samsara life. So what do we do? First,
we have to recognize this nine aspects of the thought. It happens in an instant, but
it narrows down to four steps. The thought rising, the thought of binding, the thought
changing, and the thought ceasing. For example, sitting at home, bored, so I start thinking
about that person bad-mouthed me, how rude he is. So it's the thought rising, that's
my activity of ignorance. Then the thought of binding, me perceiving his words, and the
world object is his words. And then I will have discerning intellect, I dislike his words.
Aspect of continuity, feeling of pain from his words. And aspect of attachment, I will
keep thinking about it, I might not be able to sleep because of his words. And then have
aspect of speculation on names and elements.
What'sarsi Nopedi, how a person Durong and
Zanse be for the next?
Master Fengeding,
Oh, I
was
thinking a little bit bad about this position.
Master Fengending said the ultimate inner strength of specialists is when we collect
our
soul.
Master Fengending,
Oh, oh, oh, oh.
OK. Master Fengending and Zang Guixiang are both importantं this! Master Fengending,
or about to end when you commit the karma and have suffering so that's how every thought has
these four stages we want to recognize it as soon as we can the sooner you catch it the sooner you
stop it the more enlightened you are ordinary men like us we might not catch the thought until it's
kind of late we already create the karma and we already creating the anxiety for example i already
ate a chocolate cake then i realized oh it's not good for me i am creating greed and more samsara
so but that is already at the seizing the ending stage but for our arhat who is a theravada
self-enlightened saint they might catch their thoughts in this changing state for example
there was a monk he was studying with the master for many years and one day he decided to leave
the master and go on his own for years he started
building his own temple and he started building his own temple and he started building his own
temple and he started building his own temple and he started building his own temple and he started
building a majestic temple and had many disciples one day he heard that his master was coming to
visit him so he started cleaning up the whole place trying to impress his master and the night
before his master came he looked at his place and he thought oh my pride and my ego is at work
i'm so ashamed of myself so he grabbed a pile of sand
and spread it in front of the main hall of his temple the next day the master came looked around
the whole place and he said the most impressive thing in this whole place is the pile of sand in
front of the main hall so this monk he catch his thought with the attachment state when he is
attached to his ego and to his pride and then bodhisattva who is the mahayana buddhism trying to
enlighten others they might catch their thoughts in the binding stage there was a monk he was a thief
before he became a monk he was a thief before he became a monk he was a thief before he became a monk
one day he was giving a dharma talk in front of a large audience and after the dharma talk there was
a lot of tin cans of tea leaves and he loves tea leaves so he thought to himself oh it'll be great
if i can bring these tea leaves home so i can enjoy them for a long time and then he realized
that was a thought of greediness obediently he shout out see thief he tried to stop his own
greediness so he is catching his own greediness and he is trying to stop his own greediness so he is catching
his discriminating intellect the first moment of likes and dislikes and greediness okay so if you
are bodhisattva you might be able to see your thoughts at an earlier stage and buddha sees the
thought and the rising stage he is completely enlightened so he doesn't even have the thought
arising basically his alaya consciousness is completely purified he has no more thoughts
so that's the final enlightenment that we're trying to reach so why do we meditate we meditate
to quiet our mind to be aware of our thoughts and to be able to stop our thoughts that's diluted
back to our pure immutable pure mind that's our goal so at the end you will realize the original
enlightenment is the process of actualization of enlightenment is the final enlightenment
because of the process of realization of enlightenment is the final enlightenment
because of the process of realization of enlightenment
it's just one mind and one world of reality so that's a class for today thank you for listening