Today we are going to talk about reincarnation, which means the continuation of birth and death, lifetime after lifetime.
This is not our first lifetime. We've been reincarnated millions of times.
Today we are going to understand reincarnation as discussed in the Sravagama Sutra.
Reincarnation according to the Sutra has three kinds of continuity.
The first one is the continuity of the world.
Two is the continuity of living beings.
Three is the continuity of karmic retribution.
Let's first look at the continuity of the world.
How does the world come about?
First, we have the original enlightened mind.
Unfortunately, it becomes agitated, and it starts having movement.
Then it becomes the alaya consciousness, the mind that has rising and ceasing.
Because of the movement of our mind, it creates a big empty space.
The perpetual rotation of space becomes the wind, and we have the wind that supports the world.
When the emptiness hardens, it sets up the solidity, which is the store of metal,
which supports the earth, the land.
When the wind and the metal rub together, it creates the light of fire.
Then we have the fire wheel.
The brightness of the metal creates moisture, and from the light of the fire, steam arises.
That's when we have water.
So we have the four basic elements that create this world.
So is our body.
Wind, which is our breathing.
Metal, our bones.
Fire is our temperature.
Water is our saliva, our blood.
All the elements that comes from the cause and conditions, the karmic seeds,
store in our alaya consciousness, creating the entire world and our bodies.
None of it is real.
The nature of all these things is emptiness.
It's just cause and conditions, and rising and ceasing.
From these four elements, we have the four kinds of habitats.
Fire rises, water falls.
The combination creates the solidity.
What is wet becomes oceans and seas.
What is dry becomes continents and islands.
And when the power of water is less than the power of fire, it produces high mountains.
When the power of earth is less than the power of water, it becomes grass and trees, and it becomes groves and meadows.
That's why we have four kinds of habitats of ocean, islands, mountains, and meadows.
Our own alaya consciousness created the four kinds of habitats.
Some people love to live by the ocean.
Some love to live in the islands.
Some live in the cities.
Some live in the valleys.
Our alaya consciousness has different cause and conditions.
There's no coincidence where you live right now.
It's all because of our karma.
Now let's look at the continuity.
There are three of living beings.
This is our environment.
This is our birth.
There are four kinds of birth.
The first one is egg-born.
Two is womb-born.
Three is moisture-born.
Four is transformation body.
The egg-borns come from thoughts.
If we have a lot of wandering thoughts, we're likely to become an egg-born,
such as feather, vertebrates, chicken, birds.
It's all coming out of thoughts.
Our mind creates life and death.
It's all because of our alaya consciousness.
That's why we try to meditate.
We quiet our mind so it has less wandering thoughts,
and it doesn't create so much life and death.
Then we have the womb-born, which are mammals.
That's due to emotions.
If we have a lot of emotions of happiness, sadness, anger, greed,
we are likely to become a mammal.
This mammal needs four kinds of conditions.
A mother, a father, individual's karma, and warmth.
Then we have life.
Then we have the moisture-born, which is like insects, like mosquitoes.
They arise from union.
The union of sunlight and moisture that creates the moisture-born.
Lastly is the transformation body that occurs through separation.
The opposite of moisture is from union.
This is from separation.
You are separated from the old body to become the new transformation body,
just like butterflies.
They need to leave the old caterpillar body to become a butterfly.
There are lots of transformation bodies in the six realms of incarnation.
Heavenly beings are transformation bodies.
Hungry ghosts are transformation bodies.
When we go to Amitabha's Western Pure Land,
we are the transformation body of the lotus.
There's no doubt that we've been through all of these four kinds of births in our reincarnation.
During the reign of Emperor Wu of Liang,
there was a Master Zhigong.
Master Zhigong had the ability to see people's previous lives.
One time he was passing by a wedding.
He said,
How strange, how bizarre.
The grandson is marrying the grandmother.
Pigs and sheep sitting in the chair.
The six close kin cook in the brazier.
People get together to celebrate.
I see it all as a form of suffering.
The groom of the wedding is the grandson.
The bride is the grandmother.
Because when the grandmother passed away,
the person she loves the most is her grandson.
That's why she reincarnated as a woman and marries her grandson.
The pigs and sheep were eaten by this family before,
but now they are sitting on the chair as guests of the family.
The six close kin that ate the pigs and sheep before,
now they are cooked as dishes to be served on the table.
People see it as a celebration.
Master Zhigong sees it all as a form of suffering
and sees the truth about reincarnation.
So we've been reincarnated as all these living beings before
in our prior lifetimes.
Three, continuity of karmic retribution.
It says in the sutra,
You owe me a life.
I have to repay my debt to you.
You love my mind.
I adore your form.
This is all due to our killing, stealing, and lust.
You owe me a life.
You eat me.
I eat you.
So you owe me a life.
I owe you a life.
We keep eating each other and keep coming back to kill each other.
So that's reincarnation.
Basically to pay back debt.
I have to repay my debt to you.
You have to repay your debt to me.
Keep stealing from each other.
Then we keep having to pay it back.
Sometimes we become bankrupt this lifetime
because we've done this to others.
Or it's due to love.
You love my mind.
I adore your form.
You love how I am.
I love your looks.
We keep having lust and entangle with each other.
The father and mother is consummating.
Our alaya consciousness gets attached to the egg and the sperm.
That's how we become a living being.
This is all due to our lust.
If you are a son, you love the mother.
If you are the daughter,
you actually love the dad.
That's how you become a fetus.
That's all how we got our life.
Because of killing, stealing and lust,
we go through hundreds and thousands of eons
of sustained mutual entanglement.
This is not our first lifetime we've been with these people.
We've seen them many many many lifetimes
in different environments.
Maybe we're all pigs together.
Now we're gathered again
to pay back each other's debt.
That's what life is all about.
So Buddha wants us to awaken
from all these reincarnations.
If you can see that this is all a dream
created by our deluded consciousness,
we will be enlightened.
This is the truth that we need to ponder upon.
If you do not understand reincarnation,
you will have no motivation to cultivate.
In conclusion,
when the madness ceases,
just that ceasing is bodhi.
We need to cease the deluded mind,
the liar consciousness
from having these thoughts of killing, stealing and lust.
If we stop this condition,
the real cause of greed, anger and ignorance
will not arise.
That ceasing itself is enlightenment.
What is enlightenment?
Enlightenment is just the ceasing
of the deluded mind.
We don't want to keep using the liar consciousness
that is keeping us through reincarnation.
We created reincarnation for ourselves.
We create all the plot in our dream
from our own karma.
If we just wake up,
see the falseness of all appearances
and we see the truth of the real nature of all things,
which is emptiness,
there will be no more reincarnation.
We need to treasure this lifetime as a human.
If we really understand the Dharma
and really cultivate ourselves
not to be caught up in the world
and keep having the thoughts of greed, anger and ignorance,
let go of our attachment to the self,
then we can really be enlightened.
All the cultivation,
all the meditation,
all the chanting is to wake us up
so we can be out of reincarnation forever.
We are in this lifetime present.
We don't even know that we need to get out.
If you don't cultivate next lifetime,
it's more reincarnation waiting for you
and it will never end.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.