Today's topic is on emptiness.
Emptiness means all things have no independent existence of its own apart from reliance on
other conditions.
We will use Bodhisattva Nagarjuna's The Treaty of Great Wisdom to understand emptiness.
It talks about 18 types of emptiness.
Number one, the emptiness of the internal.
That's the sixth sense organs of the eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body and mind.
Number two is the emptiness of the external.
That's the sixth sense objects of the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch and dharma.
Number three is the emptiness of the internal.
That's the sixth sense objects of the internal and the external.
So in the internal organs and the external objects, there is not a sense of eye.
So this is talking about non-self.
In our daily lives, we have to learn to have emptying experience, which means to remove
the eye and the mind from our thoughts.
Emptiness is a great tool to extricate us of ego-centered experience and to liberate
us from the presence of selfishness.
Number four, emptiness of emptiness.
It's the emptying of the first three.
Emptiness is a tool.
Once we demolish afflictions of the self, we need to let go of the dharma as well.
So emptying of the self and emptying of the dharma.
Let go of our attachment to the self and let go of our attachment to the dharma.
Just like if we go upstairs, then we don't need to carry the stair with us once we get
up there. Just like we are sick, we eat medicine. After we are cured, we don't need to have
the medicine anymore. Just like if a strong man fought off the thieves in our house, once
the thieves are gone, we don't need the strong man in the house anymore. So that's the emptiness
of emptiness. So we need to get rid of the tool as well. Number five, emptiness of the
great. It's talking about the emptiness of space. We are all attached to the concept
of space. This is a big house or big land. If we let go of our attachment to space, we
actually can experience something that's limitless. In the Practice and Vow of Universal Vorti
Bodhisattva, it says, in one mold of dust are lands as numerous as molds of dust. In
each land are an incalculable number of Buddhas. Small as a dust, small as a mold of dust,
there are numerous Buddha lands. And in each Buddha land, there's numerous Buddhas. That's
the world of bodhisattvas experience. If we just open up our heart to prajna and to emptiness,
we can experience much more when we let go of our attachment to space. Number six is
emptiness of the ultimate. Ultimate means nirvana. Sometimes we become attached to nirvana,
to what's the ultimate.
But when you're
attached to the ultimate, it's no longer the ultimate. In the Diamond Sutra, Shakyamuni
Buddha said to Shri Puti, in the neutral sammyaksambodhi that I have fulfilled, there's not even a
modicum of Dharma to be obtainable. Such state is denominated as a neutral sammyaksambodhi.
So there is not obtaining of enlightenment. Because once you have attachment to it, it's
no longer enlightenment.
So prajna or emptiness does not allow you to build any credential or build any self-identity
to be someone special. We need to let go of all attachment in order to be awakened.
Number seven is to emptiness of the compounded phenomena. Compounded phenomena means all
conditioned phenomena. Everything is conditioned existence that we are experiencing right now.
We need to understand they are only conditioned arising based on causation. For example, the
father is a father because he has a son. The son only exists because there's a father.
And the father is also a son to the grandfather. This is all conditioned arising. If we just
respect all conditioned and play our part in our lives, then we be the best that we
can be. Be a good son, be a good father.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
In all situations, we go with the flow, be flexible, and do the best that we can. That's
someone who really have the view of prajna and emptiness.
Number eight is the emptiness of uncompounded phenomena. Uncompounded phenomena means the
same as the ultimate, something that's not conditioned because it is the ultimate. But
we should know we cannot be attached to the uncompounded phenomena easily.
Because uncompounded phenomena only exist because there's such thing as compounded
phenomena. If we are attached to the uncompounded phenomena, it's no longer the uncompounded
phenomena. So we need to really understand the wisdom in this conditioned arising. So
do not be attached to what's the ultimate, what's uncompounded either. Number nine, the
emptiness of what has been. We need to be aware of the emptiness of what has been. Remember,
also because the emptiness of what has been is zero. You should not be attached to your
past beyond the extremes. It's the emptiness of the first eight. They all need to be empty.
So you want to demolish all your attachments until there's nothing left to demolish. That's
the Garjuna's specialty. It's a great refutation of everything. So let go, know everything,
its condition arising, and it has no intrinsic nature of its own, then we can see beyond
everything. But some people say, if I empty everything, let go everything, then I have
nothing. Isn't that scary? Actually, if you think about it, you have never really lost
anything because you never possessed anything in the first place. Emptiness, it's like a
double-edged sword. It cuts through our afflictions. It also cuts the person who is holding the
sword. So we need to use the sword, but let go of the sword at the end.
So we need to use the sword, but let go of the sword at the end. So we need to use the
sword, but let go of the sword at the end. Number 10 is the emptiness of what is beginningless
and endless. So number 5 is the emptying of space. Number 10 is the emptiness of time.
Because we're attached to time, Buddha tells us about beginningless and endless. A lot
of people ask, when did reincarnation start? Did we have death first or rebirth first?
All these questions have no definite answer.
Buddha just used beginningless and endless to demolish your attachment to the concept
of time. Once you demolish your attachment to time, then we do not want to attach to
beginningless or endless either. Number 11 is the emptiness of the indestructible. It's
talking about the emptiness of things in their part and as a whole. For example, a car is
made out of car parts. It can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a
car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car,
it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it
can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car, it can be a car. It
cannot be a car without its parts but the parts do not equal the car. So both the car
and the parts, they have no real existence of their own. They are just conditioned existences.
Once you really understand this, you will not be sad or upset when it breaks or things
change, because you already saw that it's a conditioned existence and it's not going
to last forever.
So once we have this prajna of emptiness,
when things change, we will be able to accept
and be the best that we can
and not be caught up in the situation.
Number 12 is the emptiness of nature.
Number 13 is the emptiness of all phenomena.
Nature means the inner essence.
All phenomena means its appearance.
Are we the same inside and outside?
Sometimes when we do good deeds,
when other people are watching,
but actually in the prajna,
it's like the sun that's illuminating everywhere.
We are under the spotlight all the time
and we are fully exposed.
So there's nowhere to hide under prajna.
Know that when you're really cultivating,
do not fool yourself that you're practicing.
Be the same inside and outside.
14, emptiness of definitions.
All definitions.
And all names are just a name.
For example, the six sense organs,
the six sense objects, the 18 rounds,
everything is just a name.
It's only forced to demolish our attachment to the self,
but do not be attached to the concept either.
A lot of people are attached to name brand things
or your title or your credential,
but all of these are just human made concept.
They have no real essence
or real value.
So see through all the definitions.
15 is the emptiness of the unapprehensible.
This is the opposite of the definition.
What's definable and what's undefinable.
This unapprehensible means the unattainable
or what we say the ultimate,
something that is hard to see or hard to describe.
But if you're attached to something that is unattainable,
then it loses meaning.
So if you're attached to something that is unattainable, then it loses meaning.
It's no longer the ultimate.
Just like if you see a hand.
In the five fingers, you do not see a fist.
So in all the phenomenons,
you do not see anything that's attainable or unattainable.
Number 16 is the emptiness of non-things.
When things cease to be, we do not lose anything.
Number 17, emptiness of its own emptiness.
When things arise, we do not get them.
We do not gain anything.
Number 18, emptiness of the inherent existence of non-things.
When things exist, we are not happy.
When things cease to be, we are not sad.
When you have this wisdom, you have real peace in your mind.
That's the prajna of emptiness.
The 18, emptiness is truly empty and truly non-empty.
When you realize emptiness, you can eradicate all your afflictions and all your attachments
and all your problems, and you will be at peace.
So this is only a glimpse of emptiness.
It's for you to come up with your own questions and have creative doubts about emptiness.
So you can use and see emptiness in your daily life and see the truth more clearly.
When we really understand emptiness, we'll be soaring.
Like an eagle who sees from above.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.