Today we are going to talk about the Eight Consciousnesses.
In the Consciousness-only school of Buddhism, its main theory is that everything is created
from the Consciousness, hence the word Consciousness-only school.
This means everything is based upon the coming into being and the ceasing to be of the Consciousness,
therefore it's impermanent, it's conditioned, and unreal.
By knowing what is unreal, then we can discover what is real, which is our originally pure,
bright, enlightened mind.
Today we will use verses from the Verses Deliverer.
First, let's have an overview of the Eight Consciousnesses.
The first five consciousnesses are eyes, ears, nose, tongue, and body.
These five are in direct contact with the external world.
Then we have the sixth consciousness that is our thinking mind that conceptualizes everything.
We also have the seventh consciousness, the ego consciousness that only thinks about the
self.
Then we come to the eighth consciousness, the storehouse of the self.
So that's how our Eight Consciousnesses work together.
Now let's look at them in detail.
It's divided up into four sections.
The first five consciousnesses are together, then the sixth consciousness, the seventh
consciousness, and the eighth consciousness are divided up separately.
Now let's first talk about the first five consciousnesses.
All five consciousnesses rely on the Eight Consciousnesses.
They rely on their own pure form organs.
Because they are in contact with the external world, they must have organs.
There are two kinds of sensory organs.
One is the visible physical organs.
The second type is the pure form organs.
That's our neural pathways or something that is not visible.
We usually use the example of the flower pot.
The pot outside is the visible physical organ.
The soil inside is the pure form organ.
And the flower growing out of it, that's our consciousness.
So without the soil, there won't be any flowers.
There won't be any consciousness working.
So that's why we have to have the pure form organs.
Furthermore, they require nine, eight, or seven conditions working together as neighbors.
In order for us to see the world, we actually need nine.
Nine preconditions.
The first one is we need to have distance.
If you look at something this close, you won't be able to see anything.
Two, we need light.
Without light, we cannot see.
Three, we need the organs like we said above.
Number four, we need to have an object, the thing that we want to look at.
Then we also need attention to focus our consciousness on the object.
Then we have the sixth consciousness.
The basis of the consciousness.
The basis of discrimination.
The seventh consciousness, the basis of defilement and purity.
And the eighth consciousness, the fundamental basis.
And number nine, we need the seed, the karmic seed of the consciousness in order for the
consciousness to arrive.
So we need all nine conditions in order for us to see one object.
It actually requires a lot for us to be able to see.
And in order for us to hear, we need eight conditions.
We subtract the lights because we don't need lights to hear.
And for our nose, tongue, and body, we subtract light and distance because they are in direct
contact with the object of our smell, taste, and touch.
So as you can see, we need a lot of conditions working together like neighbors in order for
us to be in contact with the object.
So we need a lot of conditions working together like neighbors in order for us to be in contact
with the object of our smell, taste, and touch.
So, why do we need to know this?
So little cognitive testing experiences can help us learn more about the external world.
Why do we need to know this?
But this is from far away.
Is that my perspective.
Dr.
Shifu Jiening.
It was common knowledge.
Dr.
Shifu Jiening.
Here, what we are observing as we look at the
external world focused on these five things the economic , political, social, and
environmental health impact.
Why do we need to know this?
is tricking you. By understanding how our consciousness works, then we won't be afraid
of height anymore. So this conscious only school of Buddhism is actually the psychology
of Buddhism that will help us overcome a lot of our emotions.
Now let's look at our sixth consciousness. In physical action and in speech, it is the
most important. Our sixth consciousness, that's how we create karma. It has a lot of karma
generating power because it directs our body to take action and our mouth to make speech.
So that's how we make our wholesome and unwholesome deeds. That's why it has the ability to
summon forth the power of karma that leads to rebirth and retribution. There are two
kinds of karma.
The first is summoning karma. It brings us to the realm of rebirth. For example, the
heavenly realm or the human realm or the hungry ghost realm. So that's the major karma.
Number two, we have the retribution karma, which is the lesser degree. Once you're
reborn in that realm, the retribution can be very different. For example, in the animal
realm. If you're a stray dog, you might have a very difficult life. But if you're
in the million dollar home, you might have a lot of servants taking care of you. So your
retribution might be very different, even you're both in the animal realm. So use our
sixth consciousness wisely to cultivate all the goodness and eradicate all our bad deeds.
When Buddha was around, one day there was a young girl sweeping the front courtyard
of her house. Buddha passed by with the Sangha.
This girl saw Buddha. She said,
She felt a great sense of joy and elation, and she was gazing upon Buddha in awe and
admiration. Because of this good deed, after she passed away, she was reborn in the heavenly
realm. She knew that it was because of this one good deed, she was reborn there. So she
came back to thank Buddha. Buddha expounded Dharma to her, and she actually became enlightened
and obtained Arhatshet. So from this one good thought of being joyfully
beautiful, seeing Buddha, that created a lot of great positive karma for her. So use our
sixth consciousness wisely.
Now let's look at the seventh consciousness. It continuously follows and grasps the object
of the self. The seventh consciousness, it doesn't come in contact with the external
world. It only tells the sixth consciousness what to think based on the self, and it just
attaches to the eighth consciousness as the self.
So, it has 4 strong innate afflictions. Number one, it has the self delusion. It doesn't understand
that we are the pure enlightened mind. So it keeps attaching to the self as the real
personhood. That's why it's an ignorant and delusion. Number two, we have view of the
self. Our view of the self becomes very stubborn and very strong, and we are full of this ego.
Then we have number three.
our self-conceit. We become very arrogant. We compete, compare, and be jealous of others.
Number four, we have self-love. We love the self and we do everything to benefit the self.
Even if you're born as a fish in a tank, the fishes will fight over territories. The same
kind of fish will get together and fight against the other group. So everyone is attached to the
sense of the self. That's why we keep reincarnating. So day and night, it induces the state of dreaming
and confusion in living beings. Because of this consciousness, day and night, we are reduced to
the state of dreaming and confusion. If you ever notice, in your dream, you're always the main
character because we're so full of the self. That's due to our seventh consciousness. The
eighth consciousness.
It undergoes perfuming and contains the seeds of organs, body, and the environment. The eighth
consciousness has two major jobs. The first, it undergoes perfuming. Whatever the first seven
consciousness does, it perfumes and permeates the eighth consciousness. The eighth consciousness
doesn't produce any karma. It's all produced by the first seven consciousnesses and stores them.
So the eighth consciousness is constantly,
being permeated and influenced by the first seven consciousnesses.
Number two, it contains the karmic seeds of everything, so everything we've ever done
are seen is all cumulated as karmic seeds in the storehouse. So it's a big warehouse
that stores all our karma. When the conditions are right, the seeds ripen into results. The
result is our organs, our body, and the environment, basically the entire material world. So the
entire world is created by our own alaya consciousness. That's the truth, the reality of the universe.
Furthermore, it is the one who comes first and leaves last being truly a master of the
house. When we pass away it is the last one to leave this body. Even though we are medically
pronounced dead, the eighth consciousness still lingers on for 8 hours or even up to
36 hours. That's why we have to have people that help you chen omitofo even after your
last breath. Because the eighth consciousness is still there. When we take rebirth it is
the first one to get into the house.
the mother's womb because it's the first one to come in so this eighth consciousness is what
carries us throughout our reincarnation and through samsara so this is our life by understanding this
we actually can learn a lot first we need to know that karma and reincarnation is real we have to
use our consciousness to cultivate goodness and eradicate our bad deeds number two we need to know
this eighth consciousness is all conditioned none of it is me as we perceive this is not the real me
the thinking mind everything is not the real me the real me is actually the originally pure bright
enlightened mind that's who we really are
so by understanding what is unreal we can go back to what is real we want to be apart from the
heart the mind and the consciousness we usually call the eight consciousness the heart the seven
consciousness the mind and the sixth consciousness the consciousness so we actually want to be apart
from the heart the mind and the consciousness that's how we're supposed to be
we're supposed to be apart
living in our originally pure, bright, enlightened mind. So that's the class for
today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.