今天我們要討論的是Karma 什麼是Karma?
Karma 意思是你的行動,你的言語和你的想法 實際上創造你的命運
所有事情發生在你自己的行動上,我們稱之為Karma
無論你做什麼,都會回到你身上
你的命運創造在你自己的言語,你的想法和你的行動上,我們稱之為Karma
我們有個有名的說法是
To know of past life causes, look at the rewards you're reaping today
To find out about future lives, you need only notice what you're doing
Right now, so you don't need to go to a fortune teller or a psychic to know what you did in your past lifetime
Just look at what you're experiencing today
If you're very wealthy, that means you donated a lot of money, you've been very generous
That's why this lifetime, you're very wealthy
If you're very healthy, that means you were very kind
If you're very attractive, that means you never get mad
So everything has a cause and an effect
And it's all based on your doing
So look at your life right now, then you know what you did before
And to find out about the future, to know about what's going to happen to you later
Look at what you're doing right now
If you always do good deeds, you're always meditating, you're doing great mantras and chanting
You will create a wonderful future for yourself
So notice what you're doing currently
Then you know what your future is going to be
In the Qing Dynasty, there was a student, Mr. Yang
Mr. Yang, he was very rich, grew up in a rich family
And he studies very well
So one time, he went with his friends into the city to take the imperial exam
He was sure that he was going to do well on the exam
Before they went, they went to a fortune teller
The fortune teller looked at him and said, you're very smart
Unfortunately, you're not
You only have three more days to live
You're going to die before the exam
Oh, he was traumatized, he was shot
So at night, he couldn't sleep
He went for a walk
He went for a walk, he saw a lady crying
And he asked, why are you crying?
And she said, my husband owes 50 gold pieces to the government
And he's in jail right now
That's why he sold me
Tomorrow, I have to leave my children to be a slave
Mr. Yang said, can I give you the money?
Tomorrow morning, will it still be okay?
And she said, sure
So the next morning, Mr. Yang brought the lady 70 gold pieces
And he said to her, 50 gold pieces for you to return the money to government
And save your husband
And 20 gold pieces for you guys to do some business
So you guys can have a better life
He did that for this lady unconditionally
Just gave her the money
That night, he slept very well
The next day, somebody knocked on his door at the hotel room
When he went to open the door
At the same time, the roof of the hotel room just collapsed
So he went to open the door
He actually saved himself
So why did that happen?
Because he did a very good deed
The next day, he went to the fortune teller
The fortune teller looked at him again
He said, oh, congratulations
Your life totally changed
You must have done something really good
You will live to a really old age
And you're gonna be a great government official
Because he did this good deed
To save someone's life unconditionally
Your life is changed by your good deed and bad deed
It's like multiplication
Do good deed, it multiplies
Do bad deed, it's like division
Our life is depending on what we do
We call it the causes
And causes are dependent on three factors
First, your intention
What is your intention
That determines how much the karma weighs
For example, if you drive to work
And the wheel of your car killed a thousand ants
Does that give you negative karma?
No
Because you didn't do it on purpose
On the other hand, if there's two ants on the table
You purposely killed the ants
Does that have karma?
Yes
Because why?
It's bad
It's based on intention
When you have the intention of doing something
That makes a big difference
That's how much the karma weighs
So first, it's depending on your intention
Second, it's dependent on the condition
What do we mean by condition?
Who you do the deed to
For example, if you do a good deed to your parents
To your teacher
Because they are your benefactors
They do great things for you
You do good deeds to them
Then it weighs a lot
At the same time, if you do bad things
That weighs more than other people
Because they are the most important people to you
So who you do it to really matters too
No matter to change your karma
The third is determination
How much you want it
If you go steal someone's money
But you feel kind of guilty
You don't really want to
But you just really have no money
You feel guilty
If you have no guilt
You just keep stealing, stealing, stealing
That will cost a lot
Because you wanted to do it wholeheartedly
So depending on your motive
And how many times you do the deed
The karma will be different
So the karma is dependent on these three factors
What about the results?
There are actually three kinds of results
First is called ripened results
You do a good deed
The good karma can happen to you
This lifetime
Or next lifetime
Or next year
Or many, many lifetimes later
We don't know
Because karma is very complex
It ripens at different times
It can ripen really fast
Or many lifetimes later
So that's called ripened results
The second is called carried over results
You will carry over results
From your prior lifetime
And there are two kinds
One is called carried over behavior
The child whenever he eats
He likes to share
That means what?
Because prior lifetime
That person loves to share
That's why in this lifetime
Nobody taught him
But he just loves to share
So that is called carried over behavior
From your prior lifetime
And there's also experienced carried over
If you've done a lot of killing
In your prior lifetime
This lifetime
You will experience bad health
And feeling sick all the time
That's called the carried over experience
So we have a lot of carried over karma results
The third is called overall results
That's your environment
If you did a lot of sexual misconduct before
In this lifetime
You will live in a very dirty and messy place
According to the sutra
If you did very well in your prior lifetime
You will live in a beautiful house
In a beautiful country
Beautiful environment
That's all based on what you did before
So what happened to you at your dying day?
At the end
What counts?
What counts and bring you to the next lifetime?
Usually on three things
First is called weighed karma
Weighed karma is kind of like this
If you did something really really significant in this lifetime
You saved someone's life
Or you did something really bad
You actually killed a person
That weighs a lot
A strong negative deed
Or a strong wholesome deed
That will take you to the next round
You can become a heavenly being
If you did really well
You can go to hell
Animal realm
Or you can be a person again
So it's depending on the weighed karma
So that's usually the first determinant
The second is called habitual karma
If you didn't do anything very significant this lifetime
You were just ordinary
Not very good
Not very bad
Then it will be dependent on your habit
What do you do all the time in this lifetime?
Like what's your habit?
If someone is obsessed about drawing horse
Next lifetime
They will probably become a horse
Because you're obsessed about drawing the horse
What's your habit this lifetime?
Then you will follow that habit
And have that kind of karma
If you didn't have much habit
And you don't have much significant deed that you did
It depends on your approximate karma
That means your thoughts at the time you're dying
You think of Amitabha Buddha
At the time when you're dying
He will come and get you
Because you are thinking of him
Whatever you're thinking at the time you're dying
Is very important
If you are very depressed
Very upset
When you're dying
Then you're likely to go to hell
So whatever you think about
At your dying moment
Brings you to the next lifetime
So it's very important to know the cause and the effect
So that's karma for you in a nutshell
So karma is very accurate
It's never wrong
Always has its cause and effect
It will never make any mistakes
So use this lifetime wisely
To do all that is good
And create a positive and wonderful karma
And destiny for yourself
So that's it for today
Thank you for listening
Amitabha