Today we're going to talk a little bit about the history of the United States of America.
We're going to talk about our self-nature. Do you know yourself? Who are you?
The reason we're meditating is so that we can find our true self.
The sixth patriarch of the Zen school of Buddhism, he was a lumberjack.
He doesn't know how to read or write. He's a very, very poor person.
But he wanted to be a Buddha. He wanted to know his true self.
He went to the fifth patriarch and finally became enlightened.
When he became fully enlightened, this is what he said, and this is who we are.
First, our self-nature is originally pure.
This pure is not the clean or dirty pure.
It's just naturally, it's already pure in its own essence, never been contaminated before.
You think you have all these wandering thoughts. Actually, you don't.
These are not your true self. Your true self doesn't have any of these wandering thoughts.
Usually, we have the metaphor of a mirror.
It's never affected by whatever comes and goes.
Nothing really affected you. You're always perfect and complete and pure.
Your true self really has no wandering thought at all. Just know that for a fact.
So that's the first one.
The second one is the self-nature does not arise or perish.
Everything in life is based on cause and control.
Everything comes and goes because there's a cause.
A little seed, we plant it, we give it water and give it sunlight, it becomes a tree.
So it's based on cause and condition.
But when the time is up, the tree will die.
That's the same as our lives. We have our birth, life, and then we have our death.
Everything is coming and going.
But there's only one thing that doesn't perish if your body dies.
And what is that? Your self-nature.
It never got started or ended. There's no beginning and there's no ending.
It will continue no matter what happens to you.
Your self-nature will go on forever and ever.
So know this for a fact and not be afraid of anything that happens in life or death or anything.
Because your self-nature, your true essence, will always be lasting.
Live and be aware of that fact about yourself.
The third is self-nature is originally complete.
You're not lacking anything.
You grow up and you go to school and the teacher taught you, you know, English, math, science.
It's not because the teacher taught you.
You already know that inside of you.
You already have the perfect wisdom inside of you.
They just helped brought it out of you.
You already have it.
You have all the wisdom, all the perfect compassion,
all the talents in the world.
So there's nothing that you can't accomplish because your self-nature has everything.
If you want to be a writer, you can be a writer.
You want to be a singer, you want to be an athlete.
There's nothing you can't do if you just put your attention on it
because you know your self-nature is complete.
It's never lacking of anything.
That should help boost our confidence.
The fourth is our self-nature does not waver.
We were meditating.
We were on a mountain.
Your self-nature is like this mountain that is stable,
never moving by the outside circumstances.
If people ridicule you, they will judge you,
or you have a bad day at work,
or something happened to you that's terrible, your tragedy.
Nothing will affect your self-nature.
It doesn't waver by any outside circumstance.
It stays true. It stays complete.
It stays solid.
So your emotions should not go up and down
based on what's happening.
You should decide your emotions and your happiness.
That's why we meditate.
We meditate so we're fully in line with our true nature
that's never shaken by the outside world.
You're complete and perfect and do not waver.
The fifth is self-nature can generate everything.
Your thoughts create the world.
You are the creator of the universe.
Your thoughts.
So don't have negative thoughts that doesn't benefit you.
You want to have thoughts that will help you,
help you become a better person,
help you do things well.
Don't be negative or upset or be jealous
because that's not your true self.
Your true self is perfect and complete.
You want to use your thoughts to create all that is positive.
You want to create a beautiful world for yourself.
Be confident and know that every one of your thoughts
creates a reality.
I was meditating last year
and I wanted to teach meditation.
And guess what?
In September of last year,
strangers brought us the cushions,
gave us for free.
What is that?
It's not coincidence I put the thought into it
because I have the self-nature that I can manifest anything.
So know how important, how precious you are.
Use your mind because you are the universe.
You create the universe.
Know yourself completely.
Be confident and know that you can create anything you like.
Lastly, I want to share with you a little story.
There's a monkey that lives in a village.
There's 500 monkeys.
In this village, all the monkeys have one eye.
Except one.
There's only one that has two eyes.
When he was growing up, everybody laughed at him
because he's so different, he's weird.
So he grew up self-conscious and really had no self-esteem.
And had a very depressing childhood.
When the monkey grew up, he said,
OK, I'm going to go outside and see the world.
He went to other places and he saw other monkeys.
All the monkeys have two eyes.
And he's like, oh, I'm not the weird one.
They are the weird ones.
So just know that you have two eyes.
That means you are the perfect self-nature.
You are not who you think you are.
You're not this person with this identity,
with this family, with this mom and dad.
You're not this person.
You are the perfect self-nature
that is the creator of the universe,
that is holy and divine.
It doesn't matter what religion you are.
Just know who you are.
Keep meditating, keep meditating.
You quiet your mind, then you will find your true self-nature.
So that's the class for today.
Hope you enjoy and keep on meditating.
Thank you.