Today we are going to talk about the Dharma door of non-duality.
This is from the Mimalakirti Sutra.
It talks about the concept of non-duality.
Hopefully it will help us live a life that follows wisdom and happiness.
In terms of non-duality, first we have to talk about the two truths.
One is called the ultimate truth.
Two is called the conventional truth.
The ultimate truth is what we call the absolute truth.
The conventional truth is what we call the relative truth.
So everything has two aspects.
The ultimate truth, the thing that is invisible, that is its essence.
And there is always the conventional truth, what appears in form.
What we can see that is visible.
So one is substance, that is invisible, that is the heart, that is the mind.
And one is the form, that is visible, that is the phenomenon.
So this is the inner truth, this is the phenomenon.
So in terms of phenomenon,
it's always in duality,
such as pure, impure, transcendental, mundane, attention, distraction.
Good, evil, self, others, large, small.
Non-duality, duality.
We need to see the world without duality
because they are in oppositions.
Oppositions, they are not the essence.
They always have obstructions.
We want to live in this conventional world
but enter into the substance,
the inner truth, the mind of all things.
That's why we call enlightenment.
Forms always have forms.
Because of conditions arising,
substance is without forms.
It is what it is.
So they are not the same, but they are not different.
They are not apart from each other.
You always have form.
You always have substance.
You just need to see that the forms are illusory.
They are unreal.
Then you will see the true substance,
the true inner truth.
We will explain this non-duality
in terms of the two truths
with examples from chapters of the Mimalakirti Sutra.
First, let's look at the difference
between pure and impure.
In the very first chapter,
it talks about the pure land.
How does the pure land come about?
If our mind is pure,
then the land is pure.
The land is the result of the cause,
which is always our mind.
So if you want to make this world a better place,
you change your mind.
You purify your mind.
That's called true pure land.
After Sariputra heard this,
he had a thought.
This world is so impure.
Shakyamuni Buddha must be such an impure bodhisattva.
That's why this world is so corrupted.
Buddha is all-knowing.
He heard his thought.
Buddha said,
Sariputra, do not think this world is impure.
This world is impure
only because your mind is impure.
If you will only see how I see this world,
so Buddha put his big toe on the ground.
All of a sudden,
everybody saw this world as Buddha sees it.
It's full of splendors, virtues, and precious jewels.
It's the most beautiful, perfect world.
Sariputra realized,
I never saw this world as Buddha saw it.
The world is pure to the extent that your mind is pure.
So the difference between pure
and impure,
it's only your mind.
So that's the first chapter.
Now let's talk about transcendental and mundane.
Some people might want to live in the monastics,
thinking that's better to cultivate.
They don't want to be in this world
full of ordinary people with worldly desires.
The second chapter,
layman Mimalakarti.
He is not a monk.
He's a super wealthy businessman with wife and children.
But he is more religious than any monk that we know.
He goes to brothels to demonstrate the evil of sexual desires.
And he goes to casinos to teach them not to be attached to gambling.
And he goes to bars to teach drunks to have mindfulness.
He can mix into any crowd
and eloquently expand the Dharma.
He lives in non-duality.
To him, there is no difference between being a layman
or being in the monastics
because his mind is so firm in the Dharma.
So that's the second chapter.
The third chapter,
duality of attention and distraction.
We often sit in quiet meditation,
put our attention on mindfulness.
We think that's the best way to cultivate.
But in the sutra,
it talks about how distraction and attention are not so different.
In the third chapter,
Mimalakarti manifested to be sick
in order to expand incredible Dharma.
All Buddha's disciples,
they were all reluctant to pay him a visit
because Mimalakarti always corrected their Dharma.
For example,
Shraputra,
one time he was sitting under a tree meditating.
Mimalakarti came and said,
that's not the way to absorb in contemplation.
That's not how you meditate.
You should meditate in such a way
that you manifest ordinary behavior
without forsaking cessation.
Which means you should just be in meditation
in your daily experience
while sitting, standing, eating,
in ordinary behaviors.
And also,
you should absorb in contemplation
so the mind is neither settled within
nor moves without in the external form.
There is no difference between attention and distraction.
It's all how your mind is dwelling
in the non-duality
of your one true mind,
your true suchness.
Now let's talk about the duality
in terms of good and evil.
One of the Bodhisattva,
his name is maintained in the world.
One time he was at home.
Mara disguised himself as Indra,
the god,
appeared with 12,000 goddesses.
And he said,
I would like to give these goddesses to you.
This Bodhisattva said,
I'm a cultivator.
It's not proper for me to have these goddesses.
All of a sudden,
Vimala Kirti appeared and said,
This is not Indra.
This is actually Mara.
He is trying to ridicule you
to give you these goddesses.
Mara is very distressed
and he wanted to flee.
But a voice in the sky said,
You better give the 12,000 goddesses to him
then you can leave.
So he gave the goddesses
to Vimala Kirti.
Vimala Kirti started teaching these goddesses Dharma.
They all became enlightened
and had great Bodhi resolve.
After a while,
Mara came back to take these goddesses back.
Because the goddesses are now Bodhisattvas.
They don't want to go back to the palace of the Mara.
But Mara insists on taking them back.
So Vimala Kirti said,
Don't worry.
You can go back to where you came from.
Because I'm going to teach you
the doorway of inexhaustible lamp.
Go back to this place of the Mara.
You are now a lamp.
One lamp can light up hundreds and thousands of lamps
without itself being diminished.
You will be like a Bodhisattva.
One lighting up the others.
The realm of Mara will be lit up.
They will all have Bodhi resolve.
And reach enlightenment.
So go back without being afraid.
The goddesses heard of this Dharma
and went back with Mara.
So there is no difference between good and evil.
It's all in your heart.
Even if you are in a very corrupted environment,
you can still teach them Dharma
and change them into Bodhisattvas.
The duality between good and evil
should be let go.
Be an inexhaustible lamp.
Now let's talk about the difference
between self and others.
In the fifth chapter,
Bodhisattva Manjushri
paid a visit to Vimalakirti.
He said,
How come you are sick?
My sickness comes from the sickness
of all living beings.
Because living beings are sick,
that's why I am sick.
There is no difference to him
between self and others.
All other sentient beings,
they are like his only child.
Only if this child is cured,
then he will be cured.
And he talks about how we are sick.
We are all sick
because we think this body,
this self,
is permanent and is me.
We have a strong ego
thinking this is the self.
Vimalakirti is using his sickness
to teach us that we are all sick,
thinking there is a real me,
a real self.
That's why we are all selfish.
Out of his great compassion,
he is trying to show us
how sick we are.
So the whole society is sick,
the entire world is sick,
because our mind is not in the right place.
We are not back to this non-duality,
the substance of our mind.
This true nature,
now let's talk about
the duality between large and small.
We think large and small is an opposition,
but to a Bodhisattva,
there is actually no opposition.
In the sixth chapter,
with Bodhisattva Manjushri,
everybody came with him
to visit Vimalakirti.
So the empty room had to fit
hundreds and thousands of people.
Sir Puca thought,
oh, how can we have no place to sit?
Vimalakirti, he did a miraculous feat
by transforming 32,000 chairs
into his little room.
How did these 32,000 chairs
fit in his little room?
Because there is no difference
between large and small
in terms of the mind,
in terms of the essence.
The difference between
large and small is only concept.
But mundane,
we don't know the difference.
That's why to us,
they are in opposition.
The largest mountain in Buddhism
is Mount Sumeru.
Mount Sumeru can fit into a mustard seed
without having to enlarge the mustard seed
or shrink the mountain.
Why?
Because to a Bodhisattva,
there is no difference between
large and small.
For example,
your mind is so small in this little skull,
but all the books you have studied
your entire life,
it's where?
It's here.
The book doesn't fit in here,
but it's all in your brain.
So in terms of the mind,
the substance,
the inner truth,
there is no duality.
There is no opposition of any kind.
Lastly, in chapter nine,
it actually talks directly
about the Dharma door of non-duality.
33 Bodhisattvas,
they talk about what is duality,
such as what is pure,
impure,
transcendental,
mundane,
attention,
distraction,
good,
and evil.
They talk about all these.
At the end,
Bodhisattva Manjushri
asked Vimalakirti,
how do we enter
the principle of non-duality?
Vimalakirti,
he kept his silence.
He did not speak a word.
Bodhisattva Manjushri said,
wonderful, wonderful.
That is the way
to enter non-duality.
Because non-duality
is without syllables,
without words,
without concepts.
In this substance,
in this ultimate truth,
in our pure mind,
there is no concepts,
no words,
no language
that need to be said.
That is true non-duality.
In conclusion,
what we need to do
is be like a Buddha
who is an expert
in the deep analysis of things,
yet dwells
in the ultimate meaning.
This summarizes
these two truths.
We need to live
in this conventional world,
still be an expert
in analyzing
all the differences.
There is still difference
because we live in this world
between pure and impure,
between transcendental and mundane.
It's just that
you dwell in this ultimate meaning,
which is the substance,
without any visible forms.
Be away from duality inside,
but you still live
this conventional life,
which means you are not attached
to anyone or anything
because all the forms,
all the duality you see
are only illusory.
It's like things happening in a dream.
They're only concepts of the mind.
That is what we call
true enlightenment.
This is the highest dharma,
the principle of non-duality.
Doesn't matter if you're a layman
or you're a monk
or you live in a pure world right now
or a very corrupted world,
nothing really matters.
What matters is where you reside,
where you dwell in this heart
that is without any opposition,
no judgment.
We call it the true suchness.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.