Today we are going to talk about No Thought, No Mark, and No Dwelling.
This is from the Platform Sutra of the Sixth Patriarch of Zen Buddhism, Master Huineng.
He said this is the three pillars of Zen Buddhism.
No thought is the doctrine of Zen Buddhism.
No mark is the substance of Zen Buddhism.
And no dwelling is the basis of Zen Buddhism.
Let's first look at no thought.
What does it mean by no thought?
It is to be without thought while in the midst of thought.
No means no two marks, no thought of defilement.
Thought means thought of the original nature of true suchness.
So to be without thought while in the midst of thought.
We cannot be without thoughts, but we should have the state of no thought.
No means no two marks, which means no duality of good and bad, large or small, pure or impure.
We all think in terms of dualism.
That means we are labeling and we are judging.
So no thought means no judging, no labeling, and no thought of defilement.
All dualism is considered defilement.
Our natural state of mind should be without defilement.
Thought means thought of the original nature of true suchness.
The real thought means when we are aligned with our true suchness.
That's our Buddha nature.
When we are aligned with our Buddha nature, our thought should be no thought.
What is the state of no thought?
It's quiescent, which is still and not moved, yet it's shining with awareness.
Shining with awareness.
Yet ever quiescent.
We usually use the metaphor of a mirror.
The mirror itself is quiescent.
It doesn't move.
It doesn't react to the images.
But it's aware, which means it can reflect all the images clearly.
Our mind should be in this state, like the perfect mirror.
That's the state of no thought.
No thought doesn't mean we get rid of all thoughts.
Master Hui Nan said if we get rid of all thoughts,
even at the time of our death, we have no thought,
we still keep reincarnating.
We think to be completely without thought is no thought.
Then you misunderstood the Dharma.
And if you pass it down to others, that is blandering the Dharma.
So do not think it's completely without thoughts.
It is just being quiescent and shining with awareness.
Master Hui Nan, he was a poor, illiterate lumberjack.
When the fifth patriarch, Hong Ren, passed him the robe and the bowl,
which means passing down the lineage of Zen Buddhism,
everyone was jealous and upset with him.
So he had to run away and hide.
The first person that caught up to him was a monk named Hui Ming.
He was a general of the fourth rank when he was a layman.
So he's very strong, very powerful.
Once he caught up to the master,
the master put the robe and the bowl on the rock
and hid himself in the bushes.
Hui Ming immediately tried to take the robe and the bowl.
But for the life of him, he could not move them.
He knew something was mysterious.
Being a practitioner, he immediately changed his attitude.
He said,
I came here for the Dharma, not for the robe.
That's when the master came out of the bushes.
He said,
If you really came for the Dharma,
you should refrain from thinking of anything
and keep your mind blank.
Then I will teach you.
So they sat in silence for a long while.
Finally, the master said,
When you are thinking of neither good or evil,
what is at that particular moment is your real nature.
As soon as Hui Ming heard this,
he at once became enlightened.
So we should keep our mind at the state of no thought,
no dualism of good or evil.
That is the true state of mind that we should be at.
That's when we are aligning ourselves with our true suchness.
Now let's look at no mark.
No mark means to be apart from marks while in the midst of marks.
Mark means phenomenon or forms.
Everything we see in the world is considered a mark.
So we have all these existences in the world,
but we are detached from them.
We see everything, we hear everything,
but we are not attached to them.
The ability to be separate from marks is the purity of the Dharma substance.
We should have the ability to detach ourselves from all the phenomenon.
That is when our mind is pure,
our Dharma substance, which is our true suchness,
it will surface.
So only when your mind doesn't have defiled thought,
no judgment of the outside phenomenon,
that's when we are aligning ourselves with our real nature.
That is enlightenment.
That is prajna.
In the Diamond Sutra,
it teaches us to be away from four forms.
The form of the self,
form of others,
form of people,
form of life span.
Therefore we should not have the idea of the self.
The form of a self,
form of another who is separate from us,
form of everyone else,
all the beings in the world,
and form of time.
So time and state,
self and other,
these are all phenomenon.
All phenomenon are just illusions created by our mind.
So detach from the form.
Though they have conditioned existence right now,
but be detached,
that means our mind doesn't have afflictions or emotions
based on the external world.
So that means no mark.
That's the substance of Zen Buddhism.
Lastly, no dwelling.
In every thought,
do not think of former states.
We should not let our thought keep continuing
from one thought
to another.
When we have succeeding thoughts
after thought without interruption,
that is bondage.
That is why we are reincarnating.
Reincarnation doesn't just mean
lifetime and lifetime of rebirth.
It means in our mind,
our thought keep going
and going in a vicious cycle.
This cycle is reincarnation.
So if we want to be reincarnated,
we have to be free from reincarnation.
We have to learn
so our mind does not dwell
in thought after thought.
Master Hui Nan says,
in the world of good and evil,
attractiveness and ugliness,
friendliness and hostility,
when you are faced with language
which is offensive, critical and argumentative,
you should treat it all as empty
and have no thought of revenge.
So in all worldly experience of duality,
do not have defiled thoughts.
That is called no dwelling.
Not to dwell in dharmas
from thought to thought
is to be free from bondage.
Free from the bondage of our mind.
The fourth patriarch of Zen Buddhism,
his name is Daoxin.
He became a monk
when he was only seven years old.
When he was fourteen,
he went to visit the third patriarch,
Sen Can.
When he arrived,
he asked the master,
Master, please teach me
the dharma of liberation.
The master asked him,
Who tied you up?
The young monk thought about it
for a long time and answered,
No one.
Then the master said,
If no one is tying you up,
why do you need the dharma of liberation?
As soon as he heard this,
he at once became enlightened.
So who is tying you up?
It's not the people around you.
It's not your situation.
It's only your attachment
to your own thought.
That is reincarnation.
So enlightenment means
we do not dwell
in our thought after thought.
In conclusion,
if one is well able
to discriminate all dharma marks,
then in the primary meanings,
one does not move.
This is from the Mimalakirti Sutra.
If we are well able
to discriminate
all the phenomena of the world,
we can see,
we can hear,
we can feel,
we can know
everything clearly.
But we do not move
because we dwell in the primary meaning,
which is the true suchness.
Therefore our mind
should not be moved
by all the phenomena in the world.
That's when we have
real liberation.
So Zen Buddhism
is to teach us
in our prajna,
samadhi,
we should have
no thought,
no mark,
and no dwelling.
That should be
our natural state of mind.
That's when our mind
is aligned
with our Buddha nature.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community