Today we are going to talk about Two Resolutions.
How come we can never change what we want to do with our lives?
We cannot put it into fruition.
We are going to talk about the Shakyamuni Sutra, Two Resolutions.
Hopefully we will find out the problem of our cultivation and our lives.
The first resolution, you must carefully consider whether the resolve on the cause ground and
the enlightenment on the ground of fruition are the same or different.
We want to reach Buddhahood, that's the ground of fruition that we want.
But what is your cause?
You must have the right cause in order to have the right result.
So what is the cause?
We don't have the right cause to begin with.
We are all stuck with our five aggregates.
We are using the deluded mind, that's why we cannot reach enlightenment.
Right now we are using these five aggregates thinking that's me.
That's why we are creating the world of five turbidities.
We have the turbidity of time because we are all stuck with our form.
We are very selfish.
We are all attached to the body, that's why the world is so corrupted.
Then we have the turbidity of views.
We only care about our own feelings, our own happiness.
Everybody is chasing after their own self-benefit, that's why the views are corrupted.
We have the turbidity of afflictions.
We are all caught up in ourselves.
We are all caught up in our own thinking, thinking about the past, future, present,
all based on the self.
And all living beings are corrupted because we have the mental formation of the strong
self.
Everybody has deep attachment to the ego.
Lastly, our lifespan is very corrupted, short and whimsical because we are attached to our
consciousness, it's the deluded self.
We are using the five aggregates.
So what is your cause?
The cause is the real me, but that should not be your cause ground because this is all
based on cause and condition.
We must decisively renounce this pseudo-self, condition, appearance.
This is not the real me.
If you rely on this view to cultivate, you will not succeed no matter how hard you chant
the Buddha's name, how hard you meditate.
You will not reach Buddhahood.
For example, why are you listening to the Dharma or why are you a Buddhist?
You don't even know why we are still using the selfish self to cultivate.
We will never reach the right fruition.
So let go of this attachment to the self.
First, carefully consider.
That means recognize.
If you start off the wrong foot, you will not reach the right destination.
Clarify.
It's like we are trying to purify muddy water.
Put it in a clean vessel that is still and unmoved.
All of the sand and slits will settle to the bottom, then you will have clean water.
So, that's why we can clean this turbulent, dirty water by residing in our perfect, tranquil
nature that does not rise or cease.
There is neither production nor extinction.
Then we will completely accomplish the cultivation of, and you will experience rescuing, reappointment.
No matter how cuz, it's a better explanation.
off and the certification to the ground of fruition so if you really want to reach buddhahood
you have to start with the buddha mind that does not go with your selfish self that is the first
resolution you must tell yourself no more selfish pseudo self the five aggregates decisively
renounce it when you're not attached to this selfish eye anymore that's when you can start
cultivating figure this out in the first place the first patriarch of zen buddhism is bodhidharma
the second patriarch is huike when huike first met bodhidharma he was in the cave meditating
facing the wall and ignoring him so huike stayed outside
in the snow the snow was covering his knees he was still with reverence standing in the snow
waiting for the master to speak to him the master ignored him for many many days finally to express
his sincerity in trying to find the dharma he cut his left arm the blood splashed everywhere
on the snow that's when bodhidharma asked him what do you want huike said your disciples mind
has no peace as yet master please put it to rest bodhidharma said bring me your mind
i will put it to rest huike said i have searched for my mind i cannot find it then bodhidharma
said i have completely put it to rest for you at that moment just one sentence with the master
he was completely enlightened and he became the
second patriarch of zen buddhism so he completely let go of his attachment to his body to his
feelings to his perception his mental formation his consciousness that's why he was able to let
go of his arm we're not asking you to have this kind of resolution but at least stop complaining
about your human existence little pain in the body here and there or how bad you feel
or
how horrible your life is if you keep thinking the human thoughts with your human mind
it's not gonna bring you into enlightenment stop thinking in terms of the five aggregates
attaching to the aggregate will only cause you to stay in the reincarnation we must have firm
resolution the second resolution you should carefully consider the origin of a fiction
and the beginningless creation of karma and perpetuation of rebirth
who creates it and who endures it the second question you must ponder upon it deeply
what is the origin of your afflictions why do you keep having greed anger and ignorance it is very
painful you don't know how to stop it you don't even know how to cultivate how to change yourself
you don't know the origin of your afflictions. So Buddha asked us to figure it out. What
is the origin? Why do you keep having reincarnation lifetime after lifetime? Who is creating this
affliction that's causing samsara and who is enduring the samsara? It is you. But what
about you that is causing it? What is the root? So Buddha tells us the answer. The origin
of your affliction is actually your sixth sense organs. Your eyes, your ears, your nose,
your tongue, your body and your mind. That is the origin of your afflictions. You don't
even know that. You never thought your sixth sense organs are the thief, the thief of your
life, that's stealing your treasure at home. We have the Buddha nature at home. But the
thief is stealing it. We call it the thieving matchmaker that's plundering the jewels of
your household. Why do we call it the thieving matchmaker? It's like the agent. You have
the external sixth sense objects, the outside thieves of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch
and dharma.
We have the agent, the organs in between. Then we have the inner thieves, the sixth
sense consciousness, the eye consciousness, ear consciousness, nose consciousness, all
the way to the mind consciousness. That is the problem. Now we have to cultivate. Start
cultivating from here. This is where we fall. This is where we get up. So what we need to
do is to untie the knot.
Of our sixth sense organs. If you don't know where the knots are, how are you going to
untie it? So the knots are in the sixth sense organs. We need to untie them. Pick a sense
organ to return from. The sutra teaches to pick the ears. Just like Guan Yin Bodhisattva.
She became enlightened by cultivating her hearing. She entered the fruit of the Bodhisattva.
She flowed through hearing and forgot all objective states. She was able to let go
of all the sens. She does not hear the outside sounds anymore. She hears it, but is not caught
up with it. Her mind is always inward toward her true buddha nature. She has an owner at
home. It's not we don't hear, we don't see anymore, we closed everything. No, we still
see we still hear but we collect them inward we are still intact at home your
shelter from the outside wind and the storm all the outside conditions should
not affect your peace of mind should not affect your samadhi should not affect
your presence and your emotions if your emotions are always controlled by the
outside experience you will never become enlightened so you must collect them
inward you still see you still hear but you always have an owner guarding it at
home you're not completely going out to experience the world like a wild kid
doesn't know how to come home we know how to come back we always stay at home
experiencing the world as a person who has
something to do with the world and the world is not a place for you to be
this inner awakening extract one organ from adhesion free it subdue it from its
inner core once subdued it will return to the inherent truth and radiate the
inner brilliance we just need to extract one organ for example the ears from its
adhesion to sound free it and subdue it once it's subdued from the
inner core our true buddha nature will surface we will glow with the inner
brilliance in conclusion reject production and extinction and uphold
true permanence reject all rising and seizing any conditioned appearance such
as the five aggregate or the six sense organs let them go reject all the conditioned existence
and we uphold the true permanence there is something that is permanent not
moving with the external condition that is our true nature that is perfectly
tranquil and pure and calm that's where we should reside so we need to let go of
our attachment to the five aggregates because that is not the right cause
ground let go of the selfish싱
ground let go of the selfish
self the selfish eye let them go one layer at a time like peeling off an onion first detach
ourselves from our body it's not permanent it's not me do not be attached to our feelings of
pleasure displeasure don't be attached to our thinking our concepts our ideas don't be attached
to the strong sense of self don't be attached to our consciousness none of them is me this is to
peel one layer at a time and the sixth organ is to pick one if you can just purify one and all of
them will be pure simultaneously this is the secret to our cultivation we are not really
cultivating until we have these two resolutions
Now we know Buddhism is like someone is giving us a mansion.
There's so many windows and doors,
but we don't know how to get in.
No matter how much sutra you read,
how much you cultivate, how much you meditate,
you don't know how to get into this house.
Even if you buy all the furniture,
try to decorate it by doing a lot of practice,
you are still outside.
You are still in the wind.
You're still under the rain.
You're still homeless.
You are not inside yet.
You need to make these two resolutions.
Stop chasing the selfish self.
Stop following with your sense organs.
Go inward to your true self, to your true permanence.
Then you can get into the house.
That's when your cultivation and the certification
of the ground of fruition will be complete,
which is real Buddhahood.
Hopefully.
You've figured out how to cultivate
and the problem that is stopping you
from improving this lifetime.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.