Today we are going to talk about motivating yourself.
We all want to be a hero, a man of greatness, reaching excellence.
But how do we motivate ourselves to keep going when we face a lot of obstacles?
Today we will discuss Mencius' great quote on motivation.
Hopefully it will inspire you to succeed in all your endeavors.
When the Heaven is about to place a great responsibility on one man,
it always first frustrates his spirit and will, exhausts his muscles and bones,
exposes him to starvation and poverty, harasses him by troubles and setbacks.
When the Heaven is about to place a great responsibility on one man,
this great responsibility is becoming a saint and a sage, reaching Buddhahood.
We have a calling, we are inheriting the Buddha's family business
of saving all sentient beings out of reincarnation.
That's a heroic mission.
We need to be trained in four ways.
First, it frustrates his spirit.
He would be trained in a lot of hardships and difficulties.
The struggles and the hardships are our teachers that will make us grow spiritually.
Confucius had a student, his name is Ziqian Ming.
His mother passed away when he was young.
His father remarried and he was raised by his stepmother.
His stepmother gave birth to two younger brothers but mistreated Ziqian.
He was often verbally and physically abused, but Ziqian never had any complaint and never had any resentment toward his stepmother.
In the winter, the stepmother would line the clothing of her own children with warm cotton and would line Ziqian's clothing with weeds.
One day, it was snowing. His father asked him to drive the carriage.
So Ziqian was shivering uncontrollably and lost control of the carriage.
So his father was furious and whipped him with the horse whip, his clothes ripped, and all the weed petals came out.
The father realized that his son was being abused by his stepmother.
They immediately went home, and the dad wanted to divorce the stepmother.
But Ziqian sincerely pleaded,
Father, when mother is here,
only I am cold.
If mother leaves, then three of us would be cold.
The father let stepmom stay, and stepmother was very touched and felt ashamed of her behavior.
From that day on, she changed her way, and the family lived in harmony ever since.
So by the virtue of this great boy, he changed the life of the family.
So through hardship,
our greatness and virtue comes out.
We say the most neglected child is usually the more mature, more successful, and has the most filial piety.
So no matter how hard your family life is,
you want to bring out your filial piety, your respect, and love.
Number two, exhaust his muscles and bones.
Just like you want to be a professional athlete,
you need to train diligently.
With discipline, and go through all the hardcore trainings.
There were two rocks and a sculptor.
The sculptor went to the first rock and started carving.
But the first rock started complaining,
ouch, you're hurting me, you're hurting me, stop it.
The rock kept complaining, so the sculptor could not take it anymore,
and said, fine, you take a break, I will work on the second rock.
So he went to the second rock and started carving,
and the second rock said, I will not make a sound,
I will endure any kind of pain and difficulties.
The sculptor calmly carved for two weeks,
and finally made a magnificent statue of Shakyamuni Buddha.
Thousands of people came to pay respect and worship the statue.
So they needed something to lie on the ground,
so people can prostrate and bow on.
So they decided to break the first rock,
into little pieces of pebbles for people to bow on.
If you can endure the pain in the working process,
you will definitely reach greatness at the end.
Just like a stone we want to make into a piece of artwork,
into a jade, we need to polish and grind over and over,
until it becomes a masterpiece of artwork.
Number three,
exposes him to starvation and poverty.
In Taiwan, there was a nun.
Before she became a nun, she was a doctor of oncology.
One day came a 50-year-old breast cancer patient.
Her medicine was not yet approved by the insurance.
She felt a great financial burden,
and she felt the great pain of her sickness.
So uncontrollably, she started crying.
Next door, there was also a 30-year-old breast cancer patient.
She overheard the whole thing,
and asked the doctor to go outside.
And she whispered to the doctor,
Can you please give this money to that lady?
Because we are all suffering the same fate.
I just want to be able to help her in any way I can.
The doctor was extremely touched,
because she knew this lady
is even in greater hardship than the first lady.
Her child is still an infant,
and her husband doesn't make much money,
and she doesn't even have insurance.
For many times, because she didn't have enough money,
she forfeited treatment.
So she's going through so much hardship,
and she can still find it in her heart to help a stranger.
So the harder the hardship,
the greater we have to hold on to our virtues.
And our compassion.
Just like the cherry blossom,
the colder it gets, the prettier it blooms.
Number four, harasses him by troubles and setbacks.
Even if you work very hard,
you might still face a lot of troubles and setbacks.
Just like Buddha's disciple,
Purna Maitrayani Putra.
One day he asked Buddha,
May I please go to that remote country
and teach Buddhism?
Buddha said, Are you sure?
They are all very vicious and barbaric.
What if they started berating you?
Purna said, I will still be very thankful.
At least they didn't hit me with a stick.
And Buddha said, What if they start hitting you with a stick?
Purna said, I will still be thankful.
At least they didn't use a blade to cut me.
Buddha said, What if they start using a blade to cut you?
Purna said, I will still be thankful.
At least they didn't kill me.
Buddha said, What if they killed you?
Purna said, I will still be so thankful.
I will have reached Nirvana.
Buddha said, With this great determination and boldly resolve,
you can now go.
So he went to the country.
Everybody hated him and started berating him.
But he didn't care.
He went to the hospital and started taking care of the sick.
Then he started to teach them how to read and write.
And gave them education.
He showed them how to farm the land so they would have food for themselves.
Finally, he earned the trust of all the people.
And then that's when he started teaching them Dharma.
Soon the entire country became Buddhist.
And he built a Sangha of 500 people.
No matter how hard and how much troubles and setbacks,
we have to keep going until we reach our goal.
Just like to make iron ore into steel.
We need to keep burning it in high heat.
And pound it and burn it over and over until it becomes useful steel.
So the result is,
toughen our spirit,
soften our nature,
and enhance our abilities.
So first we need to toughen our spirit.
This is the Voi meditation.
Which means understanding the emptiness of all obstacles.
No matter how big the obstacle seems,
it's only in our mind.
It's not real.
There's no obstacle too big for you.
You want to have the steel backbone.
Always go toward your greatness and your virtue.
And never give up no matter how hard the situation may seem.
Second, you want to soften your nature.
Train yourself in this unreal world.
This is the unreal meditation.
Which means in this unreal conditioned existence,
we want to be the best that we can be.
Be tolerant and forgiving toward everybody.
Inside, you are tough.
On the outside, you need to train yourself to be extremely soft.
So you don't have an ounce of resentment toward anything or anyone.
Finally, you will enhance your abilities.
That's the Ming meditation.
When you balance the Voi and the unreal,
when you balance the toughness and the softness,
you will come to great ability.
You now are able to take on the great responsibility
of becoming a saint and a sage that's going to save the world.
This world is a Buddha selecting field.
You want to be the chosen one to take on the great responsibility
of saying being awesome.
To become a saint and being,
you need to go through the hardship and the obstacles.
Each of us is responsible for the fate of our family,
our country, our world.
So it's now time for us to bring out the best in us.
Use the hardship to bring out our great compassion,
our great innate wisdom,
our determination, our virtue and nobility.
So together,
we will prevail.
There's definitely light at the end of the tunnel.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Aum Tofu.