Today we will talk about realization.
Buddha is the enlightened one who realized the truth about life and reached ultimate happiness.
In this class, we will learn about what is realization.
This is a verse from the Eight Realizations Sutra.
It says,
Realize that this world is impermanent, that nations are unsafe and unstable,
that the four elements cause suffering and are empty,
that there is no self within the five skandhas,
that all things that arise must change and decline,
and that they are false appearances without any stable essence,
that the mind is a source of evil,
and that the form is a congregation of wrongdoings.
Contemplate all of this,
and gradually you will disentangle yourself from the cycle of birth and death.
I numbered them as ten lines.
Number one is realize that this world is impermanent.
There are two kinds of impermanence.
One is called the impermanence of continuance.
This is talking about our lifetime.
In the continuity of life,
we must go through aging and decline.
That is impermanence.
The other impermanence is called the subtle impermanence.
It's talking about moment-to-moment impermanence.
Everything is causing conditions,
therefore the conditions are always changing,
so the world is constantly changing.
Just like two years ago,
we would never guess the world would be plagued by the coronavirus.
That is a big shock to us.
But if we really understand
that this virus is expounding the dharma of impermanence,
we will no longer be afraid.
We will accept this phenomenon
and actively use this impermanence
to come into spiritual awakening.
So when we really realize impermanence,
it will help us sever our attachment to the mundane world,
and it will also bring our great compassion
to everyone who is suffering right now.
Number two,
the nations of the world.
The nations are unsafe and unstable.
All the countries right now are unsafe
because of the virus, the politics, and economics.
Nobody is for sure.
So when it's uncertain and unstable,
we feel suffering.
But a person can still have inner peace
in a chaotic world.
It just takes a lot of meditation and wisdom.
When we really understand impermanence,
we will accept the current condition
and actually create positive condition
to benefit the world.
Number three,
that the four elements cause suffering
and are empty.
The four elements are earth, water, fire, and wind.
These four elements make up the world
and make up our body.
Because they're conditioned existence,
they're always changing.
They cause suffering
and is empty in nature.
When we really let go of our attachment
to the four elements,
to our body,
then we will see our true nature.
In the Shogama Sutra, it says,
the nature of form is true emptiness,
and the nature of emptiness is true form.
So when you let go of all your attachment
to form, to water, to fire, to wind,
then you will see your true essence.
So in the sutra, it talks about
King Parson Nagya.
He was having a conversation with Buddha.
Buddha asked him,
is your body indestructible
or is subject to decay?
The king replied,
this body of mine will constantly change
until it perish.
Buddha said, so it is.
You are in your declining years.
How do you look compared to when you were a boy?
Because now the king is 62,
the same age as Buddha.
The king replied,
when I was a boy,
my skin was fresh and smooth,
but now my hair is white
and my face is wrinkled.
Buddha said, did this happen suddenly?
The king replied, no,
it's subtle transformation.
It happened decade by decade,
year by year,
month by month,
day by day,
instant by instant,
and thought by thought.
I know my body will keep changing
until it's extinct.
But Buddha said,
your face is wrinkled,
but your nature is not wrinkled.
What wrinkles is subject to change,
what does not wrinkle does not change.
Your nature is fundamentally free
from production and extinction.
Therefore, it's not subject to birth or death.
The king heard this,
really believed in it,
and he felt this great delight and dharma joy
because he does not have to be afraid of death anymore.
When you see suffering and emptiness in the form,
that's when you find
your true nature.
Number four,
that there is no self within the five skandhas.
The five skandhas are
our form,
our feelings,
our perception,
mental formation,
and consciousness.
So the body and mind,
there is no self.
Everyone is clinging to the five aggregates
as the self,
but it's actually not.
So we have to see emptiness
and relinquish.
Only when we relinquish our attachment
to the five aggregates
can we be free from suffering
because attaching to the five aggregates
is causing the suffering
and the reincarnation.
So we need to understand non-self.
The five aggregates is not me.
There was a 50-year-old patient.
Her stomach was bleeding,
so the doctors had to use a feeding tube through her nose.
And because the hospital was too crowded,
she had to sleep in the hallway.
And when people sleep in the hallway,
they always have to hear lots of complaints.
But this woman is a devout Buddhist.
In the morning, she woke up.
She told the doctor,
good morning, doctor.
The air is great in this hospital.
I already finished my morning recitation
and I'm very happy.
The doctor was very surprised to hear that from her
because she has a feeding tube through her nose
and she's in the hallway.
But she was so cheerful and happy.
After the exam, the doctor told her,
you actually have late stage liver cancer.
This lady was still smiling and said calmly,
if I live for one day,
I will serve Amitabha and serve others.
And when it's time for me to go,
Amitabha will come take me.
So she was calm when she heard the diagnosis.
Many months after she was supposed to die,
the doctor called and asked about her.
Surprisingly, she is still healthy,
still going to other temples,
helping out everyone learn Buddhism,
and is still spreading hope and love to everybody.
So this is a Bodhisattva that understands no self.
She let go of her attachment to her body
and to her ego.
All she does is to serve others.
That is a true Bodhisattva.
These four, truth, impermanence, suffering,
emptiness, and non-self,
we need to contemplate in order to come to
true realization about suffering,
the first noble truth.
The next lines further explain these four truths.
Number five, that all things that arise
must change and decline.
We talk about everything in terms of its changes.
So it goes through our thoughts arising,
abiding, changing, and declining.
Our body goes through birth, aging, sickness, and death.
And the world goes through formation, existence,
disintegration, and emptiness.
So everything goes through cycles.
This is just telling us it's impermanent
and it's causing suffering.
So this is describing number one,
impermanence, in detail.
You might ask, what is wrong with arising
or with birth?
We actually like birth.
Birth is actually the biggest culprit of suffering.
And the sutra, it gives a metaphor of four robbers.
There were four robbers that were trying to rob this person.
So one of the robbers disguised as a very nice person
to lure the person to come out.
When the person comes out,
the three other robbers
attack the person.
So the first robber that's disguised
is actually birth.
And the other three are aging, sickness, and death.
So when we have arising,
there must be ceasing.
That is impermanence.
Number six,
and that they are false appearances
without any stable essence.
False appearances is talking about suffering.
And without any stable essence
is talking about emptiness.
Everything you see is a false appearance.
We are being deceived by ourselves.
We are actually the person
that is causing the cage of reincarnation.
And we don't even know.
Just like all the virtual reality rides
in the amusement park.
It's just a projection with special effect
that we think is so real and so fun.
But it's actually a delusion.
This life is full of false appearances.
Do not be attached to them.
When you're attached,
you don't see the truth.
Without any stable essence,
which means everything is empty in nature.
That means it doesn't have a permanent,
independent, and controlling self nature.
Number seven and eight,
that the mind is the source of evil
and that the form is a congregation
of wrong doings.
This is talking about number four,
which is non-self.
Our body and mind is not the real us.
If it's the real us,
why do we have so many evil thoughts
and wrong doings?
If we can control it,
why will we create negative karma for ourselves?
So it's actually all conditioned seeds
from our elia consciousness
that's causing us to be more deluded
and keep creating reincarnation for ourselves.
So realize that your mind and body
is not the real you.
Let go of your self ego.
That's the only way to cultivate.
If you keep cultivating
and you still hold on to the self,
we will never succeed.
Just like if you go up to the mountain
and hide there to be in solitude
and meditate,
but you still hold on to the self,
it's still useless cultivation.
So let go of the self.
That's the most important realization.
Contemplate all of this,
impermanence,
suffering,
emptiness,
and non-self.
And gradually,
you will disentangle yourself
from the cycle of birth and death.
You keep realizing these four truths,
you'll be free from birth and death,
which means reincarnation.
So when you really understand this,
you will be a true bodhisattva
who will make the bodhisattva vow
to endure suffering
on behalf of all sentient beings.
So do not ask for
a certain enlightenment.
Just look at your life right now.
See the impermanence,
suffering,
emptiness,
and non-self
in your current life.
And you will find your true nature.
We call it the real mark.
When you really see clearly,
you will be at peace with yourself
and your life.
Then you can influence everyone around you
to be peaceful and happy.
That is a true realized buddhist.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.