Today we are going to talk about mental factors.
This is from the Consciousness Only School of Buddhism.
It talks about the working of our minds to get rid of our defilements and afflictions
and transform our ignorance consciousness into wisdom.
Now let's look at the five universal mental factors and five particular state mental factors.
First look at the five universal mental factors.
It's called universal for four reasons.
One, it happens all the time, two, it happens in all places, three, it happens in all eight
consciousnesses, and four, it happens in all three states.
It happens all the time, that means no matter which realm you're in in this reincarnation,
whether you're a saint or a mundane, you all have these five universal mental factors.
Number two is in all places, doesn't matter which realm you're in, you will have these
mental factors.
Number three, it happens in all eight consciousnesses, your eye consciousness, your ear consciousness,
nose, tongue, body, mind, these are your six consciousnesses.
Number seven is your manas, your seven consciousness, that's how you perceive the idea of the self,
that's your ego.
Then you have the eighth consciousness, the big storehouse.
All eight consciousnesses have these five mental factors.
Number four is universal in three natures of karma.
One is wholesome.
Two is unwholesome.
Three is neutral.
In all three states, you will have these mental factors.
Now let's look at these five mental factors.
Number one is attention.
You pay attention to a certain sense object.
For example, if you're in a party, there's lots of people talking, you will focus your
attention on one person that you're talking to.
Sometimes when you're eating, you don't taste the food that you ate.
Or you're listening to the radio, but the song already passed, but you didn't hear anything.
That's because this mental factor of attention is not working.
We want to bring our attention to the mental object we want to focus on.
In Reader's Digest, there was a funny story.
A young girl, she got her first paycheck.
She was very happy so she went to the mall and got herself a beautiful hat.
She went home, hoping her mom would praise her for the beautiful hat.
Then she was home.
She was very happy.
So she went to the mall and got herself a beautiful hat.
hat but mom was busy cooking didn't say anything didn't even notice at dinner time she showed her
dissatisfaction mom asked what is wrong with you she said i bought this beautiful hat with my first
paycheck but you didn't even notice mom said oh i got my hair permed today you didn't notice either
so everybody only notice what they want to notice we want to choose the mental object that we
pay attention to that is called proper attention when we are meditating or focusing on a mental
object number two is contact so this contact is our sixth sense organ contact with sixth sense
objects then we develop sixth sense consciousness that's how we experience this world our eyes
ears nose tongue body and mind that's the sixth sense organ
come in
come in contact with the sixth sense objects
of sight sound smell taste touch and dharma then we develop sixth sense consciousnesses
that's how we experience this world one day there was a little wasp on the floor
i picked it up and prayed for it chen amitabha for it by coming in contact with this wasp
i feel the impermanence of life that contact was a special experience for me
i know a lot about mandrake pack because
everything he said pretty much every day i was frustrated every day for every posture
i learned a lot about
something but i still feel uncomfortable about it
Unfavorable feelings is when we want to be apart from it.
There is a monkey who was being massaged by a lady.
Because he liked it so much, every time the lady tried to stop,
he would grab her hand and put it on his head, wishing for more massage.
It's a pleasurable feeling for the monkey.
So he wants it to repeat over and over again.
So we can actually choose the feeling.
It's all up to us to feel pleasure or pain.
Number four is perception, our distinguishing thoughts.
Our feelings will affect our perceptions or vice versa.
Every situation, we can choose to have positive, wholesome thoughts.
For example, we should always choose to be kind instead of being right all the time.
We can choose to be grateful instead of complaining.
We can choose not to be offended
and always be grateful.
We can always live in a friendly, happy world.
And we can choose to look at other people's good qualities instead of looking at people's faults.
Always choose to be positive and wholesome, and we will create positive karma for us.
Number five is deliberation.
Careful contemplation is also called a mental urge.
Mental urge to take physical or verbal actions.
This is how we start taking action.
And create karma.
It has three stages.
One is planning.
Two, deciding.
Three, taking actions.
Our deliberation goes through these three steps before we take action to speak or move.
Again, we want to choose wholesome actions and speeches.
There was a man in a very crowded street.
All of a sudden, it started pouring rain.
He saw a lady in a wheelchair.
He had an umbrella.
So he put the umbrella over the lady and escorted her all the way home.
His deliberation helped him decide to take this action of giving.
This is through planning, deciding, and taking action.
Every one thought goes through these five mental factors.
So it's shorter than an instant.
But when we talk about it, it's in five different mental factors.
By understanding the details of our thoughts, we can take action.
We can take action.
We are able to choose positive, wholesome thoughts, and change our karma,
change our lives for the better.
Now, let's look at the five particular state mental factors.
These five factors are not like the universal mental factors.
These five all have to happen.
And it happens in this sequential order.
But these five do not happen all the time.
They only happen in specific situations.
situations. Number one is intention. Intention only happens when we have pleasurable states.
Only things that you like, you will have positive intention. You'll be motivated to keep doing
it. Some people are motivated by money. Some people are motivated by fame. Some people
are motivated to meditate. Everybody is motivated by different states, but all has to be pleasurable
state. So whatever gives you pleasure is what motivates your life to take action. What is
the subject of your motivation is very important. Number two, resolution. Resolution only happens
in states requiring decisiveness. In this state, when we are trying to decide, we will
make a firm conviction, strong belief about certain things. All these can be wholesome
or unwholesome, depending on the state.
For example, we might have a resolution about Pure Land Buddhism. You believe that chanting
the name Amitabha is the most powerful mantra, and once we are chanting, we are immediately
aligned with our Buddha nature. There was a grandma chanting Amitabha, but her grandson
think it's very annoying, so he played a joke on her. One day, he started saying, Grandma,
Grandma, Grandma. In the beginning, grandma thought it was very sweet, but then she started
saying, please stop, this is very annoying. The grandson said, see, if you keep chanting
Amitabha, Amitabha will be so annoyed too. Grandma, she retrogressed and stopped chanting.
That means she doesn't have strong resolution about Pure Land Buddhism. So we have to decide,
make a firm determination and conviction about a certain subject.
Number three is mindfulness. Mindfulness is what states already experience. For example,
if you look at a Buddha picture, once you close your eyes, you still have the image
in your mind. Or you hear a song, after you stop listening to it, you still have the melody
in your mind. That's because we have this mental factor of mindfulness. It always remembers
states that you have experienced before.
This is very useful.
This is very useful because in our meditation, we have a method called visualization or contemplation.
Our mind is very powerful because it remembers. If you want to visualize the Western Pure
Land, you can study the 16 Contemplation Sutra that will teach you how to meditate on Amitabha's
Pure Land. This is very powerful when we remember. We can go into deep meditation with our visualization.
Number four.
Contemplate.
Number four is concentration.
This is what states want to contemplate on.
You have a state, object that you want to focus on, some people are very focused on
their career.
They have a strong mental factor of concentration, they are most likely to succeed in their career.
Some people are very concentrated on playing video games because their mental factor is
very strong.
Some people are stronger, some people are weaker.
Some people are very weak.
If we have a strong concentration in chanting the name Amitabha, we will reach single-pointed
awareness or we call it Buddha Remembrance Samadhi.
All these can be wholesome or unwholesome depending on the subject that you focus on.
A thief can be very concentrated in stealing, but that would be unwholesome, but his concentration
can be very strong as well.
So all depending on your subject of awareness.
Number five, wisdom.
This wisdom is not the wisdom of Prajna.
This wisdom means your ability to make judgments.
It's your distinguishing awareness.
You can distinguish what's good, what's bad.
For example, a thief can have a strong wisdom, mental factor and how to steal.
Everybody has their secret of how to do a certain subject.
That's the wisdom.
So it can be wholesome or unwholesome.
Stage one, contemplate on.
Whatever you focus on and contemplate on, that's the subject.
In conclusion, all dharmas have no self.
All these mental factors, you don't see a me or I.
There's no such thing.
The I that we think of is a pseudo self.
It's only our ego.
We want to get away from the ego and go back to the ego.
We want to get away from the ego and go back to our Buddha nature, our true suchness.
The only way is to become wholesome and purify our consciousness.
Turn from contaminated to purity.
That's when we reach enlightenment.
Change our ignorance consciousness into wisdom.
So it's from everyday experience.
Be aware of these mental factors.
Watch your thoughts.
Pick wholesome thoughts instead of bad thoughts.
Defilements, afflictions, greed, anger, ignorance.
Turn your life around.
Change from a mundane to a sane.
That's what Buddha wants us to cultivate.
So this is Chinese New Year.
We should really use our time wisely, diligently, watching every one of our mental factors.
If you're unaware of how your mind is functioning in everyday life, there is no way you can
change yourself. So in this new year, hopefully we can all make this a wonderful year of enlightenment.