Today we are going to talk about Tiantai Buddhism.
This is a major type of Buddhism founded in China by Master Zhi Yi,
who lived in the Tiantai Mountain in the Zhezhou Province, therefore the name Tiantai.
This school of Buddhism is based off the Lotus Sutra,
which incorporates all Buddha's teachings and it emphasizes on the one Buddha vehicle,
which means that we all inherently have the absolute mind, the Buddha nature,
and we are meant to reach Buddhahood.
Master Zhi Yi, he is famous for his ranking of the Buddha's teachings into five periods and eight teachings.
Now let's first look at the five periods.
The first period is the Aventasaka period, that is the Flower Adornment Sutra.
When Buddha first became enlightened, that's what he really wanted to share with us,
is the state of the Buddha, the incredible nature of their mind.
This is an exposition of Buddha's and Bodhisattva's, their way of reaching enlightenment,
their incredible state of being a Buddha.
This is all about the broadness of our mind.
We call it the Dharma Tattoo.
Our mind is the center of the universe, the vast entire Dharma realm,
and the vast emptiness is our mind.
Everyone in this universe is one with us.
That's the grandness of our mind.
So this is the king of all kings of all Buddhism scriptures.
Buddha really wanted to share with us.
However, Buddha realized not all sentient beings
can believe or understand this kind of profound teaching.
Therefore, he decided to change his teaching to the Agamas period,
expounding the four Agama Sutras.
The Long Agama Sutra,
two is the Medium Length Agama Sutra,
the Miscellaneous Agama Sutra,
the last one is Increasing by One Agama Sutra.
This is all Theravada Buddhism teaching us
how to get rid of the self and be out of reincarnation.
Their focus is to become an Arhat.
These people, they are not interested in becoming a Bodhisattva
to save sentient beings or reach Buddhahood.
They just want to leave the six realms of reincarnation.
So Buddha is tailoring his teaching toward these kind of people.
Therefore, he has this period of teaching.
But that's not what he really wanted to teach.
So he moved on to the third period,
Vipohya period.
It's the expansive period.
Now there's extensive Mahayana teaching coming out.
This is the period where we learn about the Pure Land Buddhism.
All the Pure Land Sutras are from this period.
And also Mahayana teaching such as the Mimalakirti Sutra.
It talks about a layman practitioner with incredible wisdom
that expanded Mahayana.
And also Mahayana teaching such as non-dualism.
There's no dualism in anything,
not the subject or the object,
not the self, not the selfless.
There's just one Buddha nature.
The fourth period is the Prajna period.
Prajna is wisdom.
We want to move toward the wisdom of true emptiness.
This is not the emptiness in the Dravata Buddhism.
This is all conditioned existence are empty in its nature.
This includes the Heart Sutra, the Diamond Sutra,
that really help us to let go.
Let go of all our attachment to the world of form,
to all the worldly appearances.
So Prajna is like the light that is getting rid of our ignorance.
That's major Mahayana teaching.
Then we move on to the Dharma Ponderic Narvana teaching.
That's the Lotus Sutra.
And the Nirvana Sutra.
Buddha shared this at the end of his life
because there's no time left.
What he really wanted to say is the one Buddha vehicle.
We all have the Buddha nature within us.
We are supposed to be Buddhas.
We're not supposed to just be Arhat or Pratyekabuddha
and not even Bodhisattvas.
We are supposed to reach Buddhahood
and reach final enlightenment.
These five periods of teaching,
oftentimes we say this is the first 21 days
after Buddha became enlightened.
This is 12 years of the Agama's teaching,
8 years of the Valpola teaching,
and 22 years of the Prajna teaching.
And the last 7 years is the Lotus Sutra
and the Nirvana Sutra.
But it's not necessarily in this order
because Buddha is very flexible.
Depending on the capacity of the student at the time,
he will expand all kinds of teaching
throughout his 49 years.
So these five periods of teaching in the Nirvana Sutra,
it is the analogy of the milk.
When Buddha first expanded the Avanthasaka Sutra,
it's like freshly squeezed milk out of the cow.
But not everybody can accept.
So Buddha moved on to the Agama's period.
This is like turning the milk into cream
so people are more likely to accept.
Then we turn to the Vipolya period.
That's like turning the cream into curd.
Curd is coagulated.
Sour milk is more processed for intake.
Then we move on to the Prajna period.
It's like turning the curd into butter.
So it's even more refined.
Lastly is the Dharmapanduruk period.
That's like the ghee.
Ghee is the most refined type of fat or oil
used for cooking in India.
It's not found here.
But that's supposed to be the more refined
and most delicious form of milk you can find.
That's describing the preciousness of the Lotus Sutra.
So this is the five periods in this state of richness
of Buddha's teaching.
We move on to the eight teachings.
It consists of the fourfold doctrines of conversion
and fourfold methods of conversion.
Let's first talk about the fourfold doctrines of conversion.
The first one is Tripitaka.
This is the Dravata Buddhism.
We call it the store teaching.
It consists of the three canons of Buddhism.
Sutra, Vanaya, and Shastras.
Sutra means concentration.
Vanaya means precepts.
And Shastra means wisdom.
It's not apart from the three aspects of learning
of precepts, concentration, and wisdom
to get rid of our greed, anger, and ignorance.
So Dravata Buddhists are very firm in this practice.
They really want to become an Arhat
and be out of the six realms of reincarnation.
Then Buddha has the common teaching.
Common also means shared teaching.
So it's common to the Dravata vehicle
and the great vehicle, the Mahayana.
This includes the Vipoya period
and the Prajna period.
All these are common to trying to help
all the Dravata Buddhists
to get to know Mahayana Buddhism.
So it's a lot about Prajna, about emptiness.
When you realize real emptiness,
you will realize reincarnation, samsara, and nirvana.
It's both empty in nature.
So you get rid of all your attachment to the Dharma as well.
Then there's the distinctive teaching.
It's special teaching only for the Bodhisattvas.
Help all sentient beings become enlightened.
So this is a distinctive teaching.
It also includes Vipoya period and the Prajna period.
A lot of it is like the conscious only school of Buddhism
that really help us delve into
the workings of our mind
and to bring ourselves out of the deluded consciousness
into our pure nature, our pure wisdom.
Finally, we have the complete teaching.
It's like the Lotus Sutra
that is telling us we are perfect and complete
in our Buddha nature.
There's nothing else we need.
We just need to know that we have the true nature.
We have the absolute mind just as Buddha.
So Buddha's teaching,
it looks like there's many different types of teaching,
but there's only one flavor, one way
that is a complete, perfect teaching.
We are all supposed to reach supreme, perfect enlightenment,
anuttaro sammyo sambodhi.
The first three types of doctrine
are all expedient ways.
They're skillful means of Buddha brought about
because everybody has different capacities of learning,
have different interests,
that's why Buddha has to use these teachings
to help us to start learning Buddhism.
But what he really wants us to learn
is the real teaching.
Every day you should understand
that you are a Buddha.
It doesn't matter what you practice anymore.
If you are Pure Land Buddhist,
when you chant Amitabha,
the mind that is chanting Amitabha
is the mind of the Buddha.
You are Amitabha.
If you are pure,
if you are a Zen practitioner,
you meditate,
you meditate to go inward into your true mind.
All you want to do is to go inside
and find your absolute mind.
So it doesn't matter
which kind of school of Buddhism you practice,
the only goal is to reach Buddhahood.
In this Lotus Sutra,
in this Tiantai Buddhism,
it's very clear in helping us
find our true Buddha nature.
It's called exposing the expedient
and revealing the real.
Take away all the expedient means
at the end,
just reveal the real teaching.
Now let's look at the four full
methods of conversion.
These are like the ways Buddha has teaching.
The first one is the certain teaching,
the immediate enlightenment.
Just like expanded in the Aventasaka Sutra,
we are the Dharma taught to,
the Buddha nature.
The entire universe is us.
Our mind is the Buddha.
The gradual teaching,
that's the Agama's period,
the Valpoa period,
and the Prajna period.
Beginning gradual,
the middle gradual,
and the final gradual.
Little by little,
bringing you to Buddhahood,
to enlightenment.
It's not the certain teaching.
Then we have the secret
and the variable.
The certain is the Aventasaka.
The gradual is two, three, and four.
The secret and the variable
is all first four.
The Lotus Sutra is completely
separate from these four.
So what is the secret teaching?
Sometimes when Buddha expounds Dharma
in the audience,
Buddha will transmit some teaching
through his psychic power
to certain students
that he will reach enlightenment
in a secret manner.
Only Buddha can do this.
No one else in the audience
will know what Buddha is doing
to that student,
except the student himself.
Then there is the variable teaching.
Variable teaching is out in the open.
Different students learn different things,
even in the same Dharma teaching.
For example,
in the Mahayana teaching,
you can have a Theravada enlightenment.
In the Triyagama Sutra,
the daughter of Mantanji,
she heard the Mahayana teaching
of the Triyagama Sutra,
she became an art hack.
So everybody can reach different state
from listening to Mahayana teaching.
They might have a Theravada enlightenment
or you learn the Gamma Sutra
and you have a Mahayana enlightenment.
So everybody varies
depending on their capacities
and their liking.
These are four methods of teaching
but what about the Lotus Sutra?
It's beyond certain.
It's beyond gradual.
It has no secrets
and has no variables.
When you learn the Lotus Sutra,
there's only one teaching
which is the perfect complete teaching.
You will not learn anything else
but the fact that you are supposed to be a Buddha.
It's very, very firm,
very sure.
Buddha gives a lot of hope
and faith
that we are supposed to be Buddhas.
Supreme Perfect Enlightenment
Annyo Toro Sama Sampodhi
is what we're supposed to be.
This is the perfect teaching.
That's what Tiantai Buddhism is all about.
It has this extensive way
of ranking Buddha's teaching
just to let us know
how important the complete teaching is.
So it goes to this very, very extensive system
just to point out
that we are supposed to reach Buddhahood.
Lastly, I want to share a parable
from the Lotus Sutra.
There is a king
that always rewards his soldiers
by giving them lavish presents
such as big houses, clothing,
treasures of gold and silver.
But he has this precious jewel
in his topknot
that he does not give to anybody.
Only if there's a soldier
that is perfect in his combat
and is able to triumph through all evils
then he will give away
this perfect jewel to him.
So what does this mean?
The king is Shakyamuni Buddha.
All the lavish presents,
they are like his teaching
before the Lotus Sutra.
They are only precious teachings
for us to learn Buddhism
but they are nothing like
the precious jewel in his topknot.
That's like the Lotus Sutra.
He only gives it
when it's the right time
and the right condition
because it's so precious.
We wouldn't understand
until you learn all these
and you realize what's most valuable.
Do not let our teacher down.
He really wants us to reach Buddhahood.
Do not waste your life away
working on the mundane world
and not having any spiritual enlightenment.
You can use all kinds of teachings.
They will help you
to reach Buddhahood.
So it doesn't matter what you practice.
They are all causes
for you to reach Buddhahood.
So the Lotus means cause
and the effect happen at the same time.
So it doesn't matter
if you are a Theravada Buddhist,
you are practicing your precepts,
concentration and wisdom.
At that time,
your Buddhahood is coming into fruition.
There's no doubt about it.
The cause and the effect,
they happen simultaneously.
All teachings will bring you
to Buddhahood eventually.
It's just sooner or later.
So believe in Buddha's teaching.
Get rid of our greed,
anger and ignorance
and let our absolute mind come out.
Then we are really the person
that the king gave away
the precious jewel in his top knot to.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.