Today we are going to talk about the Sutra of Complete Enlightenment.
This Sutra consists of 12 Bodhisattvas asking Shakyamuni Buddha how to practice and reach
perfect enlightenment. I summarize the points of the 12 chapters on this board.
1. Bodhisattva Manjushri asked Shakyamuni Buddha,
What is the causal ground of all Buddhas? Shakyamuni Buddha answered,
It is the complete illumination of intrinsic enlightenment.
It's like we have the perfect mirror that reflects everything clearly without being attached
to anything that's happening in the mirror.
This is our pure mind. This mind is the intrinsic enlightenment.
That means we're originally enlightened. We have to start our practice from this causal ground,
which means start from your true suchness, your perfect complete enlightenment.
Just like if we're trying to cook rice, we have to put rice into the rice cooker.
If we put sand into the rice cooker, you will only get hot air.
So if we do not start with the right causal ground, we will not reach enlightenment.
No matter how much Buddha you chant, how much offering you give, how much precepts you observe,
that is not going to work.
2. Bodhisattva Samantabhadra asked Shakyamuni Buddha,
How to reach the Sun Enlightenment? Shakyamuni Buddha answered,
To know illusion is to depart from it. To depart from it is to be enlightened.
The secret is in this verse. All we have to do is to know illusion.
Everything that's going on right now, we are attached to it.
We do not understand its illusion.
Now what you have to do is to have a clear understanding.
See through the reality you're experiencing right now.
All the people in your life, your family, your work, all your possessions,
it doesn't belong to you.
It's like the things that's happening in your dream.
If you can see this clearly in this present life right now, you will be enlightened.
So all you have to do is to know what is illusion,
which is basically everything that's happening right now.
You see it with the clear eyes.
Then you will depart from it, which means you will be detached.
You will no longer let these things drive you.
They drive your happiness and sadness.
We have the perfect enlightened mind, but we're giving our power away
when we're dwelling in what is going on right now.
So to depart from it, it is to be enlightened.
Enlightenment is departing from illusion.
Separate from what's going on.
This person yelling at you is not happening right now.
It is a condition arising.
It will go away the next minute.
Nothing is permanent.
Nothing is real.
It's all illusion.
You just have to see, then you will reach this complete enlightenment.
This is called the sudden enlightenment method.
The third, bodhisattva universal vision.
Basically, it's Guanyin Bodhisattva.
She wants to know if we cannot do the sudden enlightenment,
is there a gradual practice we can do?
Shakyamuni Buddha's answer is to know our body and mind are illusory flowers.
This gradual step is not different from the sudden enlightenment method.
It's basically the same, but in more detail.
You have to see the illusory nature of your body and mind.
In this sutra, it uses the main example of the illusory flowers.
We have sickness in our eyes.
So we see there's lots of flowers in the sky.
But in reality, the sky has no flowers.
The sky symbolizes our intrinsic enlightenment, the true mind.
We have optical obstructions that prevent us from seeing the truth.
All our body and mind is just illusory flowers.
You think your body is the real me.
You think your thoughts,
your concept is the real me.
But that is all ignorance.
Our true nature is non-self.
It's emptiness.
The sky is originally empty,
but you see all these flowers.
That's why we're deluded and confused.
There is no flower in the sky.
The sky is perfectly clear,
just like our intrinsic enlightenment.
Number four is Bodhisattva Vajragarbha.
Now it's talking about self-enlightenment.
How do we become self-enlightened?
Again, Shakyamuni Buddha answered,
the sky originally has no flowers.
The flower is not caused by the sky.
The sky is originally empty,
and there's no flower to start with.
You cannot say,
how did the flowers extinguish?
Because there's no place it came from,
and there's no place
it extinguished.
The flower itself never existed in the sky.
That is how we attain self-enlightenment.
This chapter also gives another example,
smelting gold out of the ore.
Our Buddha nature is the perfect gold.
The gold does not come from the process of smelting.
It is originally 24 karat gold.
Once you go through this process,
you will not go back to the ore again.
Just like if we reach Buddhahood,
are we going to get back to this ordinary being
full of greed, anger and ignorance?
No, we will never go back
because we are originally the perfect pure gold.
The fifth chapter is the enlightenment of others.
This is Bodhisattva Maitreya.
Bodhisattva Maitreya asked Shakyamuni Buddha,
what is the cause of samsara?
Shakyamuni Buddha's answer,
cyclic existence is due to all kinds of affection,
love, craving and desire.
Basically all are clinging,
love, desire and lust.
This is how we have reincarnation,
the continuation of life and birth.
If we do not have love and affection,
that is tainted,
we will not have reincarnation.
This chapter talks about
because of this,
we have two kinds of obstructions.
One is the obstruction of principle.
Two is the obstruction of phenomenon.
Principle is basically
we think everything outside of us is real.
Obstruction of phenomenon is
we think there is a real me.
So these two kinds of obstructions
hinder us from reaching enlightenment
and continue to be in this cyclic existence.
So out of these two kinds of obstructions,
we have five nature of people.
One is ordinary beings.
They have not eradicated
any of the two kinds of obstructions.
That's why they are ordinary mundane people.
Number two is the shravaka
and pratyekabuddha nature.
People who already eradicated
their obstruction of phenomenon,
but not yet eradicated
their obstruction of the principle.
They got rid of the self,
but they still don't see the reality of the world.
The third nature is bodhisattvas.
They do get rid of both kinds of obstructions.
So they will eventually reach
Buddhahood.
The fourth nature is people who are unstable.
If they meet good teachers,
they will reach enlightenment.
But if they meet people that are bad influences,
they will go down the wrong path
because of the wrong views.
Number five is people with the outer path nature,
which means they like other religions and practices.
Or you can say they are people who think
there is a truth outside of their own mind.
Number six is bodhisattva pure wisdom.
This bodhisattva wants to know
how do we accord with this intrinsic enlightenment?
Shakyamuni Buddha answered,
we have four kinds of accordance
with the nature of enlightenment.
It's kind of like the five nature of people.
Now it's four levels of attainment.
The first one is the ordinary people's
accordance with the nature of enlightenment.
Even though they get rid of their toil and anxiety,
but they are still caught up
in their knowledge of this purity.
They don't have the freedom and ease
with their true nature.
The second accordance is the lower level bodhisattvas.
The third is the higher level bodhisattvas.
The fourth is the Tathagata, the Buddha.
The second accordance is the lower level bodhisattvas.
They understand and they get rid of the hindrance,
but their knowledge of the obstructions
becomes a hindrance in itself.
The third is the higher level bodhisattvas.
They know eradicating hindrance itself
is only a dharma tool.
They are not caught up with this cultivation
so they are more at ease with their practice.
Lastly, it's the Tathagata's
accordance with the nature of enlightenment.
At this stage, samsara is nirvana.
Affliction is bodhi.
Everything is one.
There's no more duality.
All the problems, all the hell and heaven,
they are all pure land.
That's the last level of
accordance with the nature of enlightenment.
Chapter seven is bodhisattva at ease in majestic virtue.
This bodhisattva wants to know about
how do we actually practice meditation.
If we cannot have certain enlightenment,
do we have ways of meditation?
Now Shakyamuni Buddha teaches three singular meditations.
Samatha, Samapati, Dhyana.
These are three names of meditation.
Basically, Samatha is void meditation.
Understanding the emptiness of all things
and you stay in the stillness.
Number two, Samapati is to contemplate
that everything is illusory.
So the key word here is illusion.
You have to see everything as existing,
as illusion.
Then you have great compassion
for all sentient beings
because you have no more self.
Lastly is Dhyana.
Dhyana is a combination of the two.
This is the mean meditation.
When you combine emptiness
and illusory existence,
that is the middle way.
We call it the mean.
So that's the seventh chapter
teaching us how to actually practice meditation.
Eighth chapter is Bodhisattva sound discernment.
Now the three singular meditations
have different combinations
for a total of 25 kinds of samadhis.
So out of the three,
now it's 25.
Seven start with Samatha,
seven that starts with Samapati,
and seven that starts with Dhyana.
For a total of 21,
plus the first three originally,
the 25th is basically the combination
of all of them.
If you want to practice meditation,
you can use any one of the 25 kinds of samadhi.
You will reach this level of enlightenment.
Number nine is Bodhisattva
cleanse of all karmic obstructions.
We often have problems in our meditation
because of our faults.
So number nine is our self-inflicted faults
in our meditation.
Number 10 is other inflicted faults
How come we cannot succeed
in our meditation practice?
Because we have these sicknesses.
Self-inflicted sickness is because
we are caught up with four forms.
This is discussed in the Diamond Sutra as well.
We are caught up in the sign of self,
the sign of others,
the sign of sentient beings,
and lifespan.
This is why we cannot succeed
in our meditation.
Because we have an ego,
we are in opposition with all other person.
Everybody else is outside of us.
So we have competition.
We have jealousy.
We have problems.
Because we have these views,
we cannot reach enlightenment.
All sentient beings in this space and time,
they are in opposition with the self.
And in this lifespan,
in terms of time and space,
we all have strong thinking of dualism.
Because of these false views,
we cannot be a Bodhisattva.
So if you practice meditation,
but you still have strong sense of these four forms,
you cannot become enlightened.
Number 10 now is talking about
other inflicted faults.
Bodhisattva Universal Enlightenment
asked about what other faults do we have
in our meditation.
How come we cannot succeed in our meditation?
Shakyamuni Buddha says
we have four kinds of faults
that are learned from the wrong teacher.
Or other people give you false
ideas.
The first one is contrivance.
When you think you have to do certain practice,
exert yourself with a lot of energy
in order to become enlightened.
This is a false view.
Enlightenment is originally with thinness.
It's not from exerting yourself really hard.
Second one is naturalism.
The opposite.
Some people are very lazy.
They think I don't have to practice
because samsara is nirvana.
Nirvana and affliction is bodhi.
So I just let everything be as it is.
You have this kind of view,
you cannot succeed in your meditation either.
The third one is stopping.
Some people think I just stop all thoughts.
Then that's enlightenment.
Stopping all thoughts is not in accordance
with your intrinsic enlightenment.
That's not the way either.
Number four is annihilation.
Some people think I just get rid of all my afflictions.
That's it.
Emptiness.
Nothingness.
That is enlightenment.
That is also a false view.
If you have any kinds of these wrong views,
you cannot succeed in your meditation.
Chapter 11 is Bodhisattva of Complete Enlightenment.
He asked if we cannot do any of these,
what do we do?
So Buddha tells us expedient path.
Basically,
you have to have utmost sincere repentance.
You have to do 21 days of concentrated confession.
If you can confess single-mindedly,
you can get rid of problems in your meditation.
If you don't confess,
you cannot get rid of your common obstacles.
You cannot really sit there and meditate.
You cannot even bring yourself to sit there for a long time.
Lastly is the 12th chapter,
this is the Bodhisattva foremost in virtue and goodness.
This is the dissemination chapter of the Sutra.
The Sutra is the pure eye of the 12 divisions of Buddhist scriptures.
There are 12 canons of Buddhist scriptures.
Some are long discourses.
Some are gathas and verses.
Some are Shakyamuni Buddha stories.
Some are metaphors and parables.
There are 12 canons.
But this Sutra is the pure eye.
That means you understand all kinds of Sutras.
If you understand this Sutra,
then you understand all Dharma.
You understand how to be enlightened.
You understand the truth about all Buddhist scriptures.
So this is the synopsis of the Sutra of Complete Enlightenment.
All 12 Bodhisattvas,
they are not people.
They are not people outside of us.
These 12 Bodhisattvas are you.
You are the Buddha.
You are the Bodhisattva.
You are Manjushri.
You are Samantabhadra.
These are not talking about other people.
They are you.
Because you originally have this perfect enlightenment within your mind.
The mind is the Buddha.
Buddha is the mind.
That's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.