Today we are going to talk about using suffering as our teacher.
Buddha taught the Four Noble Truths.
The First Noble Truth is understanding suffering.
If we can understand suffering, then we can end the suffering, reach Nirvana.
We will discuss ten different kinds of sufferings and learn how to use them as our spiritual
teacher.
Today we will discuss the first five and the next class will discuss the other five.
Number one, do not wish to be free from illness.
Our body is impermanent.
It's made out of impermanent components.
It's constantly changing.
Sickness is inevitable.
Suffering doesn't really come from being sick.
It comes mostly from our resistance to the sickness.
We don't want to be sick, don't accept sickness.
If we can understand impermanence and accept the sickness, then there will no longer be
a suffering.
Our ninth patriarch of the Pure Land Buddhism, O.E.
Master, he was enlightened when he was 24.
He wrote a lot of great commentaries and treaties.
When he was 56, he was severely sick for seven days.
He couldn't sit or lie down.
All he can do is chant Amitabha Buddha's name with tears in his eyes.
That's when he realized no matter how enlightened he was, he had to rely on Amitabha Buddha and
go to the Western Pure Land.
So use our illness as medicine to cure our attachment to our body, to this world, and
have true renunciation.
And understand that true renunciation is the true renunciation.
Understand the true importance of going to the Western Pure Land that's without any suffering.
Number two, don't always aspire to be free from difficulties.
When life is smooth sailing, we're likely to be arrogant and have indolence.
I had a pretty good life growing up.
I was always the head of my class.
I was a valedictorian on my high school.
I went on to UC Berkeley, got a business degree, and I got a great job after graduation.
I was promoted very quickly.
Until one day, I couldn't see out of my eyes.
It's a rare retina degenerative disease that took most of my central vision.
So I couldn't go to work, I couldn't see the computer, I couldn't drive.
I was devastated.
But that's when I started putting all my time into learning Buddhism.
I just closed my eyes and listened to the Dharma.
That was the only way to cope with my tragedy.
Now it's been 18 years.
If it's not for my eyes, then I wouldn't devote myself to Buddhism.
I just closed my eyes and listened to the Dharma.
That was the only way to cope with my tragedy.
I don't want to devote my whole life to Buddhism.
So use our difficulties as a deliverance.
Deliver us from complacency.
Motivate us to practice diligently.
Number 3, ask not for easy realization when self-reflecting.
Buddhism is about the study of our own mind.
It's very complex to study our own mind.
Especially, we have a lot of depression, anxiety, and a lot of fear.
We need to use this focus.
this fear to really understand the dharma for the first years of my eye condition my eyes was
progressively getting worse so i developed strong depression i couldn't eat couldn't sleep i had
severe insomnia i was really depressed then i realized my depression did not come from not able
to see well it actually came from the fear of being completely blind what if i see pitch black
what will my life be like other people have to take care of me that would be horrible the more
i thought about it the more depressed i became until one day the dharma and the heart sutra
really hit me it says to realize the emptiness of the five skantas body feeling perception mental
formation and consciousness so i asked myself is this depression real is this feeling my is it the
real me then i realized it's all an illusion this is not me it's just my deluded mind conjuring up
this image in my head it's not real then i learned to shift on my focus i don't think about my eyes
anymore i just put all my energy into helping other people and to be of service to other how
people learn buddhism miraculously my eyes stopped getting worse i was genuinely happy and all my
depression went away
so use the complexity of our mind as liberation to liberate us from the deluded mind and to gain
wisdom about emptiness number four when cultivating there will be demonic obstacles mara which is
the sanskrit word for a demon he is not happy when someone is trying to get out the six rounds
of reincarnation when you're cultivating heart he will try to block you just like
in the shiragama sutra it talks about ananda's fall one day ananda was collecting alms through
the city in sequential order he passed by a house of prostitution this happened to be the house of
the daughter of matangi who's already madly in love with ananda for his good looks so when she
saw him she immediately went to her mom and begged her to do a love spell onto ananda so the mother
sent her mantra onto a cloth to cover up ananda's bowl when ananda removed the cloth he was
controlled by the spell he went up to her room lied in her bed and she started caressing him
that's when he was on the verge of losing his precept substance luckily he was able to call
out to buddha in his mind buddha sends ananda's trouble immediately sent manjushri bodhisattva to
rescue ananda
when manjushri bodhisattva arrived he immediately recited the shiragama mantra and broke the spell
then he brought back ananda and their daughter matangi back to buddha that's when buddha
expounded the great dharma of the shiragama sutra so if it's not for ananda's fall he will not be
enlightened he will not find his true nature and we will not have the shiragama sutra to learn from
so use the obstacles
ask our spiritual companions to find our true nature our pure mind number five do not hope for
goals to be easily achieved all successful people go through trials and tribulations
before their goals are achieved the key is not to dwell on the outcome the key is to enjoy the
process of learning to train our perseverance as long as we try our best and learn along the way
then it's already a success
desperado
super
so
there was a pig that was only born with two front legs without hind legs nobody thought he could
survive but the owner did not give up on him he kept trying to train him to walk on two legs when
feeding him he kept moving the feeding dish further and further away so the pig had to try to rock on
his front legs he fell many many many times but finally he was able to walk run and jump with his
front legs so as long as you hit a wall you may get water then you can perfume the tent and everyone over night will be happy
he became the inspirational mascot of the town so we want to use our adversities as a fulfillment
as long as we try our best and never give up and train our perseverance it's already a fulfillment
in itself in conclusion we say affliction is Bodhi our affliction and our suffering is the way to
become enlightened without them we will not have enlightenment so don't worry if you're having
sufferings right now all you have to do is to understand it accept it and use it use it to
develop true renunciation to motivate us to practice diligently to gain wisdom on emptiness
to find our true nature and to train our perseverance this is actually
a
suffering
a teaching from a treaty of a Pure Land recitation.
If we can really use our sufferings as teacher
in our daily lives on the brink of our death,
we'll no longer be afraid,
and we can really choose the Pure Land
as our final destination.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.