Today's topic is Tugging the Ox.
There are ten stages of enlightenment depicted by the ten ox-herding pictures of Zen.
Enlightenment is a process of freeing ourselves from the unenlightened states.
There are actually nine aspects of the unenlightened states.
Number one is activity of ignorance.
We were the suchness, but our mind started moving, become agitated,
it started to become the alaya consciousness, the storehouse of our karma.
So that's the activity of ignorance.
Then we would create the perceiving subject, the thinking mind,
and then we create the world of objects, the things that we think about, images in our mind.
So everything outside of us are actually all created by our alaya consciousness in the form of world of objects.
So these three are the subtle aspects of our deluded mind.
Then we have six crude aspects.
Number four is discriminating intellect.
Discriminate the world of objects.
This is what we like and what I do not like, and you keep having judgments and thoughts.
Then we will have aspects of continuity.
Discriminating thoughts will continue.
If you go to sleep and the moment you wake up, you have the same kinds of thoughts over and over.
Number six is our attachment.
When these thoughts keep continuing, it becomes our belief system.
We are extremely attached to the idea of the self and all the worldly things that we experience
based on the seventh consciousness, our ego.
Then we have speculation, our names and letters.
We think in terms of words.
In our mind, these words become our belief system and it becomes what we experience in life.
Because of our belief system, we will create karma.
Then we will have suffering based on the karma.
So these are the nine aspects of our deluded mind.
Now we are going to look at the ten stages of enlightenment compared to the nine aspects of non-enlightenment.
Number one, searching for the ox.
The shepherd boy fell asleep.
He lost his ox.
Along in the wilderness, he searches in despair.
The shepherd boy symbolizes the practitioner and the ox symbolizes our true nature.
Because of the suffering we are experiencing right now, it motivates us to search for our
spiritual self.
Number two is seeing the traces.
Along by the stream and under the tree scatter our traces of the lost ox.
Now we see something.
Some traces.
This symbolizes learning Buddhism, understanding the sutra and the dharma and help us to see
our true nature.
We are now changing our karmic deeds to align ourselves with our true nature and not follow
our defilement anymore.
Number three is seeing the ox.
This is depicted by a knight in a gown cheerfully singing on the bank, the willows are green,
the ox is there all by himself.
This is when we have epiphany, we saw a glimpse of our true nature.
A spiritual teacher, Dr. Wing Dyer, talked about how he had a shift in his consciousness.
When he was very young, his father left him, so he grew up in a series of orphanages.
In his adulthood, he was having a problem with alcohol and his marriage, so all because
of his resentment toward his father.
Finally, in his mid-thirties, he decided to go look for his father's grave as his father
has already passed away for ten years.
When he was there, there was a strong feeling that came over him.
Finally, he released all his hatred toward his father, and from that day on, he only
had love in his heart.
There is no more hatred consuming him.
He transformed his life completely.
And he was able to see his true nature.
This is when we have epiphany and seeing the ox, that's when we let go of our speculations
of names and letters, let go the strong attachment of the labels in our heart.
Number four is catching the ox.
The ox is hard to keep under control because we have strong attachment to the self.
The mind is very stubborn.
You have epiphanies.
It can still go back to the same way because of the strong attachment.
Now the attachment has been softened.
Number five, hurting the ox.
We still have work to do.
The shepherd still need to hurt the ox with whips and tether so the animal does not wander
away again because we have strong aspect of continuity.
The old negative thought pattern can still keep going.
If you look at a husband and wife, usually they fight over the same thing years after
years.
Why?
Because they didn't change their thought pattern.
Changing the ox, whenever a situation arise, we are now at least aware of it and we can
break the pattern.
We can stop it from continuing.
Number six, coming home on the ox's back.
Riding on the ox, he leisurely wins his way home.
He is filled with joy indescribable.
The strong attachment to the ox is very important.
A burden is overcome is over because the discriminating intellect has dissolved.
So we are no longer discriminating and judging the world with our ego.
Now we have found our true self and everything is under control.
So we feel this incredible satisfaction in our heart.
We are no longer dependent on outside situations to make us happy.
We are always at home and at peace.
Welcome back.
that we never felt before. We finally feel a sense of ultimate happiness.
Number seven, two ox forgotten leaving the man alone. Now we have arrived home. We don't need
the ox anymore. The boy alone sits serenely at home because we have let go of the world of
object. The world of object does not bother this person at all because he knows everything is a
dream, an illusion. The world of object does not affect him in any way. He has found his true
nature, even letting go of finding enlightenment. When you're trying to search for an enlightenment
or a Buddha, it's like trying to grab space. You cannot grab space. The truth is there's nothing
to find because you're already there. Number eight, the ox and the man both gone out of sight.
The ox and the man both gone out of sight. The ox and the man both gone out of sight.
The ox is the world of object. The man symbolizes the perceiving subject. Both the subject and the
object, they are still duality. We have to let it go. We have to let go of all dualism in order
to reach who we really are, the true suchness. Whatever you do, wherever you are, that is your
real mind. That is the real Buddha. So we don't search for anything, look anywhere,
anywhere else. The mind is the Buddha. The mind is Nirvana. There's nothing to search.
You don't want your mind to take any form. When you are still enthralled with the form
of a subject, object, you are still not free. So do not let your mind take form because
when it has no form, it's spacious and without any limitations. Number nine, return to the
origin, back to the source. Now the activity of ignorance, ignorance, ignorance, ignorance,
ignorance, the alaya consciousness is completely turned into purity. Now it's a great perfect
mirror wisdom. This mirror revives clearly without any attachment to anything. Everything
sees clearly, but there's no attachment to any form. That is when we are the Buddha.
The mind is the Buddha. The Buddha is the mind. Number 10, entering the city with bliss bestowing
hands.
Now we are like a bodhisattva with a golden arm reaching out to all suffering beings.
After enlightenment, there's nothing to do but go back to your everyday life. Be a bodhisattva
to all the people that are not yet enlightened. You want to help everyone to be out of their
suffering and reach enlightenment. Our arm is like Amitabha reaching out to help all sentient
beings.
So we can actually create miracles in our lives. There is mom. Her boy has autism so
he is always screaming. She has to work during the day and at night. It takes a lot out of
her to take care of him. She can't help but complain about why it just happened to me.
I don't think I can take this anymore. It's just a constant struggle. One day she started
learning about the power of our own mind.
But what's the meaning of spiritual awareness? How does that work? How does it work? How does
that work? How does it work? How does that work? How does that work? How does it work? How does
she was looking at her boy finally she found peace she completely accepted for who he is
there's only unconditional love and she only sees beauty in him because of the way she has changed
her consciousness the boy miraculously became calm and normal so we can all make miracles in
our lives because our mind is the buddha all we have to do is to come back to who we really are
we never finish with the journey of enlightenment and we will never get it wrong there's no
definite answer to any of these this is just a way to bring ourselves to awakening
then you will be able to really understand what is nirvana what is the ultimate world of
happiness
of the Western Pure Land. So that is the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.