Today is our first class.
So I will start from the beginning of how to meditate.
So when we meditate, the first thing we do is to adjust our posture.
There are seven ways to adjust our posture.
When you sit, it's from the bottom to top.
And when you exit, you go from top to bottom.
Remember the seven positions.
First, you adjust your legs.
If you can, try to do the full lotus.
This is called a full lotus.
Both feet are up to where your thigh is.
If you can, don't worry.
Just do half a lotus.
Or any way you like to cross your legs.
As long as you cross your legs.
Or you sit on this chair, that's fine too.
Any way you like to sit.
The purpose is for us to go into this happy peaceful mode.
Any position you like to sit.
But make it straight, comfortable, and relaxing.
The second thing that you adjust is your spine, your vertebrae.
You want to make sure your back is fully erect.
Don't try to force it straight.
It should be natural.
You're naturally built to be straight.
You're not naturally to be crooked.
Your true Buddha nature will come out when you're very straight.
So make sure your back is as straight as you can get it to be.
So that's the second thing you have to adjust.
The third is your hands.
Put your left hand on the bottom.
Right hand on the top.
And your thumb gently touch each other.
And place it in your lap.
Make sure the two are even.
Don't be lopsided or one side up.
And make sure it's comfortable.
So now we move up to our shoulders.
No slouching ever.
You gotta open up your chest so it's all the way back.
And no slouching.
Relax and straight.
That's the purpose of adjusting our shoulders.
What's the fifth one?
We move up to our head.
Make sure our head is straight.
It's not tilted this way or up.
It should be a little bit tucked in but not all the way down.
Not to one side or the other.
When you look on the side, it should be very well placed in the center.
The sixth is make sure your mouth is a little bit smiling.
Smiling.
Smiling will relax the muscles in your face so you can go into this deep concentration.
So smile as if you're seeing Buddha.
Very happy.
The happiest place on earth.
Your thumb touches the roots of your mouth where your gums and your teeth touch.
It will generate this very good soul.
Very good saliva that will nourish your body.
Lastly, close your eyes so you can focus.
If you can't close your eyes because you will fall asleep,
then you can open 30% and look down on the floor right in front of you.
But don't look around.
Forget about where you are or who you are.
Just right here.
Right now, looking at the floor or close your eyes.
Concentrate.
So that's the seventh way to adjust your body, your posture,
so you can go into samadhi, which means deep concentration.
From top to bottom.
Relax your forehead.
Your eyes.
Your neck.
Your shoulders.
Your arms.
depart your surroundings.
Your upper body.
Pelvis.
Eyes.
Your knees.
Your feet.
Your bones.
Your knees.
Now, each leg again.
From bottom to top.
Relax your toes.
Relax your feet.
Relax your legs.
Relax your knees.
Straight back.
Pelvis.
Down low.
Relax your arms, your shoulders, and relax your neck, your cheeks, and your shoulders.
Our breathing.
The way to go into deep meditation is by focusing your attention on your breathing.
Don't try to change your breathing.
Just observe it.
Observe your breathing.
That is the only thing in the world at this moment.
Enjoy your breathing.
Enjoy how you're breathing.
Now we count our breathing.
Every inhale, exhale, count one.
All the way up to five.
Make it into a cycle.
If there are wandering thoughts, just observe it and ignore it.
Go back to your counting.
Inhale.
Exhale.
One.
Inhale.
Exhale.
Two.
One.
Three.
Two.
One.
Three.
woo
Inhale.
Three.
We all want our training to be loud, to be quiet and soft.
Now we count one through five by ourselves.
In the Flower Adornment Sutra, it says,
Our mind is like an artist.
Who can paint the entire world.
From this, the five skandhas arise.
As well as all phenomena.
Our mind is like an artist.
We can paint a beautiful world if we like.
Or we can paint a very ugly picture by negative emotion.
It's all up to us what we are going to paint for our life.
We have a right to paint.
We have a right to choose.
And by meditating, we can be in touch with our true Buddha nature.
Pureness and happiness.
The five skandhas arise.
What are the five skandhas?
Skandhas also means aggregates.
Buddha says our mind and body consist of five aggregates.
The first is form.
The form aggregate means our body.
Our mind controls our body.
If you think I'm always sick, I'll always be sick.
It's all up to your mind.
The second skandha is our feelings.
We have the feeling of pleasure, displeasure, and neutral.
It's all up to us on how to feel.
The third aggregate is our perceptions.
Perception is based on how we like or dislike.
Hot or cold.
Nice or mean.
That's how we perceive.
This perception is also based on our feelings.
It's also based on our mind.
We can change how we perceive the world.
If I think everybody is mean.
Everybody is mean.
If I think everyone is my friend.
They are all wonderful people in my life.
The fourth aggregate is our feelings.
The fourth aggregate is mental formation.
It's our perception going into a deeper level of labeling, discrimination, prejudice, or all kinds of judgment.
This is also up to us to change.
The last skandha is mental formation.
It's our consciousness.
It consists of higher three skandhas.
Feeling, perception, and formation.
The whole thing is called consciousness.
We can paint a wonderful life for ourselves.
If we can just change our mind the way that we're supposed to be.
Everything in this world is created by our thoughts.
Through meditation and deep concentration,
we are able to control our thoughts to be in line with our true Buddha nature.
Perfect and pure.
That is a short way of contemplation.
Now we go back to count our breathing.
Inhale.
Exhale.
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven.
Eight.
Nine.
Four, inhale, exhale, five, now count by yourself.
If you start having wandering thoughts, then start over from one.
When we exhale, we relax from the top to the bottom.
So relax your legs first.
Now you rub your hands.
Put it on your eyes.
That will give you good eyesight.
Now rub again.
And rub your whole head all the way to your ears.
You can use a little force, it's fine.
Now massage your arms.
And make it hot again.
And put it on your waist.
That's how you have good kidneys.
Now you rub your legs because you haven't moved for 45 minutes.
So you have to protect it.
So the next time, you can sit for longer.
So everybody did really well for the first time.
Everybody's really good.
Thank you.
.