If you want to understand all Buddhas of all times, just observe the nature of Dharma rounds.
So what's the nature of the universe?
We call it Dharma rounds.
Everything is actually made from our mind.
Quantum physics has proven every matter is just a vibration from the energy of our thoughts.
In Buddhism, we call it karmic effect.
So our good thoughts create heaven.
Our bad thoughts create hell.
That's why our thoughts are very important.
What you think about all day long is what you create for the world.
Today we're going to talk about the Bodhisattvas' way of thinking.
What's their perfect intentions?
There are three general intentions of the Bodhisattvas.
The first is enthusiasm.
We have to have great enthusiasm when we do good deeds.
In the Lotus Sutra, it says,
Even children in play,
who make Buddhas stupas out of heaps of sand or draw a Buddha's image with a blade of grass,
all of them have reached Buddhahood.
That small act of kindness because of the enthusiasm.
Because of the sincerity, it made them into Buddhas.
So have enthusiasm when we do good deeds.
The second is rejoice.
This is for ourselves.
This is with others.
Rejoice in other people's kindness.
Let go of ourselves.
Do not compare or be jealous when other people are doing great deeds.
If we rejoice and recognize and praise their good deeds,
you're actually changing the world.
So that's the Bodhisattva's second perfect intention.
The third is happiness.
Enthusiasm is for ourselves.
Rejoice is rejoice for the others.
And happiness is praying.
You're always wishing.
That everybody will keep doing good deeds and reach Buddhahood.
So that's the three general perfect intentions of a Bodhisattva on their way to reach Buddhahood.
These three perfect intentions, they have six characteristics.
The first is boundlessness.
There's no limit to how many people you want to save or want to help.
You don't just love your own family.
You love your country.
You should extend your love and compassion to all sentient beings.
We have this organization called Doctors Without Borders.
They go to all countries in need and give medical service to casualties of war, to refugees.
And now with the coronavirus, without any consideration of country or money,
they just do it out of the goodness of their heart.
That's in the intention of a Bodhisattva.
Boundless intention without any limit.
The second one is endless.
There should be no time limit to how long you want to do this kindness.
My favorite story is about a bird in the forest.
One day, there was a big fire.
The bird was very nervous and very worried.
So he darted to the river, dipped himself in the water,
and flew back quickly to the raging fire,
shook his wings really hard,
trying to release a few drops of water that was still on his feathers.
But how much good can that do?
He kept doing it regardless for hours.
Soon, the heaven, they know,
wow, there is a bird doing such a great deed.
The heavenly being came down and asked,
what do you think you're doing?
Do you think you can really put out the fire by doing this?
And the bird said, I don't care.
Even if I die, I will still come alive.
I will keep doing this until it's put out.
The heavenly being was so touched,
it started raining and extinguished the fire.
Who is this bird?
It's Buddha Shakyamuni.
So our compassion should be endless.
The third is called joyfulness.
A lot of moms, they're always complaining.
Nobody is cleaning up in this household,
except me.
What would they do without me?
Always frustrated doing everything in the house,
but very unhappy about everybody.
That's not the way to be a bodhisattva,
just by doing housework.
Happily, joyfully, you create great merit.
That's the bodhisattva's way, creates great karma.
When you're joyful, you change the atmosphere,
you change the vibration,
you change the energy in your family.
Always be cheerful,
and without any complaints.
The fourth one is repaying kindness.
When we're doing other people's service,
don't think we are doing them a favor.
Actually, you should think they've done us great deeds
by letting us helping them.
Be appreciative,
as if they're your great benefactors.
There was a hotel attendant,
one stormy night,
the hotel is completely packed.
There came an old couple,
trying to get a room.
But the hotel attendant told the old couple,
I'm sorry, every room is occupied,
it's fully booked.
But he didn't want the old couple to go out in the storm again,
and have no place to stay.
So the hotel attendant told the old couple,
if you guys don't mind,
you can stay in my room.
Since I'm gonna be working here at the counter all night anyways,
the old man gladly accepted the offer,
went to this room,
and had a great night of sleep.
In the morning,
they went to the counter to check out and pay for the room.
The hotel attendant said,
no, thank you for letting me help you.
I'm glad you had a great night of sleep.
I feel great.
So there's no need to pay.
The old couple was very appreciative,
and they left.
Couple years later,
this hotel attendant received a letter from the old man,
please come to New York,
with the attached flight ticket,
and come to this address.
I will meet you over there.
The young man went to New York,
and it was the address of a big, huge hotel.
The old man said to him,
I bought this hotel for you.
With your service attitude,
I know you will be a great hotel manager,
and a great hotel owner.
That was a true story.
When you do everything out of kindness,
with the intention of paying back other people's kindness,
that is Bodhisattva's way of doing all the good deeds.
So be glad other people are letting you serve.
The fifth one is aspiring intention.
Bodhisattva always have great vows,
really want to help all sentient beings.
Their vows are grand and without any limits.
The most well-known,
Bodhisattva is Earth Treasure Bodhisattva.
Why is he called the Earth Treasure?
Because his heart is like the earth,
that nourishes all beings.
It's impartial,
it's grand,
and it can store everything.
Everybody who believes in him,
will get the treasure of the earth.
What was his vow?
Until the hells are empty,
I will never become a Buddha.
So everybody is safe out of hell.
Then,
I will reach Buddhahood.
What kind of compassion is that?
That's inconceivable,
but that's the kind of intention of a Bodhisattva.
If you have this kind of intention,
you will soon reach Buddhahood.
The sixth one is pure intention.
Not do good deeds,
so I have something in return.
I'll have good karma,
something good will happen to me.
No, you always have pure intention,
no motive,
except to help the person,
reach Buddhahood.
So these are the six intentions of a Bodhisattva.
We should be enthusiastic
when we are having these six intentions.
We should rejoice when other people
are having these six intentions.
And we should happily pray
that all beings will have these six intentions
and reach Buddhahood.
I want to end with a verse from the
universal worthy Bodhisattva.
My boundless compassion is endless.
Thought succeeds thought without interruption
and in bodily, vocal, and mental deeds
without weariness.
My boundless compassion
or vows
or good deeds
or love
is endless.
It's forever.
Thoughts after thoughts
without interruption.
Forever and consistently.
And in bodily, vocal, and mental deeds.
The actions that I do,
the words I say,
the thoughts I have,
they all align with this kind of virtue.
Without weariness,
I will never be tired.
With this great compassion,
with the good deeds I'm doing.
If you live this life
with these kind of
perfect intention,
you are a Bodhisattva.
You will change lives.
You will inspire everybody you meet.
You will touch other people's heart.
And you will definitely
be on the way
to reach Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Aum To Fo.