Today we are going to talk about Zen. Zen is the Chen school of Buddhism. We will use the
Dharma transmission of Patriarch Bodhidharma, the first Patriarch in China of the Chen school
in the late 5th and early 6th century BC. Zen itself, it means the Buddha mind. Patriarch
Bodhidharma says the nature is the mind, the mind is the Buddha, the Buddha is the way,
the way is Zen. Our Buddha nature is our pure mind. Our pure mind is the Buddha. You don't
have to look for Buddha elsewhere. It's right here, our own mind. And if you find the Buddha
then Buddha is the way to enlightenment and the enlightenment is Zen. How do we enter the
Zen or enter the way? There are actually two ways. One is entering the way through insight.
Two is entering the way through practice. Entering through insight, that's the instantaneous
entrance to the way. Entering through practice, that's the gradual entrance to the way. Let's
first talk about the instant enlightenment or we call it sudden enlightenment. We want
to enter the way or enter the Zen through insight. What is this insight? The insight
is to know that our mind, our awareness is the Buddha. How do we know we have this awareness?
It's not hard to see we have an aware nature, such as responding, perceiving, arching our
eyebrows, blinking our eyes, moving our eyes. It's not hard to see we have an aware nature,
such as responding, perceiving, arching our eyebrows, blinking our eyes, moving our eyes,
moving our hands and feet. That's all our miraculous awareness. So knowing this miraculous
awareness is our Buddha nature, then you are the Buddha. Whoever knows his or her nature
is the Buddha. But this nature is not apparent because we are strutted by our emotion and
our delusion. We are deluded in thinking all experience exists outside of us and we don't
know it's all created by our deluded mind. It's all illusory.
It's all illusory and it's only a false image. By gaining direct insight into the emptiness
of the mind, we will be in this evenness of the mind, knowing that everyone has this Buddha
nature. Then we will have no more distinction of the self and the others. We will maintain
a stable and clear mind like the wall. Patriarch Bodhidharma is famous for the wall meditation.
Facing a wall in silence is the best way to attain enlightenment. It's the best way to
attain enlightenment. It's the best way to attain enlightenment. It's the best way to attain
enlightenment.itt Music and meditation are pretty much the intermingle. This is the
best meditation. This wall symbolizes our mind when it's stable and Unmoved. And full
of clarity. All we have to do is to abandon all conceptuality and relax in this utter
clarity. We don't have to do anything. Just relax in the natural clarity of our mind.
The Song of enlightenment by Yongjia Zero Master is the best meditation for Mainstream
apartheid.
Once we awaken to the Tathagata Zen, the six noble deeds and the 10,000 good actions are
already complete within us.
Once we find our true nature, which is called the Tathagata Zen, then all the six paramitas
and all the wonderful virtues are already complete and done.
So this is the certain enlightenment through our insight.
Step number two is entering the way through practice.
This has four gradual steps.
One is to accept suffering.
We usually react negatively to the adversities of our lives, but we should know that everything
happened to us as the karmic ripening of our past deeds.
So everything happened for a reason.
In the Sutra, it says when you face adversity, don't be upset because it makes sense.
Everything makes sense in terms of karma.
They all happen for a reason.
So do not blame the situation or others.
We should take full responsibility of what's happening to us right now.
And we should say to ourselves, I accept it with an open heart without complaint of injustice
because there's no injustice in karma.
It's all happening the way it's supposed to be.
We want to spend our energy creating positive conditions.
By doing positive, wholesome deeds.
So be grateful of the situation, be cheerful and thankful, then it's no longer suffering.
Suffering usually exists because we do not accept the situation so we see it as suffering.
If we can accept it, and then we will have peace of mind, then the suffering will vanish
and dissolve.
When we accept suffering, we have entered the way.
Number two, adapting to conditions.
Number one is talking about pain and sorrow.
Number two is talking about pleasure and happiness.
If we are blessed by some great reward such as fame or fortune, it is a fruit of a seed
planted by us in the past.
When the condition changes, it will end.
So do not be caught up in our pleasure either.
While the success and failure depend on conditions, the mind neither waxes or wanes.
Even though conditions keep changing, but our mind will stay the same.
It doesn't increase or decrease with the outside conditions.
It stays calm and unmoved.
Those who remain unmoved by the wind of joy silently follow the way.
That's when we are following the way to enlightenment.
Number three, seeking nothing.
That is the mind of contentment.
We will understand the meaninglessness of all selfishness.
In the Sutra, it says, to seek is to suffer. To seek nothing is bliss. If we can be content
and seek nothing, that is true happiness. We even abandon the idea of seeking enlightenment.
It says in the Songs of Enlightenment that it cannot be grasped, it cannot be rejected,
just what can be obtained within the unobtainable. That's the reality. There's nothing to gain.
We don't gain enlightenment. We cannot grasp enlightenment. We cannot reject enlightenment
because it is the state as it is. So there's nothing to do, there's nothing to obtain in
the unobtainable. The subject of attaining and the object of attainable, they are both
illusory, just concepts from our deluded consciousness. Understand this, then we will no longer seek
for anything. But that doesn't mean we become inactive and
blind.
4. To unite with the way. Finally, we are like the instant enlightenment with the insight,
knowing the emptiness of the self and all that is within us.
This is also called practicing the dharma. Dharma is the truth that all natures are pure.
By this truth, all appearances are empty. Now we truly understand the emptiness of all
nature. Defilement and attachment, subject and object do not exist. All is illusory,
just like the moon that's reflected in the water. It's only a false image. That is the
reality. It says in the sutra, Dharma includes no beings because it is free from the impurity
of beings. Dharma includes no self because it is free from the impurity of self. Dharma
is emptiness. It has no living beings. When you have a concept of living beings, that
is still impurity. It is no longer emptiness, and doesn't include the concept of a self. When you
have the self is still impurity all things are pure in nature because they're all emptiness so
that is true insight when we have the insight of emptiness that's when we can give our body life
and property in charity without regret without the vanity of the giver the gift or recipient
without bias or attachment that's when we have unconditional giving like a true bodhisattva
at the end we will finally realize the mind is the buddha the buddha is the mind beyond the mind
there's no buddha beyond the buddha there is no mind our pure mind is the buddha is zen and is
the way in this lifetime use all situations to practice
the dharma to find the way by accepting suffering adapting to condition seeking
nothing and to unite with the way we will realize the mind that's chanting amitabha
is the buddha so that's the class for today thank you for listening amitabha