Today we're going to talk about pure mind, pure land.
How do we take rebirth in Amitabha's pure land?
We must have a pure mind.
The pure mind is without afflictions and without attachments.
It is our true mind, the compassionate mind.
Today we will use three sutras to describe this pure mind.
The Mimalakirti Sutra, the Awakening of Faith in Mahayana,
Shastra, and the Contemplation Sutra.
It talks about three kinds of mind in all these three sutras.
Let's first talk about the Mimalakirti Sutra.
It says bodhisattva can create their buddha field or their buddha land.
What kind of bodhisattva will create what kind of world?
For example, a bodhisattva with a mind of positive thoughts,
when he attains enlightenment, living beings free of hypocrisy and deceit will be born in his buddha field.
A bodhisattva's mind is always positive.
He will not have anyone who comes and be negative and deceiving.
If a bodhisattva has the mind of high resolve,
which means he really wants to be awakened and not be deluded anymore.
When he attains enlightenment,
living beings who have harvest merits and virtues because of their high resolve
will be born in his buddha field.
Lastly, if a bodhisattva has the mind of virtuous application,
when he attains enlightenment,
living beings lived by all virtuous principles will be born in his buddha land.
So what kind of people are surrounding us?
It's all because of our mind.
If we are always generous,
we will attract generous people into our world.
If we are always patient,
we will attract people that are tolerant in our world.
If we are always angry,
then we attract bitter people in our world.
It's all tantamount to our own mind.
Nothing is beyond this cause and effect.
The cause is our mind.
So we should reside in our pure mind.
Shri Puta heard this.
He thought to himself,
Oh Shakyamuni Buddha,
the Buddha of the Saha world,
he must have some impure mind
because the world is so corrupted and impure,
our world right now.
Then Buddha put his foot and his toe on the ground.
All of a sudden,
Shri Puta, he sees the world that Buddha sees.
Amazingly,
the world is without any darkness
or corruption.
It's perfectly pure.
Then he realized it's the mind of his that is impure,
not the world.
Now let's talk about the awakening of faith
in Mahayana by Bodhisattva Asvagosha.
He said we must cultivate the same three minds.
First, we must cultivate the straightforward mind.
Correctly meditate on the principle of suchness.
Therefore, straightforward means without any impurity.
Honestly, meditate on your true nature,
the true suchness.
Then we must have the mind of profoundness
deep inside of our heart.
It's not attached to the worldly experience,
only reside in our true nature.
That's most profound.
There is no limit to the joyful accumulation
of all kinds of goodness.
Our true nature is perfectly pure in its essential nature,
but now we are full of defilements and impurities.
We must clean off these impurities by constant cultivation.
Get rid of our greed, anger, ignorance,
and attachment, delusion about the world.
Lastly, we must have the mind of great compassion.
Great compassion is the mind of the Buddha.
How do we know if we have the Buddha mind?
When we have unconditional compassion,
loving kindness for all sentient beings.
The sixth patriarch of Zen Buddhism,
Hui Nan,
when he was first given the bowl
and the robe by the fifth patriarch,
people were jealous of him, chasing him.
He had to hide for fifteen whole years.
He actually hid in a party of hunters.
Occasionally, he would preach to them
in a way that befitted their understanding.
Sometimes they would ask him to watch their net.
When he sees like creatures,
he would set them free.
When he cooked the meat in the pan,
he would only eat the vegetables.
Because he is a bodhisattva with great compassion,
he's able to endure this kind of life for fifteen years.
He doesn't have any affliction.
He doesn't feel suffering.
He's completely pure and perfect in this kind of situation.
As long as we have the pure mind,
the living environment would be pure.
Lastly, the Contemplation Sutra.
This is really a Pure Land Sutra.
It says we must also have these three minds.
First, we must have the most sincere mind.
When we chant Amitabha,
we should have the utmost sincerity.
This sincerity also means
we sincerely respect all sentient beings.
Because all sentient beings are future Buddhas.
Do you respect all people around you as Buddhas?
That's how a true cultivator of Pure Land Buddhism should be.
Master Daozhen, she was a doctor when she was young.
One day, a felon was in the hospital
who was involved in a gunshot.
Everybody was talking about him,
but he was not her patient.
While waiting for a patient's report,
she started doing her evening recitation.
After she finished,
she prayed for this felon with the gunshot.
After she opened her eyes,
she noticed that felon was calling her.
He said,
You come help me and be my doctor.
I am in great pain.
My mind is very depressed and chaotic.
The doctor said,
I understand.
I would be too if I were you.
I am a Buddhist.
Whenever I am sad and bitter,
I chant Amitabha.
It always calms me down.
Amitabha is most compassionate and equal.
Chanting his name brings out our Buddha nature
that is within all of us.
She gave him a picture of the Buddha
and a chanting bee.
The next day she came.
Much to her surprise,
the Buddha picture was stuck on the wall
of the patient in the next bed.
This gunshot patient said to her,
I thought the new patient needs the Buddha picture
and the Buddha bee more than I do.
So I gave them to him.
Can you please give me another Buddha bee?
She was so touched.
Because he is already a bodhisattva
trying to save others.
She actually gave him her own chanting bee.
One day the doctor was walking up the stairs
in the hospital.
She saw the back of two men.
One is a police officer.
One is this patient.
His feet in chain,
but his hands was holding
the Buddha bee that she gave him.
She paid respect to him.
She knew that he did not need the chain anymore
because his feet are already stepping
on pure lotus flowers.
The pure mind of the doctor
saved this person's heart.
No matter where he is,
he is with Amitabha.
So when we have the utmost sincere mind,
we can touch the lives
of everybody in our lives.
Then we should have the mind of deep faith,
deep faith in Amitabha
and our true nature.
Think all the time that I have created
immeasurable evil karma
in all my lives of reincarnation.
If such karma has formed
the empty space in ten directions
will not contain it.
Now I am lucky.
I am a human who have heard the Dharma.
I should single-mindedly chant Amitabha,
see creepers in the pure land.
Otherwise, I will keep reincarnating
in the sixth path
and immense sea of suffering
without a way of liberation.
We should really have deep faith
in Amitabha
and Pure Land Buddhism.
Mostly, we have to have deep faith
in our true nature
like the precious mirror.
The mirror is now dirty.
We need to polish off all the dust.
That's all our afflictions and attachments.
Then it will be clean.
It will reflect everything clearly.
Lastly, we should aspire rebirth
by transferring merits.
Do not chant Amitabha
seeking rebirth for ourselves.
Every Amitabha is for all sentient beings.
We have this way of transferring
our merits to all sentient beings
in the Dharma realm
because they are all suffering,
all suffering and reincarnating.
That's the heart of a Buddha,
same as the great compassionate heart.
This is what our Buddha mind,
our Bodhi mind looks like.
In Tantide Buddhism,
it's called the threefold contemplation
in one mind.
Threefold contemplation,
the void meditation,
unreal meditation,
and mean meditation.
All contain in our one true mind.
Void meditation is understanding
the emptiness of all things.
When we have high resolve,
want to be liberated,
seeing things clearly,
not be deluded
and confused by the world,
we have the profound mind
to be liberated.
And we have deep faith
in our true nature.
When we deal with our personal affairs
and business,
we should have high watchfulness,
not be swayed or confused
by the external conditions.
If we are having favorable conditions,
we are not attached.
In unfavorable conditions,
we are not angry.
Then we want to have the unreal meditation,
which means we still have
an unreal existence in the world.
Even though everything is empty in nature,
but we still have a life to live.
Life of a Bodhisattva
is to have virtue,
great compassion,
and chant for all sentient beings.
Balance, emptiness,
and existence,
then it's the middle way,
the mean.
Then that's the mind
of pure positive thoughts,
straightforward mind,
and most sincere mind.
Why do we have to wait
until our life is up
to go to the pure land?
It's just now having the three minds
or one mind.
Chanting Amitabha,
it is already the pure land
right here,
right now.
Our lotus flower
is already full bloom.
Now it's the new year's.
Hope everyone will make the resolve
to build a pure land
in your life right now.
Then you'll definitely
go to Amitabha's
western pure land
because your mind is in
accordance with Amitabha's mind.
In conclusion,
it is your mind
that becomes a Buddha.
Nay, it is your mind
that is indeed
Buddha.
Buddha
is not Amitabha
saving us.
That's outside of our mind.
The Buddha
is you.
When you have this mind,
the pure mind,
the pure Buddha essence,
the pure self nature,
you are the Buddha.
It is your mind
that is indeed
Buddha.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.