Today we are going to talk about concepts.
We always say we need to let go.
Let go of what?
We are going to talk about 24 concepts that we should let go.
The first one is Attainment.
Attainment is when we gain something from nothing, such as fame, fortune, power.
We think the more we have, the better we are.
This is out of our greed.
We think there is something to attain, but little do we know, a lot of times misfortune
is blessing in disguise.
There is a wise old man with a beautiful stallion.
He loves this horse.
One day the horse disappeared.
Everybody came to comfort him about his loss.
He said this might not be a bad thing.
Sure enough, a few days later, the horse came back, brought another beautiful horse.
Everybody came and congratulated him.
He said this probably is not a good thing.
His son loved this new horse, rode it every day.
One day he fell off the horse and broke his leg.
Everybody came to comfort him about his son's misfortune, but the old man said this might
not be a bad thing.
Sure enough, the government was drafting for people to go to war.
Because his son broke his leg, he didn't have to go.
A lot of people died in that war.
A lot of times misfortune are blessing in disguise.
Whether it's attainment or not.
It's a blessing in disguise.
It's not necessarily just
a blessing or actually a photosynthesis.
The main thing was forgiveness.
It's Dasana.
Desana.
It was Changlin.
ls
this life that we want. That's why we keep living and it will take us into many lifetimes
of reincarnation because we have this strong attachment to this allied consciousness, the
deluded mind. Because of this attachment to this life faculty, we are continuously in
reincarnation. One and two are a group because it's based on greed. Number three and four
are a group. Number three is generic similarities. Number four is the similarity. Number three
generic similarity is when we are in a group that are similar. For example, dogs, they're
all dogs because they're similar. Arhats are saints that have relinquished the idea of
the self so they are similar. Bodhisattvas, they're all like-minded who want to save sentient
beings.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
So they are called generic similarities. But there are dissimilarities within similarities.
For example, we are all human, but they are mundane and they are saints. Mundane are actually
called people with dissimilarities. We all have very dissimilar afflictions and defilements.
But the saints, the more enlightened they are, the more similar they become. So the
people are actually called people with dissimilarities.
Number five, six, seven are based on samadhi. Number five is no thought samadhi. This samadhi
is cultivated by externalists. They go into deep meditation where their six consciousness
stop working. Therefore, they have no thoughts. They stop all thinking. They think that's
the way to liberation. But in fact, it's not. They think that's the way to liberation. But
in fact, it's not. They think that's the way to liberation. But in fact, it's not. They
think that's the way to liberation. But in fact, it's not. They think that's the way
to liberation. But in fact, it's not. It's a fourth samadhi. It's like you put a rock
on top of the grass, hoping it will never grow. But the root is still there. You're
just stopping thoughts.
Number six, samadhi of extinction. That's the samadhi of arhats. They also stop their
six consciousness from working. But they also stop all feelings. They have no feelings of
pain or pleasure.
They have no feelings of pain or pleasure. They have no thinking. They're different from
externalists in the fact that they use this to let go of the attachment to the self. So
they're more enlightened and their afflictions are eradicated based on the samadhi. But this
is still not the samadhi of buddhas. This is only a stage of the arhats. This is not
the ultimate samadhi either.
Number seven, samadhi of the past.
Number seven is reward of non-thought.
Number five, no-thought samadhi is the cause. Reward of no-thought, that's the effect. People
who practice the no-thought-samadhi, when they relinquish their body this lifetime,
they take rebirth in the heaven of no thought-in the fourth dhyana. That's when they reborn
in that heavenly realm. But that is still not the samadhi.
not a good place to take rebirth in because you will not be enlightened either. You just
have no thoughts for a long, long, long time. Last time we talked about there are five wrong
views. One is attachment to unbeneficial precepts and one is attachment to the wrong view. Number
five is attachment to unbeneficial precepts. This is the wrong cause of enlightenment.
You think practicing the samadhi, stopping thoughts would be enlightenment, but that's
the wrong cause. Taking rebirth in the heaven of no thought is attachment to wrong view,
the wrong effect. So cause and effect, they're both wrong. Externalists, they think that's
the way to enlightenment, but it's not. So all these are only concepts. There is actually
no samadhi to gain and there's no enlightenment to gain.
After all, number eight, nine, ten, that's above our language. Number eight is body of
nouns. We give names to people, place, and things. For example, body, mind. These are
nouns. When you have more than one, it's called bodies. Then number nine, bodies of sentences.
You put the nouns into sentences. You make a phrase.
Body and mind are both impermanent. That's a sentence.
Then we have bodies of phonemes. These are words.
So number ten is the basis of nouns and sentences. All these are only concepts, human-made concepts.
We should not be attached to words, to nouns, to sentences. These are illusions. These three,
they can be in the form of words. These are illusions. These three, they can be in the
form of words. These are illusions. These three, they can be in the form of words. These
are illusions. These three, they can be in the form of words. These are illusions. These
are illusions. These three, they can be in the form of words. These three, they can be
in the form of words. These three, they can be in the form of words. These are illusions.
Let's start.
They come in contact with the six sense objects of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, and
Darma. recycling and Notes
Language, they can be in three sense objects. In sight, when we see writings, or it can
be sound when we hear language. It can be...
Sitting
sitting
Nor
Seven
Sides
Three
or thoughts. It's called Dharma. That's the object of the mind. But if you want to
realize your true nature, you have to be away from these three sense objects. In the Awakening
of Faith in Mahayana by Asvangosha, he says, suchness transcends verbalization, description
and conceptualization. It's not what you hear in words. It's not what you see in writing.
It's not even the thoughts, the language in your mind. It should be away from all these
language for you to be really enlightened and see your true suchness.
11, 12, 13 and 14, there are four forms of rising and ceasing.
Everything is up and down. Everything is up and down. Everything is up and down. Everything
is up and down. All these conditions are rising. They have these four forms. Our body goes
through birth, aging, sickness and death. Every one of our thoughts. It goes through
rising, abiding, changing and ceasing. Every single one of our thoughts. And the whole
world comes into being, dwelling and ceasing.
decaying, and disappearing. Every condition arising, they go through these four stages.
So we should not be upset when we get old, when we get sick, or even when we die. Because
these are also illusions, concepts that we come up with. The whole reincarnation is only
happening in a dream. 15, 16, 17 is about karma, revolving, that's reincarnation. We're
always in this river of turning and flowing. We cannot get out of this strong current of
reincarnation. Lifetime after lifetimes, we want to turn around by getting out of reincarnation.
Number 16, distinction. That's talking about karma.
Number 16, distinction. That's talking about karma. Number 16, distinction. That's talking
about karma. Every karma has its definite effect. Wholesome thoughts will have good
retribution. Unwholesome thoughts will give you negative retribution. Karma is definite.
Cause and effect is always for sure. They cannot be mixed up, and they cannot make any
mistakes. That's why it's distinct and definite. Number 17 is interaction. Interaction
is always for sure. Cause and effect are always corresponding with each other. That's why
it's called interaction. Good cause will have good effect. Bad cause will have bad effect.
Greed, anger, ignorance will bring you to the three lower realms. If you are kind, compassionate,
you go to higher realms or go to the western pure land. It's all about your cause that
will have the corresponding effect or retribution. Number 18, distinction. That's talking about
karma. Grandy represents the opportunity, heaven represents the scandal, and nieders
represent the
hoped.
The important thing is, your ancestors who always blowed the candles of karma believe
in you.
Being with God is life.
You might say, Even though the people of this world is very powerful, it's the same
because of the cause or effect.
Even though the people of this world are very powerful, it's because of the Cause
we have no time left number 19 is sequence everything must have order like you go to
first grade second grade you move up or when you cook you must wash your vegetables cut them and
then cook you cannot do it out of order or you cannot get anything done so things must have
sequence and order if you're cultivating first you take refuge in the buddha dharma sangha then
you take the five precepts and then the bodhisattva precept you cannot do it out of order but this
order is also only a concept 20 21 and 22 they are a group 20 is about time time is marking of
intervals years
month days hours these are intervals of time this is only relative some people say you cannot chant
the sutra at night because you're gonna attract ghosts but these are all made up concepts time
is only relative and it's only happening on our earth the time elsewhere is totally different
21 is direction front back right left
north
south up and down these are man-made concept of direction location these are also relative because
we think it's important some people very into feng shui they think how you place thing is very
important that's only human made concept 22 is numeration numbers also human made concept we are
very
attached to number money we want a lot of money oil price so expensive right now we are very attached
to the price the number in our medical report it's horrible we're very upset every day we are attached
to these numbers and our emotion goes up and down because of these numbers but do we know they're
phantasms made up by our mind so we should try to let go of our memory that's the great point is
of our attachment to time, direction, and numeration.
Lastly, 23 and 24, one is combination,
one is discontinuity.
Combination, it's about blending and uniting,
such as cause and effect, they are blending and uniting.
Water and milk, put them together, it becomes milk water.
So that's combination.
Some people believe in combination,
some people believe in discontinuity,
such as people might think there's no cause and effect.
Everything happens, it's created by a God.
That's spontaneity.
Our hats are caught up in combination of cause and effect.
Externalists, they are caught up in the spontaneity.
So both of these are not in alignment
with our enlightenment
and our true suchness.
You have to let go of both of these attachments
for you to be fully enlightened.
These 24 are human-made concepts that we live by.
But if you can see all these things,
there's not a me, there's not a real existence,
but human-made ideas.
That way you can truly let go,
and one day you will really see
the world as an enlightened person.
You will feel liberation in your own mind.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.