Today we are going to talk about separation from illusion.
Buddha says to separate from illusion is to be enlightened.
We will use the Perfect Enlightenment Sutra together with the Shogama Sutra to understand
enlightenment.
In the Perfect Enlightenment Sutra, Buddha taught Samantabhadra Bodhisattva there are
actually four steps to the separation from illusion.
1.
To separate oneself from all illusory projections and deluded realms.
This world that we live in is merely a projection of images from our own alaya consciousness,
therefore all is created by our mind is merely an illusion.
This sutra uses the metaphor of a man with the illness of the eye.
The sickness of the eye symbolizes our ignorance, and the illusory flower means our attachment
to the four great elements as attributes of our bodies, and the condition of the sixth
sense objects as attributes of our mind.
We think this physical body is me, and the mind that grabs onto the sixth sense objects
as me.
This is all just our illusion.
There is in reality no flower in the sky yet the sick man mistakenly clings to it.
Because of his mistaken clinging, he is not only deluded about the intrinsic nature of
the empty sky, he is also confused about the rising of the flower.
Because of his false existence to which he clings, he remains in the turning wheel of
birth and death.
So there is actually no flower in the sky.
empty sky symbolizes our perfect nature. It's without any ignorance. Our ignorance is what
makes us keep reincarnating, so we need to let go of the idea of the self.
There is a devoted Buddhist practitioner whose farmland is being occupied by a bully in the
village without permission for many years. One time, the land officer came to mark all
the lands in the village. The bully was very upset and said to the officer who dared to
come over here to mark the land, I will beat him to the ground. Then everyone started arguing
and he said you can sue me in court if you want. The Buddhist lady came in and said,
when we are all together, we should be happy. Please don't be angry. Then she said to the
man, do you want to give the land back to us? He said, of course not. Then she said,
oh that's no problem. You are like my parents. I'm not going to give it back to you.
i should be filial to you this land officer just wants to mark the land so everybody know our
boundaries tomorrow you can still form this land if you're happy then i'm happy she was about to
leave that's when the man actually called her name from behind he said in tears i want to give the
land back to you everyone in the village was so surprised by this dramatic change when you're
selfless and sincere things will always work out for the best so be selfless and kind and
know the illusion of the self number two however when one clings firmly to the mind that separates
this mind should also be taken as illusion and one should separate oneself from it we do not
want to cling to the mind that's doing the separation from illusion because when you
attach to it it's also an illusion for example when we meditate we
usually call it mindfulness meditation why because we have awareness that is mindful
of an object of meditation such as the name amitabha or emptiness in this case we're focusing
on contemplating on the illusory nature of our body and mind but this mind that is aware
also needs to let go if i catch myself having a negative thought about a person at work i tell
myself
i should let go of the thoughts i should let go of the thoughts but the more you say that to yourself
the more you think about it so let go of this awareness and naturally you will be able to let
go of wandering thoughts and you will be able to feel at ease so do not be attached to this
awareness either number three because the separation is illusion it should be separated
the separation we used above should be separated as well
because it is only a dharma tool we should not be attached to this dharma tool
it is also illusory so there's no siddhama for anyone do not be attached to your practice
either for example i have to chant ten thousand amitabha a day or i have to meditate for five
hours in order to be a good practitioner if you're attached to your dharma it is also ignorance
in the diamond sutra buddha says if someone says that the buddha has the false
dharma he is really slandering the dharma
because if someone has a certain dharma he is calumniating the buddha
for the person could not comprehend what i have divulged
so if someone says buddha has a certain dharma he is slandering the buddha
because he does not know what the dharma means so let go of our attachment to the
dharma as well it is illusory dharma number four one should then be free from
even the separating from the illusion of separation all the separation of delusion is also delusory
above should be separated. So let go of separating or separation of illusion. Every last bit
of attachment should be let go. In conclusion, when there remains nothing to be separated
from, all illusions are eliminated. When all illusions extinguish, that's when the perfect
enlightenment remains unmoved. Then that's the real complete enlightenment. This sutra
uses another metaphor. It's like rubbing two pieces of wood together to obtain fire.
When the wood completely burns, the ashes fly away and the smoke vanishes. The two pieces
of wood is like number one, separation from delusion. And the fire is like separation
from awareness. The smoke vanishes is like number three, let go of separation. And ashes
flying away is like let go of letting go of delusion.
Letting go of separation. What's left over is just the ground that's perfectly unmoved.
This ground symbolizes our Buddha nature that is perfectly enlightened. This is called using
illusion to remedy illusion. Use the illusory body and mind to cultivate the illusory dharma.
So that's how we reach enlightenment. That's our innate prajna. Now let's combine it with
Triyogama Sutra and the Sutra Guanyin Bodhisattva.
Guanyin Bodhisattva said, Initially, I entered the flow through hearing and forgot objective
states. Since the sense object and the sense organs were quiet, the characteristics of
movement and stillness crystallized and did not arise. So Guanyin Bodhisattva became enlightened
through hearing. By hearing, he forgot the objective states. There's no more external
environment. Both sound, which is movement, and stillness, which is no sound, they become
invisible. They don't bother her anymore. And she was with her suchness, with her enlightened
mind. This is the first stage, separation from delusion. After that, gradually advancing,
the hearing and what was heard both disappeared.
That's number two, separating from the awareness. Once the hearing was gone, there was nothing
to rely on, and awareness and the object awareness became empty. That's number three, let go
of separation.
So the awareness and the object awareness were both empty. When the emptiness of awareness
reached ultimate perfection, the emptiness and what was being emptied then also ceased
to be.
That's number four, let go of letting go of separation. Since the protection and extinction
were gone, still extinction was revealed. This still extinction is when there is no
illusion to be eliminated.
That's our perfect enlightenment. That's how Guanyin Bodhisattva became enlightened is through
this process of separating from illusion. In conclusion, to know illusion is to depart
from it. There is no need to contrive expedient means. To depart from illusion is to be enlightened.
There is no gradual steps. To know illusion is to depart from it. We just have to know
what is illusion.
Everything is illusion. There is no gradual steps or expedient means. We just have to
depart from illusion. Then that's perfect complete enlightenment. So all we have to do
is to know.
This is a certain teaching of the Mahayana Buddhism. This is where we should put all
our attention to because this is the fastest and the quickest way to enlightenment. This
enlightenment is called the complete illumination of intrinsic enlightenment. This is the ultimate
enlightenment of the body. My the knowledge of enlightenment has been enhanced have been
strengthened. This is the only way you can attain enlightenment. What we have to do is to
which is pure in essence and the samadhi is called the samadhi in which all is seen to be like
illusion this enlightenment is the perfect complete enlightenment all we have to do is to know
illusion when you know then it is done it's so easy we don't even know how this is called certain
enlightenment where the causal ground and the final enlightenment is all based on the same thing
which is a perfectly pure enlightened mind so that's the class for today thank you for listening