中文字幕由 Amara.org 社群提供
entire company. It actually created everything. You can call it my soul. This
will die with your body dying but this will not die. It goes on with every
lifetime carries with you. The Alaya means the storehouse. It stores
everything that you ever done in your every lifetime. It's like a super
computer. It remembers everything. When the right causes and the
condition hits, it creates reality. So everything that you're experiencing
today is based on your Alaya. For example, we see the Azusa mountain here. Is it
real? It's not real. It's all of us here
are
Alaya. We have the same kind of causes, same kind of karma from prior
experiences create the mountain that we're seeing today. So everything is
created by the Alaya. That's why we say your mind creates the universe. We're not
kidding. It's true. Your mind creates everything that you experience. You just
don't know. Your Alaya stores everything you ever did at the right time. It will
bring out the effect of whatever you did before. Your wholesome and unwholesome
deed at the right time. It happens you know whoever you're married to today
whoever it's your mom who is your dad is all based on what you store here. So it's
amazing that after you understand this eight conscious what do you do. So there's
actually two things to change your life. First is you want to change where? When.
here because you cannot change it it's very stubborn it doesn't change it just
hold on to the idea of me okay so all you have to do is change here change what you
think how you think you gotta be positive and wholesome and get rid of all
the unwholesome negative thoughts okay because it creates reality it goes up
here everything that you're thinking every day it comes up here and it gets
stored and it becomes your future nobody creates your future your own mind
creates the future so change your thought you change your world there's a
mom she has two daughters the older daughter marries someone that sells
umbrella the younger daughter marries someone that sells ice cream so when it's
raining she starts crying because like oh the younger daughter's ice cream will
not sell so she starts crying
it's sunny she started crying again because the older daughter's umbrella
will not sell okay so every day she's crying one day she met a monk a monk
asked her why are you always crying and then she told him what happened and the
monk said why don't you change your thoughts when it's raining wonderful oh
my older daughter's umbrella will sell right when it's sunny it's wonderful
ice cream will sell very well so when you'll be smiling
instead of crying every day it's all up to you how you determine your situation
so what you think is very important so if you train yourself to be positive and
get rid of all the negativity all the complaints and all the anger and hatred
and get rid of all of that because that will just create a bad life and bad
future for yourself it's not worth it so that's the first thing that you do the
second thing you do is you meditate.
When we are trying to meditate, we are trying to go outside of here.
It's not actually just cognitive thinking.
You are actually at a higher level of consciousness.
You are actually right up here.
You immediately touch your higher consciousness that is creating the universe.
You have the sea of your self-nature inside here.
You never tap into it.
That's why your self-nature is not coming out.
But if you meditate more, you will come here.
So some people will have psychic ability.
They can levitate. All these can happen.
Why? Because they are here.
They think at a much higher consciousness than we do.
So the key to studying the A consciousness is for us to change the way we think to be positive
and to meditate, to be in touch.
To be in touch with our own self-nature.
That's the class for today. Thank you for listening.