Today we are going to talk about fate.
Last time we talked about karma.
So everything that's happened to you right now is because of your words, your thoughts,
and your actions from before.
Your merit and demerit that caused the relationship you are having in this lifetime.
All the relationships, your parents, your children, your siblings, and even people you
meet on the street, there is fate involved.
There are four types of relationships.
All relationships fall into one of the four categories.
The first one is to repay your kindness.
There are people that are in your life, you did good things to them before, now they are
here to pay you back.
They are the people that loves you, that take care of you, that's nice to you.
So they are the people that's in your life to repay your kindness.
Second, there are people in your life to revenge.
You did something wrong to them before, now they are in your life to sabotage you.
The third category is to repay your kindness.
The third category is to pay your kindness.
third type to solicit karmic debt. Debt is not money. Debt is the merit and the demerit
that you did to them. So they are here to take it back. You owe them. They are here
to take it back. And there are also people in your life to repay the karmic debt. They
owe you. So they are paying you back this lifetime. Everyone in your life is because
of the four types of relationships. The first is repaying kindness. Some people are in your
life to pay back all the good things you did to them in your prior lifetimes. There is
a man. He fell in love with this wonderful woman. They've been together for three years.
They had a wonderful relationship.
The man was asking her to get married. The lady decided to marry someone else. The guy
was devastated. He said, why is this happening? His dad found him a monk to help him. The
monk said, oh, you must be tired. Why don't you take a nap? The man took a nap. He had
a dream. He dreamt of a woman that died on the beach. The first guy walked by, didn't
do anything.
The second guy walked by, felt sorry for the lady, put his jacket on her to cover her up.
The third guy walked by actually buried her respectfully. So the man woke up and told
the monk about the dream. The monk said, you know what? Your girlfriend was that lady in
your prior lifetime. You were the second guy that covered her up.
She is paying you back for three years for that kindness. But now she's marrying the
third person because the third person actually buried her. That's called paying back kindness.
A lot of people in our life that are kind to us, that's because we did good things to
them. So always do good things to people. The second type of relationship, they are
here for revenge.
The second type of relationship, they are here for revenge. In the middle of the night,
in the Ming Dynasty, there is a Mr. Fang. Mr. Fang is the most well-known scholar. He
helps the emperor to rule the country. Unfortunately, there was a tyrant that came, invaded the country
and took over. He asked Mr. Fang, the scholar, to write the announcement to the entire country
about the new emperorship. Mr. Fang refused. He fiercely refused. The tyrant was very upset.
So he beheaded Mr. Fang and his whole 9th generation plus the 10th generation, which is his teacher,
for a total of 873 people. He beheaded them. Why did this happen to him? This goes back
to Mr. Fang's dad. Before Mr. Fang was born, he wanted to find a good burial site for his
family.
One day, he finally found the perfect location and he decided to excavate the burial plot
the next day. But that night, he dreamed of an old man wearing red, came to him and
pleaded, please delay the digging because my family is not living there. Please give
us three days to move. We need three days. Just give us three days. Mr. Fang's dad woke
up. He ignored the dream. The next day, he started digging. He was terrified. He was
afraid to do this. He was afraid to do this. He was afraid to do this. He was afraid to
do this. He was afraid. He was afraid to do this. He was afraid to do this. He was afraid.
digging. They found a huge nest of red snakes. He was disgusted by the sight. He actually
light a torch and burned all the snakes. A total of 873 snakes. So why did Mr. Fong came
to his dad to be his son? He is here for revenge. So whatever you do to people, it will always
come back to you. So do not do evil deeds and hurt other people's lives. The third type
is people that are here to take back karmic debt. And there are people that are paying
you back for good things that you did. This is a story about when Buddha was around. One
day when he was teaching his disciple, he told Ananda, Ananda, you go into the village
and
he asked the lady by the well for a bucket of water.
Ananda went into the village and then really saw an old lady next to the well.
He asked, may I please have a bucket of water?
The lady looked at him and said,
This water is only for our villagers.
You don't belong here, please leave.
She was very upset.
So Ananda went back to Buddha and told him what happened.
Buddha said, very well.
Sariputta, another student of Buddha,
you go now to the city and find the old lady and ask for a bucket of water.
So Sariputta went and the old lady saw him.
She was elated and immediately gave him a bucket of water.
She went home, got him a lot of food and offered it to him.
So Sariputta went back to Buddha and told him what happened.
And then everybody asked Buddha, why the big difference?
Buddha said, once there was a rat that died on the street.
There was a businessman that walked by, was disgusted by the dead rat.
He pinched his nose and then walked away.
The second guy was a student.
He saw the dead rat and buried the rat respectfully.
The old lady by the well was very upset.
The old lady by the well was very upset. The old lady by the well was very upset.
Ananda you were the first person that was disgusted by the rat.
That's why the lady hated you, because you were disgusted by her.
And Sariputta you were the student that buried the rat.
That's why she loves you and is paying you back.
Ok, so everything has a reason, everybody in your life has a reason.
But now in the future, you feel like you are someone, you want to be someone, you want to be someone.
So Sariputta Danny beat Buddha.
know about karma and faith we want to do all that is good so in Confucius teaching there is a very
good saying that sums up this four relationship it says kindness should be repaid let enmity just
fade away grudges are better forgotten make kindness grow day by day okay so this is actually
a poem kindness should be repaid all the people that are nice to us we want to be nicer to them
have more love for them respect them and appreciate their kindness that the kindness will keep growing
let enmity just fade away if there's any hatred or people here in your life to sabotage you
just forget about it and move on now let it fade away do not remember all the demerit that they do
to you
grudges are better forgotten don't hold grudges because that will only give you more negative
karma if you want good karma don't hold any grudges you want to make kindness and love
grow day by day only love is the solution if you want to have good relationships in your future
life just be nice to people and give people love kindness
and grudges
compassion so this is the class for today hope that we're all fine in our heart to do good deeds
and change our life for the better thank you for listening