We are going to talk about the Lankavatara Sutra.
This is the only sutra that the first patriarch of Zen Buddhism Bodhidharma passed down to
the second patriarch Hui Ke, from master to master, Buddha to Buddha.
The word Lanka is actually a city, like Sri Lanka, is the city on the top of the mountain.
Avatara is the ultimate jewel.
The whole mountain is made out of precious jewels, that's the place where Buddha is.
It's very difficult to get to, almost impossible.
It's treacherous and dangerous.
How do we get there?
We will try to explain the sutra as a whole in terms of the four doctrines.
One is the five dharmas, the second one is the three natures, then we have the eight
consciousnesses, then two kinds of no-self.
So you just have to remember them like the telephone number.
Five, three, eight, two.
Everything is described as the five dharmas.
The first dharma is name.
We give everything an identity, a name.
For example, we have me, I, and my mom, my dad, we label everything with a name.
We might like name brand, such as Louis Vuitton, or Mercedes, or Rolex, we give value based
on fabricated concept of the dharma.
Very important.
of our mind. The sutra is letting us know that everything is created by our mind only.
There's nothing existing outside of our mind. This name is also fabricated from our mind.
Number two is appearances. We have name, we have appearances. That means all the forms
that you see in this world of phenomenon, a thing, person, event, is all appearances.
We attach to these appearances. We start having emotions and we create karma. We might have
greed, anger, or ignorance based on attaching to all the life situations.
So we arrive to number three, our discrimination.
Our conceptual mind. Because we are attached to the name and attached to the appearances,
we start having discrimination. We think in terms of duality. What is beneficial to me?
What is gain? What is loss? What is pleasure? What is pain? This discrimination itself is
already full of the idea of me, the ego.
We think in terms of duality.
That's how we discriminate. These three dharmas are the world of a mundane person.
How do we ascend to a different world? We need to understand that name, appearances,
and our discrimination are only false images created by our mind.
That's how we have number four, right knowledge.
Right knowledge.
And number five, suchness, the reality. We learn Buddhism to see the truth of the world.
It's called right knowledge. This is the inner state of self-realization of noble wisdom.
We can call it prajna. This wisdom is the insight, knowing the illusory nature of name,
appearances, the object of the world, and the world. This wisdom is the insight, knowing the illusory nature of name, appearances, the object of the world, and the world.
This wisdom is the insight, knowing the illusory nature of name, appearances, the object of the world, and the world.
And our discrimination, the subject of the world.
It's called right knowledge.
They are both only made from the mind.
If we can get away from the conceptual mind, that would be the real awareness, the true
insight, the right knowledge.
If we can wake up to the reality, we will see the ultimate truth, which is our true
suchness.
Right knowledge.
When the name and the appearances are put away, the discrimination will cease.
That which is remained is the Buddha nature, the nature of all things, ultimate pure reality.
This is the absolute truth.
Only this is real.
When you reach here, you also let go of the idea of suchness, because all names and all
labels are just concepts.
We let it go as well.
These five dharmas consist of all things.
Now we explain them in terms of the three natures and eight consciousnesses.
The name and appearances are called the other dependent nature.
How do they come about?
They are other dependent, dependent on cause and effect.
Without cause and effect, you will have no name or appearances.
This cause and effect is actually from our own alaya consciousness.
We have this big storehouse that stores all our karmic seeds from many, many, many prior
lifetimes.
All our thoughts, all our actions, they are seeds.
Or we call it habit energy or impression.
When the conditions are right, they will ripen into what we call the phenomenon world.
So everything you see in the phenomenon world, they are not as real as you think.
They are actually created from our alaya consciousness.
It's like an ever-spanning whirlpool.
It doesn't stop.
It keeps accumulating seeds.
From moment to moment.
And these seeds are developed from the first seven consciousness.
This circle, which is the sixth consciousness, it includes all five consciousnesses before
this.
So our eye consciousness, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind.
That's how we conceptualize, see, and experience the world.
But this is based on the seven consciousnesses.
The seven consciousness, the ego.
We love ourselves so much, we think the alaya consciousness is me.
And we base all our thinking on the smallness.
And whatever we think becomes our action, becomes our words.
We have greed, anger, and ignorance.
And we create killing, stealing, and lust.
All these get stored back into the alaya consciousness.
A seed.
Have been energies.
They were ripened into result.
All these is created by this deluded mind.
This is not our Buddha nature.
This is an ignorantTHIS IS WHEN WE ARE FULL OF THE SELF.
Buddha nature have no self.
This is Buddha nature.
This is our deluded mind.
If you understand it's illusory nature.
No longer attached your outside.
outside world. This laya consciousness itself, when it's purified, it is the
suchness. It is the true reality. Living in the laya, we are living in a dream
state. When someone is yelling at us, we think it's so real, we become very angry.
If we know there is not the person outside of us and not the words and not
ourselves, then we will no longer be angry because we perceive it as real. We
become angry. Or we have to get the Louis Vuitton bag or the Mercedes because we
perceive them as very valuable. If we can only see this is only a life that we
fabricated from our laya consciousness, we will be awakened. All you have to know
is illusory.
Oftentimes, we describe them in terms of these three natures. The nature of all
things, which is dependent on conditions, wandering thoughts, our false
imagination, and the fully accomplished nature is our true suchness. If we always
live in the conceptualized nature, in our conceptualized thinking, we are like
the audience who's watching and completely
absorbed in this movie, thinking it's real. We're caught up in this drama of life.
If we can see it's only made out of cause and condition, we are like the actors. We
know we're making a film. We're only acting right now. That's a higher insight of
wisdom. But if you can become the director, directing your whole life, your emotion, and
realizing that your intention is not constantly
controlled by the ups and downs of the world without the conceptualization, without the
discrimination, then you will realize these two kinds of no self egolessness of persons,
egolessness
of things. Right now, we are ignorant. We think there
is a real permanent me. And we think everything outside of us is really present part of us.
But if you follow my standard, I'm gonna let you in on this. I'm gonna explain
about me first. We can see you. They can see you. I can see you freely. I can also see you.
existing. These two beliefs is hindering us from becoming a Buddha. But when you're awakened,
you will realize there's no such thing as I or ego. It's only a fabrication. There's
no me and there's no things. That's why it's called Yogyakarta, consciousness only. Everything
is only manifestation of our mind. And that is the truth. That is reality. Through meditation,
contemplate on this fact. One day you will come to this awakening that everything is
only a dream. When you have this kind of insight, you can be a true Bodhisattva. You live this
life not attached to anyone.
But help everyone to become enlightened. That's someone who is awakened. This is when we reach
the top of the mountain. Even though it's treacherous and difficult, we will get there
eventually. The Sutra keeps saying everything is unborn. Unborn means there's no actual
rising or ceasing or abiding.
When you see the Buddha, you will be enlightened. When you see the Buddha, you will be enlightened.
It is really cardboarded. You are the DISCOVERY OF THE DEVрей, the threefold meaning
of all existence in this world. You don't need
to want anything. You only need the real truth. You will no longer need the LV bag.
You will no longer need Mercedes to make you Happy. They are only the condition arising.
You will have a lot of knowledge, and you will not be offended when other people are
passing judgement on you or hurting your feelings. It's only your karma coming from your liya
consciousness. Nothing is for real. on your or hurting your feeling. It's only your karma
a dream for you to come to realization and reach this epiphany. That's when we will
become a true enlightened being, back to our original suchness.
Thank you very much for listening. Amida Pa.