Today's topic is Mind Only Contemplation.
This is verses from Mahayana Sangreya by Bodhisattva Asanga.
We want to untie our minds from impediments.
This involves deep insight meditation such as this mind only meditation.
So let's look at this verse.
The concentrated Bodhisattva sees that the images are mind only.
This concentrated Bodhisattva which is someone who has deep meditation absorption.
Someone who is able to see the truth that everything is only false images created by this mind.
In this structure, Bodhisattva Asanga delved deep into our alaya consciousness.
This big storehouse contains all our karmic seeds.
When the conditions are right, it will ripen into results.
That's all the phenomenons of this world.
So everything is only creation by our mind.
The three realms is created by our minds.
My ray Dharma originates from this mind.
All circumstances are only perceptions from our mind.
Nothing is real.
It's only phantasm and magical delusion.
We often use the metaphor mistaken a rope for a snake in the darkness.
When we see the snake and we are afraid, that's our false imagination.
A Bodhisattva in deep consciousness.
They will not see the snake.
They will see it's only a rope.
Us mundane, we might be in fear, not knowing that this snake never really existed.
This snake can be our poverty, our sickness, our afflictions, a concentrated Bodhisattva.
He rejects the notion of the snake, knowing it's only a false image created by our consciousness.
The notion of the snake is not real.
The notion of things have been expelled.
He sees that only his mind exists.
We are seeing the false image.
It's only a magical delusion, a trick of the mind.
In the Consciousness Only School of Buddhism, we categorize everything in the Dharma world
as the three natures.
One is the fully conceptualized nature.
That's all our deluded thinking.
Our wandering thoughts.
Second is the other-dependent nature.
That's all the karma that we are experiencing in our lives right now.
The third is the fully accomplished nature.
That's our true suchness.
The snake that we think exists is the fully conceptualized nature.
If we can see that it's only a rope, that's the other-dependent nature.
On another level.
If we can see.
That the rope is made out of different kind of thread, that's seeing the fully accomplished
nature.
The other example that we use is a dream.
The plot in the dream is the other-dependent nature.
We are living the dream itself.
That's the fully conceptualized nature.
If we know it's only a dream, then that's the fully accomplished nature.
It all depends on our wisdom.
If we can see that the world is only a magical delusion, why should we be worried and caught
up with everything that's going on in the world?
Master Wang Qing, he was out of the solitude, up in the cave of the mountain.
He came back to the temple, often just sat in the main hall and meditated.
One day, all the donation in the donation box disappeared.
Everybody was gone.
Everybody thought he had stolen all the donation, but he was not moved at all by this circumstance.
This has no bearing on his emotions.
After a couple of weeks, people at the temple announced that they actually hid the money
just to test the old monk's cultivation.
Everybody started praising him.
Again, Master Wang Qing was not moved by this circumstance.
Master Wang Qing was not moved by this circumstance.
He added here, in his ???
In his book, in the book of
Master Wang Qing, he said this,
This requires knowing that everything is made from the mind only and everything you see doesn't
really exist.
This required knowing that everything is made from the mind only and everything you see
doesn't really exist.
Now, let's look at the third line.
Abiding, thus, in the inner mind.
He knows that the object of perception does not exist.
Then, when the subject of perception is in the inner mind, he knows that the object of
perception does not exist.
perception as well does not exist. Later, he contacts the emptiness of non-perception.
There are three things here. One is the object of perception. Two is the subject of perception.
The third is the emptiness of non-perception. Our mind works in subject and object. We have
object of perception such as the sixth sense objects of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch,
and the Dharma. That's the object of our perception. The subject of perception is our sixth sense
consciousness, our eye consciousness, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind. The mind always
works in subject and object.
Subjects touch and objects touch. So our mind always works in subject and object. Our
an object. That's how we think and have deluded thinking. But a bodhisattva, they dwell in
their inner mind. They know the emptiness of all things and they also know the object
of perception and the subject of perception are all created by the mind. None of them
really exists. He investigates even further to get to this reality. When we reach this
level, at the end, we will see the emptiness of non-perception. The idea of non-perception
or nothing existing also is expelled at the end. Therefore, there is no existence or non-existence.
That's the original question.
The essence of our mind is unfold. That's our true suchness. We call it the fully accomplished
nature. As you can see, this mind-only meditation is in many steps of letting go. Seeing that
all images are mind-only, seeing the object of perception does not exist, the subject
of perception does not exist, theReally. At the end, the emptiness of non-perception
doesn't exist either. At the end, that's when we see the true.
The intention of this insight meditation involves four investigations and four precise
knowledges. The four investigations is to delve deep into all these four concepts. The
First is the name of all things. We give everything a name such as fire. Fire is a name. It's
also a thing. It has meaning. It has a self-nature. It's heat. It has temperature. And it has
characteristics. We use it to burn. We need to investigate into these four qualities.
The name, the thing, the self-nature, the characteristics. When you delve deep into
it, then you will realize they're non-existent. Nothing really existed in the first place.
It's all concept of the mind. For example, anger. We give it a name called anger. It
is a thing. It is an emotion. It is an affliction. Then it has self-nature. The thing is a thing.
The thing is a thing. The thing is a thing. The thing is a thing. The thing is a thing.
The self-nature of anger is suffering. Because we sense suffering, we become upset. Its characteristics
destroys our peace of mind. It destroys all our goodness. That's the meaning of anger.
But when you delve deep into it, you will realize anger never really existed. And you
can delve even further to see the meaning of anger.
We believe that this anger is only a concept of the mind. It has no real rising or ceasing.
We can investigate. Before the anger ever existed, there was nothing. Because of a situation,
we want to get angry. There was nothing either. And right now, when I'm angry, there's
also nothing to be found.
At the end, this affliction called anger never really rises. Therefore, letting it go is
not a problem at all. Because it's only a concept of the mind.
Investigate everything in this matter until you are very firm.
The first two lines is when we have the four investigations.
The first two lines is when we are so sure there's nonexistence about these four things,
that we don't know the true meaning of anger.
It's called the four precise knowledges.
When we are so sure, we have this deep concentration. Concentrate on the fact that it is merely
the mind only. Nothing really existed. We want to gain this true wisdom and really see
through things.
The four investigations.
The four precise knowledges.
precise knowledges they are exactly the same thing it just one goes into a
deeper level that is all that is what we call meditative absorption the further
you go down the further you let go the further you see the emptiness of all
things and the emptiness of the mind you will see the truth so at the end you
will see that the mind doesn't exist either because the mind cannot see the
mind just like a knife cannot cut itself eyes cannot see the eyes itself at the
end you will let go the object and the subject the mind itself doesn't exist
that's why it's the emptiness of non-perception that's when we see the
real truth
so if we can see this we will not be concerned so much about what's going on
in the world really let go of our attachments that's when our bodhisattvas
practice the six pyramidas in real life they have no attachment to
the person that they're giving to to the things they're giving and to themselves
identify as a giver when they are practicing
patience, they don't have to say I'm being patient or I'm having forbearance because
they don't even have this concept of tolerance because all things they are fabrication of
the mind. That's when Bodhisattva, their mind is undivided and without perplexity.
That's what we call deep meditative absorption. Go through these steps when we chant the name
Amitabha. This will be true recitation of the Buddha's name. Take care of business and
let it go. We don't keep anything in our mind, then we can chant Buddha's name single-mindedly.
At the end of our lives, we can let go of all attachment even to our family and loved
ones without any obstacles. Going to the Western Pure Land, that's when we can really
be out of the Sixth Round of Incarnation. Don't let everything be hanged up in your
mind. It does cause vexation for yourself. We do not want to be under the whims of others.
Discard all distinction between good and bad. That's what we call mindlessness. It's not
we are indifferent. It means we are letting go all our senses of discrimination. This
is called mindlessness.
This is called true samadhi. It's called the mind-only contemplation in everyday life.
Walking, standing, eating, sleeping, anything we do, we must know that it's all mind-only.
That way, the external circumstances will have no bearing on your emotion or your mind.
So that's the class for today. Thank you for listening. Amitabha.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community