Today's topic is the Amitabha Sutra.
We might recite the sutra every day, but what does it really mean to us?
In this class, we will use OE Master's commentary of Amitabha Sutra to learn about the meaning of this sutra.
This sutra talks about the three pillars of Pure Land Buddhism of faith, vow, and practice.
In the beginning, it gives a full-scale description of the wonders of the Pure Land to arouse our faith to really believe in the existence of this land.
And it tells us to make real vows of wanting to take rebirth there.
And it teaches us how to practice and recite Amitabha Buddha's name in order to reach our goal of rebirth.
Now let's look at faith.
First, we learn about all the wonders of the Pure Land, such as the jewel pond, the water of eight merits, the ground that's made out of pure gold, and the birds that are singing the Dharma.
How did all these come about?
So it says four times in the sutra that this land of ultimate bliss is complete with all these adornments and virtues.
The OE Master's commentary, it says,
With his great vows, Amitabha creates the cause of the world.
He creates the causal basis for sentient beings to multiply their good roots.
With his great deeds, he creates the conditions for sentient beings to increase their merits and virtues.
There are a couple of factors here.
It says in the sutra that we cannot have minor good roots, merits, and virtues, and cause and conditions to go to the Pure Land.
So we need to have ample of these in order to take rebirth.
Because these are the ingredients that make up the Pure Land.
It's actually a joint effort between Amidabha and us.
So Amidabha is helping us with his 48 great vows and his great deeds of six paramitas.
He creates the cause and the conditions when we recite His name and multiply our guru's, which is our Bodhi mind, Frankfurtest.
effort between Amitabha and us. So Amitabha is helping us with his 48 great vows and his
great deeds of six pyramidas. He creates the cause and the condition when we recite his
name and multiplies our gurus, which is our bodhi mind and increase all our merits and
virtues. That's how the Pure Land is constructed. There are three inconceivable powers here.
First is the power of Amitabha, his great vows and great deeds. Number two is the power
of the Amitabha Buddha's name. And when we recite it, that's how the power is transmitted
to us. And the third power is us. When we recite, it creates gurus and merits and virtue
in our own mind.
That's how the Pure Land is constructed. There are three inconceivable powers here.
That is how the Pure Land is produced. So we need to have faith in the three inconceivable
powers. There is a Russian boy. He's 15 years old, has no hands, but he really wanted to
play the piano. He doesn't know how to read music. He just listened to the sound and tried
to imitate. And he really did it because he believed that he can play the piano. So if
you have faith, you can accomplish everything.
If you believe in the three incredible powers, then chanting Amitabha Buddha's name is really
creating the Pure Land for us.
Number two, vow. There are three major benefits that motivate us to make vow to go to the
Pure Land. Number one is everyone that is reborn there, we immediately reach the level
of avivartika, which means three non-retrogression. Number one, we will never retrogress in our
practice of adhat, who is a saint that is out of reincarnation forever. Number two,
we will never retrogress in our bodhisattva practice. No matter what happens, we will
always have our compassion of wanting to save all sentient beings. Number three, we will
never retrogress in our mindfulness. We will always have the wisdom of the Buddha as our
mind. Once we get there, we immediately achieve these three non-retrogression. So that's the
first major benefit.
Number two, we will be someone who only has one more lifetime to go before Buddhahood.
We will be like Maitreya Bodhisattva, the successor of Shakyamuni Buddha. There's only
one Buddha in every world. When we get to the Pure Land, we are guaranteed to be a Buddha
elect.
Number three, we will be together with all these beings of superior goodness. All the
ordinary people are with the holy Buddha.
The saints with their desires extinguished, we will be with them. Over here, it's really
hard to find a temple or a teacher who really knows exactly what you need. But over there,
they are all bodhisattva who knows exactly what you need to practice. We will work to
end our ignorance and our delusion and reach wondrous enlightenment together. With these
three major benefits, we want to make real vow to be reborn there.
In summary, making vows with deep faith is precisely the mind of supreme enlightenment.
Our Pure Land vow and our Pure Land faith is precisely our Bodhi mind that will bring
us into Buddhahood. So going to the Pure Land means reaching Buddhahood. Shen Zhang, master
of the Tang Dynasty, he really wanted to learn more Buddhism that was not in China at the
time.
He took a pilgrimage from China all the way to India. He experienced insurmountable obstacles.
Many times there was not a bird in the sky and not an animal on the ground. It was him
and the desert. He kept reciting the Heart Sutra. He went through all the obstacles,
reached India and brought back the Yogacara Buddhism, which is the conscious-only school
of Buddhism.
He was the first Chinese master of Buddhism. He was the first Chinese master of Buddhism.
He was the first Chinese master of the school of Yogacara. If he can do that, we can chant
Amitabha and go to the Pure Land. It's the same Bodhi resolve, the same Bodhi mind that
will make us become a Buddha.
Number three, practice. We need to recite Amitabha, Buddha's name, wholeheartedly.
There are two ways to recite the Amitabha's name. Number one is on the phenomenal level.
Just like a child relies on his mother, he has no doubt that this person with the smell
will take care of him wholeheartedly and he's in no danger. So we rely on Amitabha. That
is on the phenomenal level.
Number two is the level of inner truth. To know that Amitabha is in our mind. When we
produce the Buddha's image, our mind is in the Buddha's image. When we produce the Buddha's
image, our mind is in the Buddha's image.
When we produce the Buddha's image, our mind is in the Buddha's image. When we produce the
Buddha's image, our mind is in the Buddha's image. When we produce the Buddha's image,
our mind is in the Buddha's image. When we produce the Buddha's image, our mind is in
the Buddha's image. When we produce the Buddha's image, our mind is in Amitabha.
Our mind is in the Buddha's image, Amitabha is in the Buddha's image, Amitabha is my
mind.
Amitabha also settled down. When we practice Amitabha, Buddha's name is finally also
in the Buddha's image. When we practice the Dok
Ik.
merit vicariously become yours. Every time you make the sound Amitabha, Amitabha is right
in front of you. His light is glowing and you are glowing in his golden light. He merges
with you. You are together as one. Your Buddha nature emerges. That's the amazing experience
of every one of your recitations. So one recitation is one inconceivableness. The key is to chant
Amitabha single-mindedly without confusion. Chant single-mindedly, wholeheartedly, without
confusion. We are being confused by our daily experiences. For example, if we have a bad
day at work, we might just forget about chanting.
All the unpleasant things that we do, we forget about chanting. All the unpleasant
things that we do, we forget about chanting. All the unpleasant things that we do, we forget
about chanting. All the unpleasant experiences in life, they lose us, clouds us, and confuse
us. And we forget about our goal and our mission of becoming a Buddha. Don't let anything get
you off track. Go to the Pure Land. Monitor your faith and vow constantly. So single-mindedness
means determination of wanting to become a Buddha. So lastly I would like to share a
story. In 1933, I was in the United States.
There was a Mr. Cheng, he was a Pure Land practitioner.
He wanted to devote all his time in his practice, so he gave the family business to the younger
brother.
He just focused on chanting.
He learned how to expound the Amitabha Sutra.
Six years later, one day after he finished expounding the Amitabha Sutra, there was only
five, six people left.
He said to his friend, please rent me a room, I'm leaving now.
Seriously?
His friend asked, if you're leaving, why do you need to rent a room?
He said, I'm going to Amitabha's Pure Land.
I don't want to die in someone's place, so please rent me a place.
His friend said, why don't you just come to my house and we will gather all the practitioners.
They can watch you and see how you go to the Pure Land.
They all went to this friend's house.
He just sat there in the full lotus position.
People asked him, do you want to say something before you leave?
He said, no.
Just watch me come and go freely.
Just witness it and believe in it.
And he sat there with a smile on his face for less than 15 minutes.
He passed and went to the Pure Land.
His younger brother, who didn't believe in him, after he witnessed it, he wanted to learn
from him.
After three years, that also happened to his younger brother.
He also knew ahead of time his date and time of his rebirth.
Everyone can do it.
Have these three years.
Three pillars of faith, vow, and practice.
When you recite the Amitabha Sutra, know what it means.
It's really the Pure Land and this is your lifetime goal.
Today is New Year's Eve.
Hope everybody make the New Year resolution using this lifetime to chant Amitabha, to
go to the Western Pure Land and reach Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Happy New Year's.
Amitabha.
Satsang with Mooji