Today we are going to talk about the ultimate and conventional truth.
So this follows the class from last week.
There are two kinds of truth that we need to know.
One is called the ultimate truth.
The ultimate truth is the truth of emptiness.
Everything happens is forever changing.
It doesn't have an inherent existence.
So we call it emptiness.
We should not attach ourselves to things that are forever changing
because in its essence, it's empty.
When you are able to understand this truth, you become awakened.
And the second truth is called conventional truth.
Even though everything is empty in its essence,
it has its forms and what it appears.
So we still follow life and do the best that we can
but not be caught up with the world.
If you balance the two kinds of truth, it's called the middle way.
When you balance the two truths.
Today we are going to talk about the sixth patriarch of the Zen Buddhism.
His name is Hui Nen.
When he was really young, his father passed away.
So he had to chop wood for a living.
Never went to school, so he's illiterate.
One day he was chopping wood and then he brought it to a hotel.
He noticed someone was reciting the Diamond Sutra.
He asked the person, where did you get the sutra?
How can I find someone who teaches me?
He said, oh, you just go to the Huangmei Mountain.
The fifth patriarch of the Zen Buddhism is there teaching right now.
Hui Nen decided to leave his home.
He walked for 30 days.
Finally, he gets there.
The fifth patriarch Hong Ren asked him, who are you?
Why are you here?
He says, my name is Hui Nen.
I'm from the South.
I'm here because I want to be a Buddha.
And then he said, you are just a barbarian from the South
and you want to be a Buddha?
He was looking down on him and he said,
people might be from South or North,
but the Buddha nature
has no South or North.
I can be a Buddha.
So he was very, very confident in his own nature.
The fifth patriarch said, just go to the kitchen and pound rice.
So he ordered him to go to the kitchen and work.
He worked in the kitchen for eight months.
One day the fifth patriarch gathered his disciples and said,
I'm going to die soon.
So I want to pass my patriarchship to someone who's enlightened.
So I'm going to have you guys write a poem.
Whoever writes the best poem that shows that you're enlightened,
I will give my robe to the person.
You'll be the next patriarch.
So everybody's like, we don't need to write
because the head monk in the temple,
he is the best student.
I'm sure he's going to write the best poem.
Everybody points to Sen Xiu.
But Sen Xiu, he's very nervous at this point.
He said, everybody thinks I'm going to be the best one.
What if I'm not enlightened?
What will people think of me?
He couldn't sleep.
But finally, he wrote this poem.
Body is the Bodhi tree.
Mind is like a bright mirror on a stand.
Diligently wipe it all the time and allow no dust to cling.
Okay, so what does that mean?
The body is the Bodhi tree.
So we cultivate with our body to become a Bodhi tree
because Buddha was enlightened under the Bodhi tree.
So we have this metaphor saying
our body is like the Bodhi tree of cultivation.
We use the body to cultivate.
And the mind is like a bright mirror.
We often describe our Buddha nature like clean mirror.
So what you have to do is diligently wipe it all the time
and allow no dust to cling.
So you just don't want any dust.
You want to make sure you have no anger,
no greediness, ignorance.
You clean yourself every day.
So that's his poem.
So do you think that's enlightenment?
Hui Neng was in the kitchen
and he heard someone reciting this poem.
He said, that person is not enlightened.
I have a better poem.
So one bystander showed him to the corridor
where this was written.
So he asked someone to write another poem for him.
And this is what he wrote.
Originally Bodhi is not a tree
nor does the bright mirror have a stand.
Originally there's not even a tree.
So where is the thing?
So where is the dust to cling?
These two poems are the opposite.
First, the body is a Bodhi tree.
Originally Bodhi is not a tree.
What does that mean?
Enlightenment or Buddha nature,
does it have a form?
No.
It's formless.
It's nothing physical.
Nor does the bright mirror have a stand.
Buddha nature is not in the form of a mirror
or anything that you think is great or clean.
Because originally there's not even a thing.
This is the concept of the ultimate truth.
Everything is empty in its essence.
When you cling to something,
that's no longer your Buddha nature.
So where is the dust to cling?
There's no mirror and it's not dirty.
There's no dirt.
You are clean and pure as it is.
There's nothing to cling.
You are perfect as it is.
You just have to let go of your attachment
and you'll be there.
The 5th Patriarch, he realized
Hui Nung is enlightened
and then he passed the robe to him.
But everybody was jealous of him.
So he disguised himself as a hunter
in the hunting group for 16 years
before he started teaching the Dharma of Zen Buddhism.
That's the legend of Hui Nung.
So why do we discuss these two poems?
Just to let you understand
what's the ultimate truth
and what's the conventional truth.
Conventional truth is what you see.
A lot of us are very caught up
with the conventional truth,
what appears on the outside.
We might be nervous.
Oh, I have to be a good mom.
I have to do my job well.
We are like sensual.
Caught up in the conventional world.
I have to be great at this and that.
If I don't do well,
what are people going to think of me?
But if you're really, really awakened,
you don't have to worry about all that.
You can work hard but no stress.
Why?
Because everything is empty in its essence.
When you find out the emptiness,
you feel liberated
because you have no more worries.
Life, the result is empty.
At the end, there's nothing for you to attach to.
When you come to that sense of enlightenment,
understanding the ultimate truth,
we will reach our Buddhahood.
Next time, we're going to talk more
about these two truths in another way.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.