Today we are going to talk about awakening.
We live our lives not awakened.
We are in a dream state unless we awaken our true self.
There are three truths that we need to know in order to be awakened.
And this truth is in this little quote that we have up here.
The dharmas arise from conditions.
I affirm that they are empty.
They are conventional but yet indicate the meaning of the middle way.
There are three truths that we need to know in order to be awakened.
The first is called emptiness.
The second truth is called conventional truth and the third truth is called the middle way
truth.
What does it mean?
How does it apply to our lives?
For dharmas arising from conditions, I affirm that they are empty.
Dharma in Buddhism, we call everything, no matter it's a tree or a mountain or a thought,
we call it the dharma.
Everything is a dharma.
Dharma arises from the conditions.
For example, this pen, you see it here today, it has many, many different conditions.
Many factors bring this pen here for us to see.
For example, I have to buy it from Walmart for it to get here.
They have to have factories, they have to make it.
It's got to have plastics, it's got to have machines to make it and then I buy them and
it gets here.
So there are many, many different conditions.
These conditions are forever changing.
Nothing is for you to control.
Nothing has its own essence that's without conditions from all the different environments
and factors.
That's why I affirm you that they are empty.
Empty doesn't mean they don't exist.
It means they're forever changing because they're based on conditions.
That includes my body.
I am on this earth right now.
But one day, I'm going to die.
The condition is going to change.
I'm going to be sick.
I'm going to get old and I'm going to die.
So conditions are forever changing.
It's not permanent.
If it's not permanent, we should not be attached to it.
If you're attached to it, you will have suffering.
You will be sad.
When you're sick, you die, you're sad.
But if I accept, I accept everything is forever changing.
When it changes, I can accept.
I will no longer be upset.
So this actually means empty of the self.
So when we say empty, it's not for you to forget about life and don't want to live.
It's for you to know that everything is forever changing.
So I accept and I let go of the idea of a permanent self because we are very caught
up in the idea of me.
This body is me with my life and my car and my mom.
Everything is mine.
But if you know that everything is mine, you can accept it.
You can accept it.
If you know that everything that you think is mine is forever changing, nothing is you.
Nothing is mine.
There's a girl, first time she got her salary.
So she bought a hat for herself and she's so happy.
She went home hoping that her mom would praise her about her beautiful new hat.
But her mom was cooking dinner and didn't see her hat.
So she was really sad.
During dinner, her mom was like, what's wrong with you today?
Well, how come you're not happy?
And she said, I bought a new hat.
I bought a new hat.
I bought this hat with my first paycheck, and you didn't even notice.
And you know what the mom said?
Mom said, I got a perm today.
Did you notice?
So everybody is living in your own ego.
It's not a real me.
You think you're the center of the universe?
No.
We are actually empty in its essence.
So let go of the idea.
Notice me.
I'm the center of everything because that's not the truth.
The truth is we are empty in essence.
Except that fact that is called the first real awakening.
The second awakening is if they're empty, they will also be conventional.
Conventional means something that you can see.
Even though it's empty in its essence.
But it has its forms.
I have this body.
If it's empty, do I need to eat?
I still need to eat.
Even though in its essence, it's empty.
Do I still need money to live?
I still need money to live.
So even though it's empty, but I know I have to live this life with the best I can be.
I still want to make the best out of this life.
Even though it's empty in essence, I still make it perfect.
I still want to live a great life.
want to live a great life this is to let go this is to embrace life to be
inspired by life to live a beautiful life it's like playing a movie your life
is like a movie do you want to play a good movie or you want to play a movie
that nobody wants to see then you want to play the great movie for yourself
before the day you die you gotta have no regrets and live every day to the
fullest that's the conventional wisdom so inspire someone with your life
there's a little boy he's very very poor he only has a pair of flip-flops
he went to the train station one day and he saw this other boy he's very rich and
he has a pair of beautiful leather shoes so the poor boy is looking at that
beautiful leather shoes the rich boy and his dad got on the train it was really
crowded some people squished them and one of the
leather shoes was this one one of the leather shoes was a pair of flip-flops
shoes fell off on the train station the poor boy sighed he tried to help him so he tried to run
run run and catch the train and let him have the shoe so he tried to run but his flip-flop is
already like broken so he cannot run very fast and finally he couldn't run anymore so he threw
the shoes hoping he would catch it but it bounced off and still got on the train station so the boy
on the train saw it and he saw that boy had no shoes he threw his one shoes down so the poor boy
will have a pair so we should all live our life to help others to inspire others with your own
existence no matter who you are what your present situation is you can be someone great in this
conventional life to make inspirational changes for other people so that's the second awakening
the second awakening is the second awakening the second awakening is the second awakening
the third awakening is if it's empty and it has conventional truth it indicates the meaning of
the middle way the middle way says we want to balance the emptiness and the conventional way
the emptiness is to let go let go of the ego
don't say notice me love others and let go of the idea of self because our self
is empty but embrace life conventional truth means be the best you can be like be
inspiring to others live life to the fullest so at the end you have no regret and the middle way says
let go of the ego but be the best that you can be so it's a balance of the two when you can do that
you will have a wonderful life you have no longer any problems when you stay at home
and meditate by yourself you are fine you are at peace when you're with a lot of people
enjoying the party you are the best you can be no matter where you are or who you're with you are
free of any attachment but you are the best that you can be when you can reach this level you reach
the true enlightenment at this level we become a real buddha and that's what we call the true and
full enlightenment now it's new year time so hopefully this lesson will help you let go of
the self but be the best you can be and change your life so at the end we have no more regrets
okay so that's it for today thank you for listening and i hope you enjoyed this video
thank you for watching and i will see you in the next video bye
you