Today we are going to talk about Buddha recitation.
Recitation means being mindful, mindful of the Buddha day by day,
having Amitabha in our mind, be awakened and return to our original faith like Amitabha.
We will use verses from Zhongfeng Master's Thrice Yearning Chanting Service to talk about Buddha recitation.
Let's look at the first verse.
Buddha is in our mind.
There are three kinds of mind.
One is the mind or the heart in our body, the organ.
It is given to us by our parents through birth.
This is not our true mind.
The second mind is the mind that comprehends and reacts to different situations.
That is our deluded mind.
Our consciousness is full of the self and the ego, so it is also not our pure mind.
The third mind is the mind of truth that is eternal and constant.
This is our true mind.
This mind does not gain anything when we reach Buddhahood,
and it does not lose anything when we remain in the six realms of reincarnation.
It is the same for mortals and saints.
By concentrating our mind when chanting,
the virtues and merits of Buddha will reflect upon us.
For Buddha, he reached enlightenment through realization of this true mind.
When we have this true mind,
we no longer create false imagery and attachments which causes suffering and pain.
When we chant the name Amitabha,
it is to leave the deluded mind and return to our pure mind.
That is perfect dharma.
We are perfectly endowed with all the virtues and merits of the Buddha.
Recitation of Amitabha Buddha's name is how we realize our self nature.
When our mind is annihilated,
our own intrinsic Buddha nature will appear.
By then, there is no Buddha since we become one ourselves.
When our mind is annihilated,
this is the deluded mind.
It creates false imagery.
We become attached to them.
That's what's creating the samsara.
We should know that this life is like the images in the mirror.
It's only a false reflection.
The mirror itself should not be moved by the imagery.
Mortals and mundane don't understand.
Just like we see in the TV screen there is soap opera.
We know the soap opera is fake,
but we don't know that our own life right now is also like a show that's in the TV screen.
Buddha, on the other hand,
he realized that everything is illusory.
He is not attached to appearances.
He remains calm and unruffled.
We must realize that Buddha is all sentient beings
and all sentient beings are Buddha.
Apart from our mind, there is no Buddha or beings.
The only difference between Buddha and sentient beings is
one is awakened and one is confused.
Buddha only sees the eternal.
In the temporary existence,
the human beings only sees the temporary existence in the eternal of life.
That's the difference.
When we chant Amitabha,
it becomes second nature.
Then there is not the subject of the chanting mind
or the object of the name Amitabha.
There is not the attaining or the attainable.
Both are unattainable and without permanent substance.
We let go of this attachment to even the Dharma.
That's when we realize our self-nature.
With closest examination of ourselves,
once again, we will realize the difference.
The only difference between Buddha and beings
is one is enlightened and one is confused.
That's why Yongjia Master says,
In our dreams, we see the six realms of reincarnation.
But when we are realized,
we can no longer see the six realms of reincarnation.
In the Saha world,
we probably heard of the story of Uddhara Master of the Tang Dynasty.
Because of his virtues and cultivation,
he was honored as the national master.
He was given a throne made out of sandalwood
by the emperor at that time.
Because of this,
he unknowingly gave rise to arrogance and vanity.
Over time, a human face ulcer grew on his knee.
The pain is unbearable.
That's when he remembered,
when he was a novice,
there was an old monk.
His whole body was filled with foul-smelling ulcers.
No one dared to go near him.
But young Uddhara, out of great compassion,
took care of the old monk until he recovered.
So the old monk told him,
Young man, you will have great achievements this lifetime,
but you will also face great obstacles.
When you face trouble that you cannot overcome,
come see me in Jiu Long Mountain in Sichuan.
When you see the twin pine trees, you have arrived.
Uddhara decided to go to the old monk and ask him for help.
When he arrived, it was already evening time.
The attendant of the old monk already knew that he was coming.
He told him,
In the morning, we will wash away your ulcer with the spring water.
So in the morning, the attendant took him to the spring water.
Before he started washing,
the ulcer started speaking.
He said,
Wait a minute.
Many lifetimes ago, you were Yuan Ang.
I was Cao Cuo.
You wronged me.
You framed me.
So the emperor ordered to kill me.
I suffered a horrific death,
and I swore to revenge.
But for ten lifetimes,
you were always a virtuous monk that holds precepts.
So I could not get to you.
But now with your thought of vanity and arrogance,
I was able to take revenge.
Now with the spring water of the enlightened Kanaka,
our feud has ended.
I will no longer take any revenge.
The bad blood has ended.
Wu Da Master was in great shock.
He sprayed spring water on the ulcer.
It was very painful.
He fainted.
When he woke up,
the ulcer was gone.
The realized Wu Da Master took care of the old monk out of great compassion.
And the monk that gave rise to vanity
and arrogance is also him.
The only difference is in one thought,
awakened or confused.
In this stage,
our mind will illuminate as the different colored lotuses.
When we are awakened,
we will have the lotus flowers of four different colors
of red, white, blue, and yellow.
Lotus flower symbolizes perfect purity.
The perfect purity and goodness
of our true mind.
We often say Chen Amitabha
until the flower flourishes
and Buddha comes into view.
This Buddha is not Amitabha.
It's the Buddha within yourself.
When we are perfectly pure without vexation,
then you will see the Buddha
that is your own true nature.
Now let's look at the second verse
that has more description of this enlightened mind.
The grand circular mirror of truth
like the true mind has no dust.
that's when our eighth consciousness
transforms into the great perfect mirror wisdom.
The alaya consciousness is erased clean.
There's no more karmic seeds,
only perfect purity and wisdom.
That's why it says there's no more dust.
The green lotus bud bears the birth of a Buddha.
The lotus flower arrives
from our mind.
When we Chen Amitabha in this world right now,
there is a lotus bud growing
in the pond of the Western Pure Land.
The color, radiance, and size of the flower
all depend on our diligence.
If we're lazy, the flower will wither.
If we are very diligent,
have firm faith, resolve vows,
and enthusiastic practice,
then our flower will get bigger and brighter.
It's all depending on our mind.
We are diligent.
We need to protect this lotus
like we protect the infant in the mother's womb.
We do not want a miscarriage.
We should practice diligently
without giving rise to evil thoughts.
Always have perfectly pure and kind heart.
Look far away from the bottom of the pond
spread with golden sand.
The bright lights from the seven jewels
shine from the jade pagoda.
This is talking about the living situation.
In the Western Pure Land,
which is symbolic of the beauty of our true nature,
the true mind.
Over here on this earth,
the bottom of the pond is full of mud.
But over there is full of golden sand.
The buildings in our world
is made out of brick stones and concrete.
Over there is made out of seven jewels,
precious stones that are soft,
fragrant, and illuminating.
All the wondrous,
the wondrous aspect of the Pure Land really exists.
They are all symbolic of our true nature.
That's why we say,
Pure Mind,
Pure Land.
Or you can say,
Enlightened Mind,
Enlightened Land.
It's all up to our mind,
right here,
right now.
This lifetime,
we have the inconceivable,
rare opportunity to become a Buddha.
We should really let go of all the worries
and affliction.
See,
through the illusion of all appearances,
chant Amitabha single-mindedly.
True Buddha recitation means
mindful of our own Buddha nature,
our true mind.
That is true recitation.
Always be aware that right here,
right now,
you are with your true mind
and there's nothing else that's more important
than be in the present moment
chanting Amitabha
and reciting in your true nature.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.