Today we are going to talk about 37 Factors of Enlightenment.
This is the jewel of cultivation in Buddhism.
No matter if you are a Chen Buddhist, a Pure Land practitioner,
or you study Mahayana Buddhism or Theravada Buddhism,
we all have to learn the 37 Factors of Enlightenment.
It might sound like a lot, but it's actually lots of repeats and only 7 categories.
Four Mindfulness, Four Right Efforts, Four Miraculous Feats, Five Faculties, Five Powers,
Seven Elements of Enlightenment, and Eightfold Path.
Let's first talk about the Four Mindfulness.
Number one, be mindful of our body.
Especially young people, we are very attached to our sensual desire,
contemplate on the impurity of our body and the body of others.
Everything from our body is filthy inside.
Do not be attached to our sensual desires.
Number two is mindful of our feelings.
Older people are more attached to their feelings,
so do not say anything wrong to old people, they remember forever.
But Buddha tells us all feelings end up to be suffering,
because pleasant feeling, when it subsides, it becomes unsatisfying.
It becomes unsatisfactory and becomes pain.
So do not be attached to our feelings.
Number three is mindful of our mind.
Intellectuals and scholars, we are attached to our mind,
what we think is right, and we are always full of our opinions.
Buddha says to contemplate on the impermanence of our mind.
All our thoughts are constantly changing from when we're young to when we're old.
Don't rely on your thoughts.
Our thoughts go through stages.
Rising, abiding, changing, and ceasing.
So nothing is permanent.
Don't rely on your thoughts.
Number four is phenomena.
Everything other than body, feeling, and mind, we call it phenomena.
Contemplate on non-self of all phenomena.
There's not a permanent, independent, controlling self that is experiencing the world,
like what we're thinking.
So our ego and our identity of the self
is actually an illusion.
That's why we have all the problems and all the emotional suffering
because we have a strong identity that we think is the true self.
If you can realize that there is actually no self,
then you will be liberated and be free from suffering.
So contemplate on the body, feeling, mind, and phenomena.
This is a cultivation of great wisdom.
Next, we have four right efforts.
As a Buddhist, our duty is to make ourselves improve spiritually
and cultivate our virtues and ethics.
Number one, non-virtue arises.
We need to get rid of it right away.
Non-virtues include negative emotions,
such as fear or anxiety or bitterness.
Realize they are non-virtues.
Get rid of them immediately
and go back to our positive, happy, and pleasant self.
Number two is non-virtue not yet arises.
If you see non-virtue in others,
cutting a line or jumping through loopholes,
we do not want to follow.
Number three is virtue arises.
We want it to maintain and grow.
For example, if we already vowed to be a great bodhisattva
to love and help all sentient beings,
we want that bodhi resolve to grow.
Just like we're rising the bread dough,
we want it to grow bigger and bigger.
Number four, virtue not yet arises.
If there's some good virtue you haven't put into practice,
you want to do it right now.
Maybe talk to that neighbor you never talked to before
or open up to that relative or a friend that did you wrong.
A lot of people think Buddhists are very pessimistic.
Everything's about suffering and pain and letting go.
But actually, we're very proactive in changing our bad ways
and making this a better world.
Then we focus on the four miraculous feats.
This is concentration.
So morality, concentration, and wisdom again.
Miraculous feats focus on concentration.
Number one is resolve.
We need to have strong bodhi resolve.
I want to be awakened.
I want to be a saint.
So I need to work hard in my meditation and my cultivation.
Then you will put in great effort.
Be strong and be consistent.
We say the dripping water can eventually penetrate a rock.
So consistency, we will succeed.
Number three is mindfulness.
Be mindful all the time, sitting, walking, sleeping, eating.
We are always aware of what we are doing and thinking.
Then we will develop the five faculties.
We will develop strong faith in our cultivation,
believe in the Amitabha Buddha,
and know that when we're chanting his name,
we are one with him,
and we're glowing in his light.
We will have strong faith in our Buddha nature.
We can be just like Buddha if we just cultivate.
We believe in karma.
Karma is real.
If I do all that is good,
I will have good karma.
When you have strong faith and confidence,
you will put in great effort.
This effort will be like training for the Olympics,
except this is more important than winning the gold medal.
No matter how much setback,
or how much your leg hurts in the forward position,
you will keep going.
Number three is mindfulness.
We often use the example of hand-hatching eggs.
If you see those hand-hatching eggs,
for 21 days they just sit on their eggs without going anywhere.
They're always mindful of their eggs.
That's how we should be when we're meditating.
Always be mindful like we are sitting on the eggs.
Number four is concentration.
We often use the example of a cat trying to catch a mouse.
If you've seen the cartoon Tom and Jerry,
you will know what I mean.
Tom stands very attentively behind the mouse hole,
waiting for the mouse to come out.
So that's how focused we should be.
Number five, we will have wisdom.
When you have great concentration,
then you will know what we mean by non-self.
You will actually experience the state
of non-self.
The five faculties, we need to balance them.
Balance faith and wisdom.
When the faith is too strong,
we use wisdom to think.
And when our effort is too strong,
we use concentration to calm ourselves down.
So you always want to be in a very balanced state of mindfulness.
With the five faculties,
we will develop five powers.
Now we will actually get rid of our defilements.
Faith will overcome our
doubts.
Effort will overcome our laziness.
Mindfulness will overcome our deluded mind.
Concentration will overcome our scattered mind.
Wisdom will overcome our ignorance.
This is when we actually transform ourselves
from a mundane person to a thing that is awakened.
Then we have the seven elements of enlightenment.
This is meditation.
Number one is mindfulness.
Mindfulness of the present moment
is actually the greatest virtue.
Number two, discernment.
We need to discern what is real and what is fake.
The truth is there is no self.
The me I'm using right now is the fake me.
So we need to discern and know the truth.
Number three is effort.
We need to put in the right effort.
Make sure we don't use defilement.
For example, don't be angry when you're using effort.
Don't say, oh, I'm horrible at this.
I can't do better.
When you have anger, that's not good effort.
Or when you have greediness, you're like,
oh, that person meditated for two hours.
I need to do three hours.
And when you're comparing and greedy,
that is not good effort either.
So don't use defilement to cultivate.
Number four is joy.
We want to have this dharma joy
when we hear of the 37 factor enlightenment.
Doing meditation is like we're seeing Buddha coming alive
and we have this great joy and rapture.
Number five is tranquility.
Tranquility is a great quality we must develop,
especially when we have accidents or we're very sick
or even time of death.
Contemplate on tranquility and relax without any worry or stress.
Number six is concentration.
We want to be able to concentrate no matter what happens.
Even when going through crisis or a lot of obstacles,
still concentrate on the name of the Buddha.
We will make sure that we will be able to chant Buddha's name when we're dying.
Number seven is equanimity.
This is when we're detached, have this neutral feeling, not happy.
We're just neutral, calm, still and composed
when we can reach this balanced state of mind.
This is actually great meditation.
So everything needs to be balanced.
If we are too drowsy,
we use discernment, effort and joy to lift us up.
When we are restless,
we use tranquility, concentration and equanimity to calm us down.
So you always want to bring your state of mind to this perfect balance.
Lastly, we have eightfold path.
Again, it's morality, concentration and wisdom.
Number one is right view.
Right view here, we mean the Four Noble Truths.
Suffering, cause of suffering,
we want to have cessation of suffering.
And how do we practice the path to end suffering?
So everything that you do should correspond with the Four Noble Truths.
Your intention, your thoughts will be based on the Four Noble Truths.
Then your action will follow.
Number three, your speech will follow.
I will make sure I don't curse, gossip, lie
because they are the causes of suffering.
I don't want to do those things.
My action will follow.
I do not steal, have sexual misconduct or kill anything
because those are the causes of suffering that I don't want.
And I will have the right livelihood.
I will not do anything illegal
because those livelihoods will not bring me to cessation of suffering.
And I will make sure I have the right effort,
the Four Right Efforts.
And I will have right mindfulness,
practice the Four Mindfulness.
And I will have right concentration,
practice the Four Miraculous Feats.
So I know these things,
they are the path to end suffering.
So everything you do will follow
based on the Four Noble Truths.
So that's the 37 Factors of Enlightenment.
Our original teacher Shakyamuni Buddha
during his dying day, his last words were
make my teaching your life, rely upon it,
do not depend upon it.
Do not depend on anything else.
Make of yourself a light.
Okay, so make this 37 Factors of Enlightenment your light.
This is what we rely on.
Just depend on this and you will succeed.
Make yourself a light.
You will become enlightened.
Every time I hear this phrase,
I feel very secure, safe and solid in my practice.
Feel like Buddha is with me.
So thank you my dearest teacher,
Shakyamuni Buddha.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.