Subtitles by
One of the 26
Today our class is still on Lao-Fan's Four Lessons.
This is a book from 500 years ago written by Lao-Fan on how to use your own potential to change your destiny.
So the first chapter was about his own life, how he changed himself.
Because he cultivated all that is good and changed all his bad ways.
He had two sons and he was a mayor and then he lived to an old age.
All because he changed his karma.
By karma we mean we do good deeds, we will have good results.
We do bad deeds, we will end up with bad results.
The second chapter was about reforming the bad ways.
So you have to change your bad ways and then do all that is good.
Today we are already on the third chapter.
So this third chapter is about ways to cultivate goodness.
After you change all the faults or the offenses that you have,
now we can really focus on doing all that is good.
A virtuous person creates a prosperous life, naturally, because you reap what you sow.
But you have to differentiate what is good and what is evil.
What is merit and what is offenses.
Sometimes it's kind of hard to tell.
You don't know if I'm doing it right or I'm doing it wrong.
There are eight pairs of differences.
You have to differentiate what's good or what's bad.
The first pair is real goodness and false goodness.
What do you buy, real goodness or false goodness?
There was a group of scholars.
They went to the Zhongfeng monk and asked him,
What is virtue? What is goodness?
And the monk said,
Why don't you guys tell me what is considered good?
All the scholars were like,
Oh, if you're respectful and you're nice, you're polite, that's being good.
If you yell at someone, mean to someone, that's considered bad.
And what did the monk say?
Unnecessary.
And they're like,
So what's the answer?
So what is real goodness?
And then the monk said,
If your intention is to benefit the other person, even if you yell at him, that's considered goodness.
So like the monk is teaching his kid by yelling or some punishment.
That is still what?
Virtue.
That's still goodness.
But if you're trying to flatter your boss and you're very polite, very nice,
that's still considered not good.
Because you're doing it for the selfish reasons.
We have to discern what's real and what's false.
Real is you're doing it for the benefit of others.
False is when you're doing it for your own benefit.
So that's the first pair.
Second pair is called honest and crooked.
This is kind of like the top one.
So honest means you're sincerely wanting to help others.
Some people, they do a lot of good deeds, but they want people to know.
They want to have a good name.
I'm a celebrity.
I want people to know that I am a good person as well.
So you try to flatter people.
That's not really considered goodness.
You want to do it because you really want to help others.
And you don't want any recognition.
You don't want anything in return.
If you want something in return and you're just trying to flatter others, that's not real.
You have to see it in your heart how good you truly are.
You really want to help someone just because you really care about the other person.
So that's the second pair.
The third pair is hidden goodness and visible goodness.
Hidden goodness is when nobody knows.
Sometimes we play with kids, playing games, Monopoly, whatever.
We let them win.
Or you lose to your friends because you want to make them happy, right?
You want your friend to feel better.
That's kind of hidden goodness.
So sometimes you do things without people knowing.
Or people accuse you of things.
Then you don't talk back.
And you don't try to explain yourself.
You just let it be.
That's called hidden goodness.
What's visible goodness?
Visible goodness is everybody knows you're doing well.
Everybody knows that you're virtuous.
When you enjoy the fame itself, that is already a good fortune to receive.
So it's best to do hidden goodness.
Nobody knows.
You don't want to tell anyone.
You go clean the bathroom.
You go do everything for other people without telling everybody that you're doing it.
That's the third pair.
Fourth pair is actual goodness and apparent goodness.
Sometimes it appears to be good, but actually it's not.
Because the longer effect might not be good for the whole society.
For example, Confucius had a student.
His name is Zhigong.
At that time, the country of Liu tried to save the people that's been putting in other countries as slavery.
If you pay for the ransom, you will get a reward from the government.
So Zhigong actually paid for a lot of people.
He paid for the ransom and saved them back.
But he didn't receive the government rewards.
He didn't want them.
Confucius heard about it.
What did he say?
He said, that's not real goodness.
Because you don't take the reward, then everybody will think, well, I'm being greedy if I take the reward.
If you do that, then nobody will go try to save other people because they will be hesitant.
Even if you're rich or you want to appear like you're very good, you shouldn't be doing that.
You should take the reward.
So everyone else will be gladly giving ransom to save our people.
We have to look at the longer effect, not just consider by yourself, but think about the long-term effect for the whole society.
There's another student of Confucius.
His name is Zilu.
One day, he saw a man drowning.
So he went and saved the man.
The man was very grateful, so gave him his cow.
Did Zilu take the cow?
Yes.
He took the cow.
What did Confucius say?
Good.
It's good you took the reward because nobody will hesitate to save other people's lives because you can get rewards.
So sometimes you think not taking stuff is good, but sometimes it's actually good to take the reward.
You have to really think of the long-term effect of whatever you're doing, not just about yourself, but about the society as a whole.
Okay.
So the fifth one is called proper and improper.
Sometimes we think we're doing good, but we're not.
For example, if you're overly polite, is that good?
No.
You know, you might make other people feel uncomfortable when you're doing too much.
Or the kid is very rude and you don't punish the kid.
You're going to make him worse, right?
So sometimes you have to judge, you know, if this is proper or improper.
There was a retired prime minister.
Of the Ming Dynasty.
He retired and went back to his village.
One night there was a drunk villager that came and insulted the prime minister.
The prime minister, he said to his servant, oh don't worry about it.
Just let him go because we don't want to be mean to him.
A year later, that same drunken person, he did a grave crime.
He was sentenced to death.
When the prime minister heard about it, he felt very sad.
He said,
if a year ago I actually punished him and made him know that he was wrong,
maybe he wouldn't do such a crime and now he's on death row.
He felt like he was responsible.
Sometimes you think being kind is proper, but it's actually improper.
It takes a lot of wisdom and a lot of compassion to find out, to know for sure.
The sixth is called full and half.
What's full goodness?
And half goodness.
So my favorite story, there was a lady, she's very, very poor.
But she wants to donate to the temple.
All she has is two cents.
She brought the two cents and gave it to the abbot.
This is all I have, can you please take it?
The abbot was like, wow, you are so sincere.
This is all you have and you're actually giving it away.
So the abbot did a whole ceremony dedicating her marriage for her.
And she was so appreciative.
A year later, she became a concubine.
She became really rich.
She came back to the same temple and now she has lots of money
and she brought boxes of gold into the temple, gave it to the abbot.
The abbot looked at the money and told his little monk,
you can dedicate her marriage for her.
The concubine, she became very upset.
She said, no, a year ago I brought you two cents and you did the whole ceremony for me.
Now I brought all this gold and you tell the little monk to do it.
So the abbot said, before you were wholehearted and sincere.
Now you're very arrogant.
Your heart is not the same.
So your money is not worth the same.
So two cents is full goodness.
Hundreds of thousands of gold pieces is actually half goodness because of your heart.
You have to know for sure.
What's full and what's half.
And the seventh is called big and small.
What's big virtue or big goodness and small goodness.
Zhong Dawei, he's a government official.
One night he was brought to the underworld for judgment.
When he was there, the judge asked to bring the record of all his good deeds and bad deeds to the place.
The bad deeds, the record will fall to the whole Korea.
His good deed was only like a small little chopsticks.
The judge asked to weigh the good deed and the bad deed.
Surprisingly, the good deed, the chopsticks side, actually weighs more than the full Korea of bad deeds.
And he asked the judge, oh, I'm not even 40 years old.
How come I have all these bad deeds?
And the judge said, every one of your thoughts is a deed.
Even if you didn't do it, it's already recorded.
That's why it's full in the whole Korea.
Then he said,
What is the one little good deed that I did?
He said, oh, once the emperor wants to build a bridge.
But it requires thousands of people's hard work.
And you actually wrote something to oppose it.
That was a very good deed.
Because, you know, you're really sincere at the time.
You try to do for the benefit of the whole countrymen.
So what was big, what was small.
Depending on how big your heart is.
He was really sincere in trying to help all the people.
So that one good deed actually was very big.
The last one is called difficult and easy.
There are some things that are difficult for us to give.
For example, some people, they really like money.
So give away money is really hard.
There was a Mr. Chen.
He saw a poor man that was about to go to jail for something that he didn't do.
He wants to help the poor man.
So he actually gave up ten years of his salary to save the poor person from going to jail.
So he doesn't have to be separated from his family.
He's giving up things that's very difficult to give up.
If you want to change your ways, you want to give what's most difficult for you.
If you're really greedy for fame or fortune, then you should give those up.
All these you can tell is not just by the appearance of what's good or what's bad.
It's all on how big your heart is
and how sincerely you want to help all sentient beings to live a happier life.
Today we talked about the eight kinds of good deeds.
And next time, we're going to talk about the second part of cultivating goodness.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you.