Today we are going to start on a series called Fourteen Chapters of Buddhism.
This is actually a book written by Professor Li Bingnan.
He was a Dharma teacher of Master Jing Kong.
He wrote this book in the 1960s to teach college students about Buddhism.
This book has three great qualities.
Number one, it's very complete. It encompasses all of Buddhism as a whole.
Number two, it's very accurate. It's only based on Buddha's actual sutras and teachings.
There's not a word of personal opinion in this book.
Number three, it's very organized.
All of the chapters are systematically ordered and it's made out of charts that are easy to follow and understand.
So today we are going to have an overview of the fourteen chapters.
Chapter One, Meaning of Buddha
When Shakyamuni Buddha first realized Buddhahood, he said,
How amazing! How amazing! All sentient beings have the Buddha nature and can be Buddhas.
It's only because of polluted thinking and attachments
do they fail to realize this and to obtain certification.
So we all have the Buddha nature.
So the first chapter is to establish our goal.
Our goal of learning Buddhism is to reach Buddhahood.
Chapter Two, Eight Basis of Learning Buddhism
We need to analyze everything in eight aspects.
The first three, we need to analyze and know its substance, its form, and its function.
Then we need to know the cause, condition, and the effect.
And then we need to know the practice and the theory.
If you can understand and analyze everything in terms of eight aspects,
then you'll be able to understand all the profound teachings in all the sutras.
Chapter Three is Clearing Up Misconceptions About Buddhism
We might have five kinds of misconceptions about Buddhism.
Number one, we might think Buddhism is superstitious.
We just bow to statues for good luck.
So that's what some people might think.
Number two, we might think Buddhism is very pessimistic.
It's all about death and reincarnation and suffering.
And number three, people might think it's creationism.
Buddha is a god that is creating everything.
Number four, we might think it's unrealistic.
We cannot really practice the teaching in real life.
It's kind of too idealistic.
Number five, we might think it's not very scientific.
All the things that Buddha is talking about, we can't really prove it scientifically.
So if you have these doubts, then you won't be able to really learn Buddhism.
So we need to clear up all the doubts.
And if other people have doubts and questions, you'll be able to answer them.
So these first three chapters, they are the introduction to this book,
if we consider this book as a sutra.
Then chapter four through thirteen,
that's the main body of the sutra.
Chapter fourteen is the transmission, the last chapter of the sutra.
Let's look at the main body of this book.
Chapter four, life is difficult.
First, we need to understand what's our situation right now.
Nobody can escape old age, sickness, and death,
or separation from loved ones, or lose of wealth, or natural disasters.
So we need to understand our situation.
And use Buddhism to resolve our problems.
That's chapter four.
Chapter five, the truth about past, present, and future.
What if we tell you that reincarnation is true,
that you have prior lifetime, and you might not be a human.
This life is only a very short period of time in the whole reincarnation.
And maybe you have many, many future lifetimes of reincarnation.
Maybe it's in the three lower realms.
So we're going to talk about the twelve dependent originations.
So you understand there's twelve links of cause and effect
that is causing the reincarnation.
From ignorance all the way to old age and death.
So that's chapter five.
Chapter four and five is about our life.
Chapter six and seven is about the universe.
Chapter six is about the six realms of reincarnation.
We can be in one of the six realms.
We can be in one of the six places when we are reincarnating.
We might be a heavenly being.
We can be a human or a Shura realm,
which is between heavenly being and human.
Or we can be in the three lower realms.
Animal realm, or we can be a hungry ghost,
or we can be a hell being.
You open up your eyes and realize reincarnation is true.
So we're going to learn a lot of details about the six realms of reincarnation.
Chapter seven is the world system.
We're going to talk about the physical place that we're in.
We call this world three thousand worlds.
It's made out of small world system,
medium size world system,
and large world system.
Our earth is actually only a small dot in this big universe.
So see the truth about our life and the universe.
So chapter four through seven is about our current situation.
Now we are sick in our reincarnation.
So we need the teaching of Buddha,
which is chapter eight through thirteen,
to help us get out of our sickness and cure our disease.
That's the medicine of Buddha.
That is Buddha's teaching and Buddha's Dharma.
Chapter eight is overview of the Dharma.
We need to understand what is Buddha's teaching.
It's basically the three aspects of learning.
Morality, concentration, and wisdom.
Morality is to refrain from doing all that is bad
and do all that is good.
Concentration is for us not to be moved by the outer circumstances.
Wisdom is for us to know the truth about our life and the universe.
So we need to practice the three aspects of learning.
That's the overview of the Dharma.
Chapter nine, that's the five vehicles.
Buddha gives us five general methods to practice Buddhism.
And it's called vehicle because
it's like transportation, like a ferry boat,
transferring us from this shore of reincarnation
to the other shore of enlightenment and nirvana.
These five vehicles will be talked about in chapter ten, eleven, and twelve.
So chapter ten is about the two worldly vehicles.
If you want to be a human again next lifetime,
Buddha will teach you about the five precepts.
No killing, no stealing, no sexual misconduct,
no lying, and no intoxicants.
If you can practice the five precepts well this lifetime,
you might be able to become a human again next lifetime.
And if you want to be a heavenly being,
then Buddha will teach you about the ten wholesome deeds,
which is expansion of the five precepts.
So the human vehicle and the heavenly vehicle,
they are focused on not going to the three lower realms.
At least we don't want to be in the three lower realms.
That is the guarantee.
But if you want to get out of the six realms completely,
then Buddha will teach you about chapter eleven.
If you want to be an art hat,
it's called the shravaka vehicle.
Buddha will teach you about the four noble truths.
Suffering, cause of suffering, cessation of suffering,
and the path to end suffering.
If you really understand the four noble truths,
you can become an art hat and be out of the six realms of incarnation.
Or if you want to be a payaka,
then you will learn the twelve dependent originations.
You will understand the twelve links of interrelated cause and fact relationship
in order for you to understand the truth about how reincarnation works
and what is our reincarnation really about.
So this is actually what we call the Theravada Buddhism.
And if you want to be a bodhisattva,
then we will talk about chapter twelve.
Buddha will teach you the six paramitas.
We should be giving and hold precepts,
and have endurance, diligence, concentration, and wisdom.
So if you want to help all sentient beings,
your main focus is not on going to the Nirvana.
You want to stay with the sentient beings and help them out.
You will risk your life and have the danger of staying in this reincarnation
because you really are compassionate about saving and helping
all sentient beings.
So everybody needs to actually learn all the five vehicles.
You need to use them skillfully,
depending on your problem and your situation.
For example, if I'm having anger right now,
I can use the worldly vehicles of ten wholesome deeds.
I will say, okay, I should hold the precepts.
I will have no anger.
Or I can use the Four Noble Truths.
Anger is a cause of suffering,
and there's actually not a me being offended,
so I should let go of my anger.
So that's using the Four Noble Truths.
Or you can use the six pyramidas.
I am a bodhisattva.
I should be tolerant to all people,
so I should let go of my anger.
So use all the five dharmas, all the five vehicles,
skillfully and selectively.
But you need to learn all of them.
And Chapter 13 is a special vehicle,
which is Pure Land Buddhism.
This is about chanting Amitabha Buddha's name.
Why is it called a special vehicle?
Because it's different from the five general vehicles.
The five general vehicles is basically your own practice.
It's relying on your own strength
to practice morality, concentration, and wisdom.
But if you chant Amitabha Buddha's name,
it's relying on Amitabha Buddha's power,
along with your own practice.
So every time you chant Buddha's name,
it's like Buddha is giving us
all his merits to us freely.
We are now born in the royalty,
so our success in this life is guaranteed.
So once you chant Buddha's name,
you are guaranteed to be out of the six dharma incarnations
and very quickly.
So that's the special vehicle,
the expedient means.
Lastly, in Chapter 14,
it's about vigilance.
We need to have really strong awareness.
We should really think about this lifetime.
We really want to go through reincarnation again.
What if there's really reincarnation?
Buddha says the chance of us being a human again
next lifetime is extremely slim.
Usually, we are in the three lower rounds.
And if you really know that practicing the dharma
will make you go out of the sixth round,
wouldn't you practice really hard?
And if you know that you can become a Buddha,
wouldn't you spend all your time chanting Buddha's name,
learning the dharma,
so have vigilance and feel the urgency to practice.
Right now, we don't feel any urgency
because we don't see reincarnation.
We feel like this is the only life,
is this existence, but it's not.
You know, we have many, many, many lifetimes to come.
We need to work on our cultivation
of the few years that we have left as a human being.
We should really practice
and don't waste our life away.
Okay, so this is the overview of the 14 chapters.
And next time, we are going to start on chapter one,
the meaning of Buddha.
So thank you for listening. AmitÄbha.