Today we are going to talk about the Four Mindfulness.
Buddha teaches us to be mindful of our body, feelings, mind and Dharma.
Before we go into the mindfulness, let's first talk about the Four Noble Truths,
Buddha's basic Dharma wheel.
First, we should know that we are going through suffering right now
because we are still in samsara, we are still reincarnating.
So that is the result of our life right now.
We have our causes of suffering.
What is causing our reincarnation is not other people,
it's our own afflictions, our greed, anger and ignorance that's causing the samsara.
We learn Buddhism so we can reach the cessation of suffering.
There should be no more reincarnation and we can reach Nirvana.
Number four, the path to end suffering.
So the Four Mindfulness is the path to end suffering.
We are suffering because we have these four upside down views about these four fundamentals.
First, we think our body is pure.
That's why we love our body, we take care of it, we want it to be beautiful and healthy.
But Buddha teaches us to be mindful that our body is impure.
Everything that comes out of our body is dirty, including our mucus, our saliva, our urine, our feces.
Nothing that comes out of our body is pure.
If we know it's impure, we won't be so attached to it.
And we can let go.
We should let go our attachment to the body.
Our second view is we think our feelings is all happiness.
Everything that we're pursuing in the world, we think will make us happy.
But know that all happiness is condition arising.
When it ends, it's no longer happiness, it becomes suffering.
So the reality is that all feelings are suffering.
We should let go of our upside down view.
That the feeling is blissfulness.
Number three, we are attached to our mind.
We think our mind is permanent.
The thing that's on our mind right now, we think it's such a big deal.
It's worrying us and we're feeling this anxiety.
Everything is so real, but our mind is truly impermanent.
Number four, the object of our mind, we call it the Dharma, all worldly things.
We think there is a selfhood.
We think there is a me, there's an ego that is controlling everything.
These four are the upside down views about our body, feelings, mind, and Dharma.
That's why Buddha teaches us to have four mindfulness to end the suffering by contemplating
on the reality, which are the opposite from the upside down view.
During meditation and during everyday life, see clearly.
The reality, everything is impure, suffering, impermanent, and non-self.
Then we will reach enlightenment and we will cease all sufferings.
This is the basic for mindfulness according to the Four Noble Truths.
According to the Tiantai Buddhism of Master Zhi Yi, he categorized all Shakyamuni Buddha's
teaching into four.
These four doctrines of conversion.
Number one is the Tripitaka teaching, that's the Theravada Buddhism, which focuses on getting
out of the suffering by practicing this basic for mindfulness from samsara to nirvana.
They focus all their attention on getting rid of their defilements and their four upside
down views.
This is called the right view.
They are rising and seizing four noble truths.
Samsara and nirvana are very real.
In this case, it's really rising and really seizing to the Theravada Buddhist.
However, number two, common teaching.
This common means common to the Theravada Buddhism and common to the Mahayana Buddhism.
There is actually a common teaching which is Prajna.
of emptiness emptiness is the reality because samsara and nirvana are actually the same they
are both empty in nature there is no self nature to samsara or nirvana both are like in the dream
one is a nightmare one is a good dream that's all when you practice the four mindfulness stand in
the point of view of the emptiness of all things it becomes easier it's like your ego you see the
big picture and when you practice in this world it's much easier to get rid of your defilement
so it's called the non-arising for noble truth there is no real samsara real nirvana everything
is emptiness we should see the truth and nothing really
arises nothing really ceases it's all conditioned and that is all number three
is distinctive teaching this is especially tailored toward bodhisattvas they practice
to save and deliver all sentient beings they have the strong bodhi resolve to help all sentient
beings out of reincarnation so the four noble truth is called immeasurable four noble truths
all sentient beings in the ten dharma rounds everyone has their suffering they have their
different body mind and dharma so we respect everybody's differences and we use the suffering
of this lifetime to transform ourselves into a bodhisattva and to benefit all sentient beings
if our body is sick we do not dwell on it we think oh because of my sickness
i really feel the pain of all sentient beings i wish all sentient beings will be free from sickness
so we're using this impurity of the body to become a bodhisattva when we are experiencing
different kind of sufferings and obstacles we use the suffering and change our mind
our mind can create a different world if we just appreciate and be thankful we can change the
world we can use this challenge to develop our leadership skill to change the situation for the
better so a bodhisattva is always using the sufferings of this lifetime to develop even
further to practice their six pyramidas they also know the impermanence of their mind because the
mind is impermanent we can change it so we think like a buddha we do everything like a buddha because
it's impermanent that means we can change our thinking from our mundane person that is always
stressed or having a lot of craving into a real bodhisattva that is always having the heart of
the dharma a bodhisattva will see that everything in the world there is not a self instead they
think everybody all the dharma around is me we are actually one in this world together
there is nothing better than feeling the oneness of the entire universe bodhisattva they have
immeasurable heart they love all sentient beings and they use this body feeling mind and dharma
to cultivate into a real bodhisattva number four is the complete teaching this is the
second enlightenment teaching complete means we are all complete
the mind is the buddha we should have faith that we are exactly the same as all achieve buddha even
though we have a lot of upside down views right now but these can all be changed in one instant
when we awaken to know illusion is to depart from it to depart from illusion is to be enlightened
just one instant that we awaken to our true nature we are really the buddha
there is no suffering to end because samsara is the same as nirvana in our buddha nature and
there is no affliction to eradicate because all afflictions are in nature the same as bodhi so
when you have this type of wisdom understanding that you are truly the mind of the buddha you have
infinite potential every time you to be enlightened that is the ultimate enlightenment
breath even though it's impure is the buddha that is breathing even though there is suffering
but suffering is nirvana even though my mind is impermanent it has an eternal nature that never
changes or moves when we get rid of our ego that's our true nature the buddha that's full of
infinite wisdom and infinite compassion when a person really knows his true nature there's
nothing that is of any obstruction there is no more resistance in his or her life
so that is the complete teaching which is called the non-doing for noble truth not doing because
you are already the buddha you don't need to cultivate the four mindfulness so hard
because you are already the buddha and you don't need to cultivate the four mindfulness so hard
because you are already the buddha you don't need to cultivate the four mindfulness so hard
because you already know they are the same.
All you have to do is wake up
and know that you have the true nature.
Lastly, I would like to share a story.
There is a village of 500 monkeys.
499 monkeys all have only one eye.
Only one monkey has two eyes.
Everybody think he is a weirdo
and despise him, make fun of him.
So he grew up very depressed and have low self-esteem.
But one day he decided to leave the village.
Once he left the village, he went into the forest.
Much to his surprise, he saw other monkeys.
All the other monkeys have two eyes.
Then he said, so I'm not the weird one.
I'm actually normal.
After he realized that, he became so happy
and he lived happily ever after.
We all have two eyes.
That means we all have the Buddha nature.
Our mind is the Buddha.
There is actually no upside down view.
There's no samsara that is hurting us right now.
All we have to do is to wake up
and know our true nature.
Then we live happily ever after.
That is the complete and perfect teaching.
Buddha wants us to live happily ever after.
Buddha wants us to reach this level of wisdom.
Whatever you practice, you will succeed in your practice.
So even with this complete teaching,
you are still doing the fundamental for mindfulness.
It's not that you don't have to cultivate anymore.
It's just that you start at the highest point.
Your starting point is you are the Buddha.
So that is the fastest and the quickest way to reach enlightenment.
So that's the point.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.