Today we will talk about 9 stages of meditation.
How do we know if we are improving in our meditation?
There are actually standards we can use to evaluate our progress.
In this class we will learn about 9 stages of meditation in order to evaluate and improve our meditation.
Now let's look at the 9 stages.
Number 1 is placement.
This means placing our mind inward instead of going outward seeking external conditions.
This is the first step because our mind likes to wander off.
Now we want to bring it inward and focus on the designated object of meditation such as your breathing,
such as the name Amitabha or a visualization.
So these are all good objects of meditation to train our mind to focus inward.
What is the secret of being able to place our mind inward?
During our daily lives we should always keep a reserve between our mind and the external condition.
Know that everything you are experiencing are not as real as you seem and always keep a distance.
That way when you sit down to meditate
you will be ready to place your mind.
Number 2 is continuous placement.
Now we brought it inward.
We want this focus to be continuous for a period of time.
For example, focus on the name Amitabha for 5 minutes without any wandering thoughts.
That's already very good.
At this time we are not too familiar with the meditation
but we are training ourselves to have this focus,
concentration for a long period of time.
Number 3 is replacement.
When our mind wanders off we bring it back immediately.
We establish placement with the object of meditation.
A meditator must be very patient.
Whenever it runs off again we bring it back.
The key is strong awareness and perseverance.
Number 4 is close placement.
By this time the object of meditation is very close to your mind
and the scattered thoughts are frozen.
They are further away from you.
We are skilled at meditation.
We can focus and we are near stabilization.
The first 4 are all placement
which means they are tranquility meditation
to train our mind to focus and concentrate.
Number 5 through 8 is inside meditation
to deal with our afflictions and problems.
Number 9 is a combination of tranquility meditation and inside meditation.
Number 5 is tamed mind.
We need to tame our mind of our desires.
Here it talks about 10 desires.
The first 5 are our attachment to the 5 sensory organs.
We like to be attached to form, sound, smell, taste and touch.
These are the 5 sensory organs.
But they are actually deceiving us
and they are actually disadvantages to our deliverance.
We have the 3 poisons.
We have the sense of greed, anger, ignorance,
also our lust for men and women.
These are the 10 desires we need to tame our mind
and reprimand them at this stage.
For example, I can say to myself,
Tracy, wake up.
What else do you want?
Death is coming.
That worked for me.
But everybody has their own way of reprimanding their desires.
That way your mind would be tamed.
Number 6, pacified mind.
Tamed mind is more on external desires.
Pacified mind is working on our internal hindrances
such as the 5 hindrances that's covering our true Buddha nature.
So these 5 are greed, anger, drowsiness, restlessness and doubt.
Our greed is our wholesome mind burned by the fire of craving.
Anger is actually enemy of Dharma joy
and rob us of our good heart.
Drowsiness, being lethargic.
It's actually really hard to detect.
Some people can mistaken this drowsiness as deep meditation.
So it's very subtle and hard to eradicate.
Number 4 is our restlessness.
It's actually wasting our time on a lot of false thinking.
It's like a mad elephant that is unhooked.
Number 5 is our doubt.
Being skeptical and confused.
This is the evil of mind.
It's the evil of all evil.
So these 5 hindrances we need to use inside meditation
to conquer them at this stage.
Number 7, complete pacification.
By this stage, all the growths, afflictions and problems
are pretty much conquered.
Your mind is pretty at peace.
Any kind of obstacles comes in
which means you take something bad,
you immediately spit it out, gets rid of them.
So by this stage,
you are pretty safe.
You already reach a good state of your meditation.
Number 8 is single-pointedness.
This is basically smooth sailing.
So there's no more obstacles.
All you need is a little bit of effort.
Number 9 is balanced placement.
This time you have reached samadhi
or meditative absorption.
This time is easy, effortless and natural for you.
So these are the 9 stages of meditation.
As you can see,
the meditation is a skillful means of enlightenment.
In the Shraggama Sutra,
it talks about Maitreya Bodhisattva.
At that time, there was a Buddha
named the Light of Sun Moon Lamp.
During that time,
Maitreya Bodhisattva left home and became a monk,
but he was deeply attached to worldly fame.
He liked to associate with prestigious families.
But the Buddha taught him conscious-only meditation.
So he went into conscious-only samadhi,
and he realized that the world,
pure or defiled,
they are all just transformations
appearing from our own consciousness.
All his seeking for worldly fame
completely ceased and never occurred again.
He realized that everything is conditioned existence
originated from consciousness only.
That's when he reached his ultimate goal.
He found his enlightenment
and found his true Buddha nature.
Through meditation,
that's the only way for us to be awakened.
Furthermore,
we have 6 corresponding powers
that will help us reach the 9 levels.
The first one is the power of study
in order to reach the placement stage.
Study, listen to the Dharma,
and really believe in the Dharma.
For example,
we know who Amitabha is,
and by chanting his name,
that's the only way for us to be
out of reincarnation forever.
So you fire up your motivation and zeal
to chant his name and meditate.
Number 2 is the power of contemplation
in order to reach the continuous placement.
Contemplate on the Dharma.
What does it mean to me,
to this lifetime?
Why do I need to chant wholeheartedly?
Because I really want to be out of reincarnation.
This should be my last lifetime.
So contemplate on it.
Focus your whole attention on your practice.
Number 3 is the power of recollection
in order to reach replacement and close placement.
The power of recollection is remembering.
Always remembering the name Amitabha.
Remembering your practice.
Like a mother always remember her child,
or a child always remember his or her mother.
So this remembrance is very strong.
By having this strong remembering,
we never forget our meditation.
Number 4 is the power of comprehension
in order to reach the tamed and pacified mind.
Comprehend, which means prajna.
We have wisdom of emptiness.
Just like Maitreya Bodhisattva,
he understand conscious only
and know that all existence are not real.
They are made by the mind.
Everything is arising by the mind.
It ceases by the mind.
It's like a mirage and transformation.
It's like the image in the mirror.
It's like the reflection of the moon in the water.
So none of it is real.
When you have that kind of comprehension and wisdom,
it will be easy to tame and pacify
your afflictions and desires.
Number 5 is the power of diligence
in order to reach complete pacification
and single pointedness.
By this time, when you have no obstacle,
you just need to be diligent.
It's like you're already on the freeway.
You just have to keep going toward your destination.
The complete pacification
is when you can meditate for 7 to 8 hours.
And the single pointedness
is when you can meditate 24 hours a day.
So it takes a lot of diligence
in order to be good at meditation.
Number 6 is the power of perfection
in order to reach balanced placement.
So the power of perfection
becomes a habituation
of complete focus and concentration.
This is the real samadhi
of the world of desire.
Furthermore, we also need 4 attentions.
Number 1 is forceful attention.
For the first 2 placements,
we need to be forceful
because in the beginning,
it's very difficult.
We need to have a lot of willpower
and give it a lot of energy
in order to start meditating.
Stages 3 to 7,
we have disturbed attention.
We know we have obstacles
and disturbances.
But we know that we keep
this disturbed attention.
We can still progress
when there's a lot of interruptions
and obstacles.
Number 3 is undisturbed attention.
By this time,
there's not much interruption
to your meditation.
So you just need to work hard
and keep going.
Number 4 is spontaneous attention.
This time is natural focused mind
that is effortless and easy.
That's the overview of meditation.
We need to understand
and evaluate our own practice.
Where are we right now?
And what can we do to improve?
This is something we can all do.
We can all reach the balanced placement
if we just work at it.
In the sutra, it says
all Buddhas gain liberation
through the cultivation of the mind.
The mind is originally
pure, clear, and undefiled.
It might reincarnate
in the five realms of existence,
but it remains fresh
and unpolluted by any form.
For those who comprehend this,
it will indeed achieve the Great Path.
All Buddhas gain enlightenment
through meditation,
which is the cultivation of the mind.
No matter how long we've been reincarnating
in the five realms,
our mind is always pure
and unpolluted.
By understanding this
and keep meditating,
we'll definitely reach
the Great Path of Buddhahood.
So that's the class for today.
Thank you for listening.
Amitabha.