Today we're going to keep talking about the Ten Great Vows of Universal Worthy Bodhisattva.
He is the symbol of all Bodhisattva because his heart is immeasurably broad and full of
love and compassion.
So he is the symbol of all great Bodhisattva.
He has ten great vows and last time we did the first four and now we're going to do five,
six and seven.
Number five is to rejoice over others' meritorious deeds.
This is to conquer our problem of jealousy.
Everybody feels jealousy sometimes, even little kids.
Now why are we jealous of others?
We're usually jealous of our peers, like our siblings or our classmates or our co-workers.
We usually are not jealous of our parents or people that are really young.
We want to be the best.
We want to be best among our peers.
In order to conquer that defilement, we need to feel rejoice, be happy for other people's
success.
Why?
Because everyone is Buddha.
Everybody is one entity.
Everybody is together as one.
Everyone has two rights.
When you realize what you have and do whatever you have to do, you move.
You move forward.
Now we gotta try to become one of all who is on the nieces and nephews of great people
of
Buddha.
So before we go on to the next verse.
One part is business and another part is爱.
The other part means the quality of life.
and it's part of anger. You'll never be happy. So in order to be happy, we want to be happy for
others. Their success is my success. When they're doing well, that means I'm doing well. So be happy
for others. In our Chinese history, the Chao dynasty is the longest dynasty. It lasted 800
years. Why? Because they use love and compassion and rejoice for others as their principle for
leading the country. There's an emperor and three sons. And the older son and the second oldest son,
they know that the father wants to give the throne to the third son. But usually you give the throne
to the oldest. So one day they just told emperor with dad, we are going to go to the mountain to
get you some herbal medicine. So they went up to the mountain, they never came back. They just left.
So naturally the father gave the throne,
gave the throne to the third son and the third son gave to his son who became a great emperor.
And that's why the Chao dynasty lasted 800 years, because they're always kind and sharing,
letting other people have their way without ever fighting for things. We want to be compassionate
and rejoice for other people's success. That's a bodhisattvas way, the sixth is to request the
turning of the Dharma wheel. What's requesting the turning of Dharma wheel? The Dharma wheel is the
the turning of the Dharma wheel it's like what you're doing right now when
you're listening to the Dharma teaching that's requesting the turning of the
Dharma wheel Dharma is Buddha's teaching why do we call it the Dharma because the
Dharma is like a wheel when you roll over something that means you roll over
all your defilements such as jealousy or anger or greediness you roll over so you
get rid of all your problems okay so that's what Dharma is for so by
listening to the Dharma you are requesting it how do you request it you
just keep doing and learning the Dharma and use it in your daily life
so in the Lotus Sutra it says in order to teach the Lotus Sutra you must do
three things what are the three things in your everyday life this is what you
do you have to enter the Buddha's room you have to where
you are
you have to wear
the buddha's clothes you have to sit in buddha's seat what does that mean buddha's room what's
inter buddha's room buddha's room is great compassion his room his heart is full of
compassion for other not jealous for other but always compassionate full of love okay so that's
buddha's room and we should also wear buddha's clothes every day we get up and we wear clothes
what kind of clothes do we wear we should wear the clothes of tolerance and perseverance that's
buddha's clothing now be tolerant of others not be jealous no matter what other people do to us
we don't get angry no we let them be and be kind and compassionate so have tolerance and
perseverance that's buddha's clothing the third is called see sit in buddha's seats what's the buddha
see buddha see is the truth about emptiness emptiness is the truth about emptiness emptiness
emptiness means letting go of the idea of the self everything is forever changing there is not
an idea called me that you should have an ego for or be attached to you should let go of all
your attachments about things that way you can have true great compassion you have true tolerance
and perseverance only when you sit in the sea of emptiness that's your wisdom so everywhere
day we should do these three things that is turning the dharma wheel the third is to request
that the buddhas remain in the world chakramoni buddha was on this earth in india 2600 years ago
he is no longer here what do we mean by requesting the buddha to remain in the world how do we make
the buddha remain in the world by practicing his dharma if you practice his dharma you're requesting
him to live in this world so by you cultivating and practicing that's requesting his presence
right now in your heart there's a great story when chakramoni buddha was alive one time he was
going to the heaven to teach his mom about buddhism because his mom is in heaven so he went
up to heaven for three months and when he was about to come back everybody knew oh by chakramoni
buddha is coming back so all his disciples and everybody they
were like oh my god he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back
he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back he's coming back
try to be the first one to greet him when he comes back so everybody's trying really hard
to be the first one to see him one of his students so bhuti he he was in his cave meditating he has
psychic power so he knew that buddha was coming back he said to himself should i go fight with
everybody to see buddha first or should i stay in my cave and meditate about emptiness because
he is supposed to be the one that understands emptiness the most he realized for himself
i shouldn't go fight to be the first one to see buddha i should just remain in my cave and meditate
so that's exactly what he did he stayed in his cave and meditate on emptiness at the same time
there was a nun she really wanted to be the first one to see buddha but she's a woman most likely she
won't be the first one but she has very strong supernatural power so she transformed into a king
so the king has the right to see buddha first and then she
bowed to the buddha as the king bowed to buddha buddha knew that was the nun and you know what
buddha said to her he said you are not the one that saw me first who saw me first saw buddhi
why because he really received my dharma about emptiness you don't need to go to find your
spiritual guru or find people to help you you have the dharma inside your heart and buddha
is alive so through teaching of buddha's emptiness inside your heart detach from the idea of the ego
and the self and let your great compassion come out then that's the bodhisattva way so today we
learned three things first is to rejoice over other people's marital seas the second is to
request the turning of the dharma wheel the third is to request that the buddha remain in the world
so next time we're gonna finish
that's it for today thank you for listening omitofo