Today we are going to talk about
uplifting our mind.
The reason we are meditating is to train our mind
to be in a state of happiness and calmness.
Everybody wants to be happy,
but how do we train our mind?
In the Sutra, we actually have five specific ways
to uplift our mind.
The blue are the direct translation,
the pink is the Chinese writing,
and the black is mind interpretation,
for you to remember it.
So the first is called skill for desires.
How do you change your life to be better?
First, you've got to have a desire to do so.
How come our life is like this right now?
If you're not happy about it,
what can you do to change it?
First, you've got to have a desire,
I want to make my life better.
If this is not the life that you want,
you should have a longing,
I want to make it better.
It's not by changing the outside world,
it's by changing your mind to think positive,
then you can make your life much better.
So first, have a great desire to be better.
I don't know if you've heard of Roger Bannister.
He's a neurologist.
He's also a runner.
In 1954, scientists told everybody,
nobody can run the mile under four minutes.
So everybody thought it's impossible
because our body is impossible
to run a mile under four minutes.
Roger, he said to himself,
I am going to set a goal.
I'm going to run the mile
less than four minutes.
On May 6th of 1954,
he did it.
He did the mile in 3 minutes and 59 seconds.
And guess what?
46 days after that,
someone else did it too.
And then a couple months later,
more people did it.
Did everybody's body change?
No.
It's what?
It's the mind.
Then people start running the mile under four minutes.
The miracle is created by our own goal setting
and we want to do it.
If you have the desire to do it,
you can do anything.
First, have a skillful desire
to change your life to be better.
The second is right effort.
You set your goal,
you've got to work hard at it.
You've got to be diligent.
That's why we have to meditate.
This diligence is not just keep meditating.
Meditating is just a short period of time.
The true diligence is when you're constantly
watching your mind.
Be aware of your thoughts.
Constantly aware.
What am I thinking?
Am I being positive?
Am I living the life that I want?
So always think of thoughts
that would be beneficial to you.
By diligent,
I mean focusing on each breath.
Each breath.
So every inhale,
every exhale,
you've got to be diligent
to be positive.
Even when you're not meditating,
you're at work,
you're doing anything,
can you focus on your breath
and be mindful?
What am I doing today?
Is this what I want to do?
Am I doing this right?
Am I living on purpose?
Be diligent with every breath.
And the third is right mindfulness.
With diligence,
you will be mindful.
Be mindful of what?
Be mindful of positive thinking.
Are you mindful of how you think?
All of us,
we have a mode of thinking.
We have a way of thinking.
And a lot of us,
we have very negative thoughts.
I'm not good enough.
I'm not pretty enough.
I'm not good at this.
I'm horrible.
I can't do this.
A lot of us have a lot of patterns
of negative thinking
and we are not even aware of it.
So be mindful.
The right mindfulness
means you got to stay positive all the time.
How you think is what you create for yourself.
It's how your life will be.
So thinking positively all the time
is actually the way of true deep concentration
or true samadhi,
as we call it,
deep meditation.
You should be mindful all the time.
Then you'll be able to change the reality
you're living in.
Especially,
you can change your body.
There was a man that he had terminal illness.
He was on his deathbed in the hospital.
He thought he was going to die soon.
One night,
he had a dream.
He dreamt,
someone told him,
the tree outside of your window,
when all the leaves are gone,
that would be your last day.
That would be your last day.
So he woke up very sad outside the window.
There's a tree with a few leaves.
And then a very kind doctor came in
and asked him what was wrong.
He said,
oh, I had this dream.
And the doctor said,
oh, not to worry.
A few days later,
there was a big storm.
So at night,
he was really worried.
He said,
oh, next morning,
there's going to be no leaves left.
It's going to be my last day.
And the next morning,
guess what?
The nice doctor came in
and then he said,
hey, look,
there's a whole bunch of leaves still hanging there.
That means you're going to have a miracle.
Something's going to happen to you.
Your disease will have a turn point.
You're going to get better.
After that day,
because he believed in it,
he kept getting better.
And,
he was cured.
And he left the hospital.
How did this happen?
Because he believed.
He used his thoughts to be positive
and he changed his body
and changed his life.
Why this story is so touching?
Because the doctor
actually glued those leaves on.
Yeah, it's not real.
Because the doctor's being nice
because he knew it was going to fall off.
But, you know,
he glued it on.
So,
you're not going to die.
You're going to stay positive at all times.
And that will make you
have a very different life.
The fourth one is
skillful insight.
Insight means wisdom.
Do you have the wisdom
to lead a happy life?
Wisdom means the ability to choose.
Do I choose to be positive
or do I choose to be negative?
Do I choose to think I live in a world
that's hostile
and everybody is mean to me
or do I choose to live in a world
choose to live in a world that everybody is in harmony and likes me then you will be living in
a different world there's a lumberjack he has a axe one day he lost it he doesn't know where he
left it so he was looking at the neighbor's kid this boy he's like oh he looked very suspicious
i think he stole it so every day so this few days he kept thinking the boy stole my axe he saw the
boy talking to his mom and he's like oh they must be thinking of how to sell my axe for money you
know for money the more he thought about the more upset he was you know it ruined his life one day
again he went to the forest by the river he found his axe so was this stolen by the boy
no but at this whole time he kept thinking the boy stole it so if you can change your way to be wise
and not be foolish
you can live a much better life by thinking positive okay the fifth one is single-mindedness
actually all five they kind of go together the more desire you have the more you put in effort
the more mindful you are the more wisdom you have the more you will be determined you'll be getting
better at it because you're fully concentrated on your goal this is full determination on how i want
to make my life better this determination
you want to make your life better you want to make your life better you want to make your life better
you want to make sure you are very firm in what you believe believe it wholeheartedly your heart is
like a diamond nobody can shake you like you burn a diamond it's still a diamond your belief should
be as strong as the diamond there was a lady in singapore she lived to be a hundred and fourteen
she's like the oldest asian lady that ever lived she never learned how to read or write until 47.
she wanted to be a nurse so i want to help people
i want to be a nurse so at 47 she went to oxford university and got her nursing degree ever since
then she became the greatest social worker when she was like 100 something she established a
senior home for seniors that much younger than her so she lived to be 114 and she said my role
model for life is i have no religion love is my religion i don't care who the person is i love
everybody and that's why i'm a nurse i'm a nurse i'm a nurse i'm a nurse i'm a nurse i'm a nurse
that's why she was determined to contribute her life to the society and that's why she lived a
great life up to 114. your determination really makes up who you are that's the fifth way to
uplift your mind so there are five ways to do that and hope everybody will remember
and change your life for the better okay so that's a class for today thank you thank you