Today we are going to talk about
Liao Fan's fourth lesson, the fourth lesson.
The fourth lesson is the benefits of the virtue of humility.
You want to change your destiny, change all your bad ways and do all that is good, but
you want to keep your virtues, you have to stay humble.
Humbleness is a virtue.
If you can stay humble, you will keep your prosperity and your good fortune.
This lesson, we're going to learn how to be humble based on what Liao Fan's experienced.
In the book of I Ching, he actually told us a lot of goodness of being humble.
The laws of heaven take from the arrogant and benefit the humble.
The heaven likes people that are humble.
They take away from the people that are arrogant and give to people that are humble.
So we want to stay down to earth and respectful and not to boast about ourselves or accomplishment
or anything that we have.
And we want to be humble.
That's the first step.
The second step is the law of the earth.
The law of the earth is that the earth brings flowing water from the areas that are full
to those that are lower as it passes by.
When you're too high, that means the water is full.
The earth always brings the water down to the people that are humble.
That means at lower places.
The earth will benefit you and bring the water to you because you are being humble.
So that's the third.
The third is the law of spirits bringing water to you.
That's the third.
bring harm to those who are arrogant and good fortune to those who are modest so
that the heavenly beings the spirits they actually can see our heart and see
our every action if you're arrogant they actually will hurt you you have bad luck
the bad thing will happen to you for no reason but if you stay humble and modest
you will get a lot of good fortune from the spirits spirit will help you out
because you've been very modest and lastly the loss of people despise those
who are arrogant and prefer those who are modest even in our world people
don't like to hang out with people that are very arrogant
you're always bragging about yourself nobody wants to be your friend because
you're so fool of yourself even the loss of people despite those who are arrogant
and prefer those who are mining so the Heaven
the Earth
the spirit people they all prefer people that are humble and don't like those that are very arrogant
their arrogance invites disaster humility gains benefit if you're arrogant you invite trouble for
yourself okay if you're humble then you gain a lot of good things good thing will happen to you
naturally okay so liao fan now tells about a couple of his friends at his time there was a
person named jing yu ding he went to take the imperial exam with liao fan so there were 10
of them all went to take the test out of the 10 of them they're the youngest who is jing yu he's
the only one that's very modest when people insult him slander him he doesn't talk back
he just accepts whatever the accusation liao fan said this person
would be the only person that will pass the test and sure enough out of that 10 jing yu was the only
one who passed the test that year then the second person liao fan's childhood friend kai zi feng now
they're older liao fan said when kai zi was young he was very very arrogant but now he's grown up
he's actually become very mild and humble and respectful one of his friends always like to
accuse him and scold him of all his mistakes
but
he never talks back he just calmly accepts all the accusations and never says anything so liao
fan said he will be the person that will pass the test and sure enough kai zi passed the test that
year there was a third person he passed the preliminary test when he was very young but
for the life of him he couldn't pass the second level he wrote very good essay but he still
couldn't pass and one year his dad went to a different province to take a government
post so he went with his dad over there there's a very famous scholar so he brought his essay to
show the scholar the scholar actually destroyed made a lot of correction on his essay he
respectfully accepts all the correction and he made all the changes and sure enough that year he
passed the exam not the imperial exam okay so that's the third person and liao fan talks about
a fourth person he has a really good essay and then the first person who passed the writing exam
came out he's also like a regular student and and he padded back with a very good Milky Way like page
and he came to university on a nose job yayayayayaya and exactly that way no more process and then the third
but he's very arrogant so that year the test result came out he didn't pass the
test and start screaming he said the examiner must be blind couldn't see my
real talent he started screaming and yelling and there was a Taoist monk
walked by and started laughing at him he redirected his anger toward the monk he
said why are you laughing monk said you must not write very good essays and he
said how do you know you haven't even seen my essay and the monk says in order
to write good essay you must have good temperament you must have a peaceful
mind with your anger and you must not write very good essay and then he said
how can I start passing the test what can I do to change my life the monk said
you know from now on you should be humble and change your way cultivate
good deeds you will pass the exam then he said how can I do good deeds I'm
just a poor student monk says you know being humble that doesn't cost any money
that is hidden virtue that is already very good deed so from that day on he
controlled himself had great discipline and so he did that for three years one
night he had a dream he went to the underworld he saw someone with this
booklet this booklet had a lot of names and some blank spaces he asked the
person next to him what is this book he said oh this book is all the
people that's going to pass the Imperial exam this year the blank spaces
are people that didn't do good deeds so their name has been erased you on the
other hand these three years you have been doing really well so your name is
going to fill one of the blank spaces and sure enough after he had that dream
he passed the exam that year so all these people by being humble actually
attract good fortune but you don't want good fortune and
it's better to do good deeds just for yourself it's better that you want it
for the entire world you want to benefit of the whole society
Mencius told an emperor that it's great that you love music but you loving music
is just a personal pleasure if you can put this love of music for all the
people in your country and make them happy as well your whole country will be
prosperous
always improve themselves so this lifetime if you stay humble and virtuous
you will do a lot more and you can benefit the entire world that's it for
the Liao Fanzhou lesson and next time we will talk about something else
thank you for listening